<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cure of preivdice, or, The doves of innocency and the serpents subtilty wherein the originall, continuance, properties, causes, endes, issue and effects of the worlds envie and hatred to the godly is pithily laid open and applyed. By R. Junius.</title>
            <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 239 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y149B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230928</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899503</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899503</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153780</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97247)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153780)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2378:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cure of preivdice, or, The doves of innocency and the serpents subtilty wherein the originall, continuance, properties, causes, endes, issue and effects of the worlds envie and hatred to the godly is pithily laid open and applyed. By R. Junius.</title>
                  <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 122 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by I.B. and are to be sold by James Crump, at his house in Well-Yard in little S. Bartholmews,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R. Junius = Richard Younge.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prejudices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153780:1"/>
            <p>The Cure of PREIVDICE, <hi>Or,</hi> The <hi>Doves</hi> Innocency and the <hi>Serpents</hi> ſubtilty, wherein The
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Originall,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Continuance,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Properties,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cauſes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Endes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſſue</hi> and <hi>Effects</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> of the worlds Envie and hatred to the Godly</p>
            <p>Is pithily laid open and applyed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. Junius.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GEN. 3.15.</hi>
               </bibl> I will put Enmity between thee and the Woman, and betweene thy ſeed and her ſeede: it ſhall bruiſe thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PRO. 29.27.</hi>
               </bibl> A wicked man is Abomination to the Juſt, and he that is upright in his way, is Abomination to the wicked.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. B.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>James Crump,</hi> at his houſe in Well-Yard in little S. <hi>Bartholmews,</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:153780:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153780:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving peruſed this firſt part of the Cure of Prejudice, we finde it to containe a lively deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that enmity and hatred which the wicked beare to Gods people, together with a perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous diſcovery of the grounds &amp; reaſons of it, laid down pith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ily, orderly and elegantly, with much both ſinew ous ſtrength of argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and variety of grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:153780:3"/>&amp; delightful Illuſtration: The which, through Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing accompanying it, is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to prove of much uſe to all ſorts that shall read the ſame, whether in comforting the godly in their ſufferings, or in reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, or (at leaſt) convincing ſuch as any way oppoſe the way of truth: So that whatſoever time, labour &amp; diligence thou shalt ſpend in often reading it, we doubt not but the profit will recompence thy paines abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>GEORGE WALKER.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>EDM. CALAMY.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>IOSEPH CARYLL.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153780:3"/>
            <head>THE CVRE OF PREJUDICE: OR The DOVES Innocency, and the SERPENTS Subtilty; wherein The
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Originall,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Continuance,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Properties,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cauſes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ends,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſſue and Effect,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> 
               <hi>of the Worlds En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie and Hatred to the Godly,</hi> is pithily laid open and applied, by way of <hi>Queſtion</hi> and <hi>Anſwer,</hi> between a weake and an experienced Chriſtian.</head>
            <p>Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow is it, that the practice of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity is every where ſpoken againſt, under the name of Schiſme, as the chiefe Jewes told</hi> Paul <hi>in his time?</hi> Acts 28.22. <hi>And that ſo ſoone as men become religious and conſcionable, they are made a</hi> by-word of the people, <hi>Job</hi> 17.6. A
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153780:4"/>ſong of the drunkards, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.12. <hi>And ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally</hi> hated of all, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer. Know yee not</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>James</hi>) <hi>that the Amity of the World, is the Enmity of God? And that whoſoever will be a friend of the World maketh himſelfe the enemy of God?</hi> James 4.4. <hi>A wicked man</hi> (ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>) <hi>is abomination to the Juſt,</hi> and <hi>he that is upright in his way, is abomination to the wicked, Pro.</hi> 29.27.</p>
            <p>There is a naturall Enmity, and a ſpirituall An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy betweene the men of the World and the Children of God; whence it is, that the holy Ghoſt (who can give moſt congruous Names to Natures) uſeth in the Scripture, Gods Dictionary, not onely to call wicked men, Adders, Aſpes, Gockatrices, Serpents, Dragons, Lyons, Tygers, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 74.13 <hi>&amp;</hi> 80.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 140.3. <hi>Eſay</hi> 14.29. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.33. which are the mortalleſt enemies to mankind that live; but moſt frequently Wolves, and the godly Sheep; <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith our Saviour to his Apoſtles) <hi>I ſend you forth as Sheep in the midſt of Wolves,</hi> Mat. 10.16. between whom there is a ſtrange contrariety and antipathy living, and dead, as both Naturaliſts and Lutiniſts obſerve.</p>
            <p>It is an everlaſting rule of the Apoſtles, <hi>He that is born after the Fleſh will perſecute him that is born after the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 4.29. not becauſe he is evil, but becauſe he is ſo much better then himſelf. 1 <hi>John.</hi> 3.12. becauſe his <hi>life is not like other mens;</hi> his wayes are of another faſhion, <hi>Wiſ.</hi> 2.15. <hi>for therefore ſpeake they evill of you, becauſe yee will no longer run with them to the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of ryot,</hi> 1 Pet. 4 4.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But are not many diſcouraged, and others beaten off from being Religious, through
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153780:4"/>the daily ſcoffes and reproaches, which in every place the godly meete withall, for refuſing to doe as others doe with whom they are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea millions, there being no ſuch rub in the way to Heaven as that generall contempt which the Devill and the World have caſt upon Religion and the practiſers of Piety; which makes our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our pronounce that man <hi>bleſſed that is not offended in him, Matth.</hi> 11.6. For hereby it is growne to that, that men feare nothing more then to have a name that they feare God, and are more aſhamed to bee holy then prophane, becauſe holineſſe is worſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated then prophaneneſſe: with <hi>Peter</hi> we are apt to deny our Religion, when we come in company with <hi>Chriſts</hi> enemies: and with <hi>David,</hi> to diſſemble our Faith, when we are amongſt <hi>Philiſtims.</hi> Like thoſe white-liverd Rulers, <hi>John</hi> 12 42. who <hi>loved the praiſe of Men, more than the praiſe of God,</hi> wee chooſe to conceale our knowledge of, and love to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> leſt we ſhould be mockt, have ſo many frownes, and frumps, and cenſures, and ſcoffes, be branded with that odious and ſtigmaticall name of an Hypocrite, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>True, with <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> we owe God ſome good will, but we dare not ſhew it, becauſe of this, we would pleaſe him, yet ſo as we might not diſpleaſe others, nor our ſelves. Like the young man in the Goſpell, we will follow <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> propound no other conditions, then what wee like of: but what will be the iſſue, our Saviour ſaith expreſly. That he will be aſhamed of ſuch at the latter day, who are now aſhamed for his ſake, to beare a few ſcoffes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153780:5"/>and reproaches from the World, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.38.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, it ſo foreſtalleth (ſuch as are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out) with <hi>Prejudice</hi> againſt goodneſſe and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect walking, that they reſolve never to be Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſo long as they live: As how many not onely ſtumble at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the living and <hi>chiefe corner ſtone, elect of God, and preclous,</hi> but quite fal as at a Rocke of offence; yea, utterly diſallow of the things that are excellent, onely through the contempt which is caſt upon Religion? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8.</p>
            <p>What ſuch mens thoughts are we may heare from the damned in Hell, <hi>We fooles thought their lives mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. Wiſd.</hi> 5.3, 4. And experience ſhewes, that they will hate a man to the death, though he have nothing to condemne him, but his being holy.</p>
            <p>Yea, where Satan hath once ſet this his porter of <hi>Prej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dice,</hi> though <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe were on earth, that ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e would ſtumble and bee offended at his very beſt actions; as we ſee in the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who made an evill conſtruction of whatſoever he did or ſpake: For when he wrought Miracles, hee was a Sorcerer: When he caſt out Devils, it was by the power of Devils: When hee reproved ſinners, he was a ſeducer: When he received ſinners, he was their favourer: When he healed the ſick, he was a breaker of the Sabbath, &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Nor can the higheſt eloquence of the beſt Preacher ever reclaime ſuch. For firſt, words are vagabonds where the Admoniſhed hath an evill opinion of the Admoniſher. Secondly, they are reſolved againſt yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thirdly, let them be convinc't by ſtrength of argument, the thought of thoſe things preſently paſſes away like the ſound of a Bell that is rung. O this is a difficult Devill to be caſt out, even like that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153780:5"/>which we read of, <hi>Math.</hi> 17.16. For as all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples could not caſt out that Devill, no more can all the Preachers this: for the <hi>Cure of Prejudice</hi> alone in one man, is more then to cure the ſeaven deadly ſinnes (as the Papiſts tearme them) in another. Nay (if I may ſpeake it with reverence) what meanes can God uſe that ſhall be able to convert ſuch an one? The nine plagues ſhall not prevaile with <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> the graves opening, the dead ariſing, the vayle of the Temple renting, the light of the Sunne fayling, the Centurion confeſſing, &amp;c. will doe no good up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees;</hi> Yea, though <hi>Ahab</hi> be told from the Lord, that if he goe to Warre hee ſhall periſh; <hi>yet he goeth and ſpeeds accordingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But how ſhould weake Chriſtians know the myſtery of this iniquity, ſhake off this ſlaviſh yoke of bondage and feare, in which Satan for the preſent holds them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Search the Scriptures, and they will ſo cleare your judgement, and <hi>cure your Prejudice,</hi> that in ſome meaſure you ſhall be enabled to <hi>quench thoſe fiery darts, Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. I meane, the reproaches of thoſe evill tongues, which are <hi>ſet on fire from Hell, James</hi> 3.6. for <hi>Virgil</hi> moſt excellently and profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly couples the knowledge of cauſe, and the conqueſt of all feares together.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the informing of your judgement, our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles hath abundantly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told the ſame. Of a multitude of predictions I'le on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtance three or foure. <hi>All that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. Not ſome, but all; and what all, but even all that will live godly? Now, me thinkes, if there were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153780:6"/>texts in the Bible but this one, it were omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient to take away <hi>Prejudice</hi> and wonder touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Worlds hatred and calumny: but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are full of the like, <hi>Yee ſhall be hated of all men and Nations</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>for my Names ſake, Matth.</hi> 10.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.9. Not of a few, but of all Men and Nations, that is, all naturall men, or the greateſt part of men in all Countryes and Nations; yea, and for no other cauſe, but for profeſſing of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Name. Neither is <hi>Chriſt a Signe to be ſpoken againſt</hi> of many in <hi>Babylon,</hi> or <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> but of many in <hi>Iſrael, Luke</hi> 2.34. where Religion is profeſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly.</p>
            <p>Yea, when ſincerity is wanting, the nearer the line with any oppoſition, the greater Eclips. The <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereans</hi> but beſought <hi>Chriſt</hi> to depart; his owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men drave him out, and caſt him downe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.29. Yea, who was his greateſt enemy but his greateſt friend, even one of his houſhold-Chaplains? And who but <hi>Jeremies</hi> familiars watched for his haulting?</p>
            <p>Againe (faith our Saviour) <hi>The Servant is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his Maſter, John</hi> 15.20. But <hi>Chriſt</hi> having ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſo much, if we ſhould reſt, the Servant were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his Maſter, which were ſenſleſſe to thinke: For could not his wiſedome, innocency, and holineſſe, ſence him from theſe ſcornes, and can thine fence thee? Beſides, that ancient prediction muſt be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, <hi>I will put enmity betweene the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and the ſeed of the Woman, Gen.</hi> 3.15. But, if there be no warre betweene the men of the World, and the children of God; if they ſhould not hate and perſecure us, this Prediction were not fulfilled: Yea, all the former predictions of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and many,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153780:6"/>that I omit, ſhould bee falſe; which were blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy once to thinke.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>marvell not, my brethren, though the World hate you,</hi> as Saint <hi>John</hi> ſpeakes, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.13. <hi>Neither count it ſtrange,</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hath it, <hi>concerning the fiery tryall which is among you, to prove you, as though ſome ſtrange thing were come unto you,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12. for <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Croſſe are unſeparable, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.27.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſearch the whole Bible over, and you ſhall not finde one holy man mentioned, without mention of ſomething h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſuffered from ungodly men; as it were eaſie to inſtance, how <hi>Abel, Lot, Noah,</hi> Righteous men, <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithfull, <hi>Iſaac, Jacob, Joſeph,</hi> Patriarches and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church, meek <hi>Moſes,</hi> upright <hi>Samuel,</hi> holy <hi>David,</hi> wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> all the Lords Prieſts, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles; yea, the harmeleſſe Babes, and our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, did ſeverally ſuffer from wicked and ungodly men: Yea, never man came to Heaven, but firſt he paſt thorow this Purgatory: God had one Sonne without ſinne, but never any one without ſuffering; which makes our Saviour ſay, <hi>Woe be to you, when all men ſpeake well of you,</hi> that is, when evill men ſpeake well of you, for ſo did the <hi>Jewes</hi> of the falſe Prophets, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.26. Whereas he pronounceth them bleſſed, which heare ill for well doing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.11. Which leads me to the ſecond point.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For Scriptures to confirme, comfort, and ſtrengthen weake Chriſtians againſt the Worlds hatred and calumny, theſe would be applyed which follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed are they</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>which ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for righteouſneſſe ſake, for theirs is the Kingdome
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153780:7"/>of Heaven, Matth.</hi> 5.10. And againe, <hi>Bleſſed are yee when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſay all manner of evill againſt you falſly for my ſake, rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven, for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before you, ver.</hi> 11.12. And Saint <hi>Peter, Rejoyce, inaſmuch as yee are partakers of Chriſts ſufferings, that when his glory ſhall be revealed, ye may be glad alſo with exceeding joy, for if ye be reproached for the Name of Chriſt, happy are ye, for the ſpirit of glory and of God reſteth upon you;</hi> Which on <hi>their part is evill ſpoken off, but on your part is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12, 13, 14. Loe, here is reward enough for all that men or devils can doe againſt us: And what will not men undergoe, ſo their reward may be anſwerable?</p>
            <p>But yet further, What ſaith Saint <hi>Paul? In nothing feare your adverſaries, whoſe malice is to them a token of perdition, but to you of ſalvation, and that of God, Phil.</hi> 1.28. Yea, in the ſame Chapter, verſ. 29. he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth the gift of <hi>ſuffering</hi> before the gift of <hi>beleeving:</hi> And in his Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily concludeth, That they are elect of God, from this ground, That they <hi>received the Word in much affliction with joy in the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Examine theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures againe and againe, for every word of them is ponderous, and conſider of whom, and by whom they were ſpoken: then certainely thou wilt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that if there be any <hi>Nectar</hi> in this life, 'tis in ſorrowes wee endure for Righteouſneſſe. And me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes, when I heare goodneſſe calumniated, I beare it the eaſier, becauſe the ſervants of vice doe it.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the</hi> Originall <hi>ground of the Worlds hatred?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153780:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That proclamation which God himſelfe made in Paradiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. where he ſaith unto the Serpent, <hi>I will put enmity betweene thee, and the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and betweene thy ſeed, and her ſeed: be,</hi> or, <hi>it ſhall bruiſe thine head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is meant here by</hi> Enmity?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A bitter, immoderate, inveterate, irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliable and endleſſe hatred and diviſion, oppoſite to that amity and familiarity which formerly had been betweene the Woman and the Serpent.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Betweene whom was this</hi> Enmity <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Betweene the Serpent and his ſeed, on the one ſide; and the Woman and her ſeed, on the other.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is meant by the</hi> Serpent <hi>and his</hi> Seed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, by the <hi>Serpent</hi> we are to underſtand <hi>Satan,</hi> who opened the Serpents mouth, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to ſpeake with mans voice; as the Lord by an Angell opened the mouth of <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe, <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By the <hi>Serpents ſeed</hi> is meant the whole generation of wicked men, as all Interpreters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, and other Scriptures make cleare, calling them Serpents, Generation of Vipers, and Children of the Devill, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.33. <hi>John</hi> 8.44. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is meant by the</hi> Woman <hi>and her</hi> Seed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the woman is meant <hi>Eve;</hi> by her ſeed we are to underſtand firſt and chiefly <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular <hi>Seed,</hi> who was ſo the Seed of the Woman,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153780:8"/>as that he was not of the Man, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. being borne of a Virgin, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 7.14.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It imployeth all his members, the Elect, when once regenerate, who are not onely <hi>Eves</hi> ſeed as ſhe was the Mother of all living by nature, but by faith alſo; as elſe where they are called the ſeed, or children of <hi>Abraham, Gal.</hi> 3.29.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What occaſioned the Lord to proclaime this enmity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Adams</hi> ſinne, in eating the forbidden fruit, and Satans malice, in moving and ſeducing him thereunto was the meritorious cauſe: the originall of this diſcord is from Originall ſin.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What Inſtruction affords this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, That to be without reproaches and perſecutions wee may rather wiſh then hope. For what peace can we looke for betweene the Seed of the Woman, and the Seed of the Serpent, ſeeing God himſelfe, from the beginning, hath ſet them at en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity? Yea, once to expect it were an effect of frenzy, not of hope.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If the Lord hath put this enmity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and the wicked, here is comfort in ſuffering, warrant in oppoſing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If the Seed of the Woman fight on <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſide, and they have Gods Word for their warrant, they are ſure to have him aſſiſt them, and prevent their enemies. And is not that God we fight for, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough to vindicate all our wrongs?</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Doth that hatred and enmity conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to this day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, the words are ſet downe indefinitely without limitation, and ſo ſignifie that it ſhall be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153780:8"/>perpetuall, from the beginning of time to the end of all time. When time (ſaith one) began, this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice firſt began, nor will it end but with the lateſt man: it is an everlaſting Act of Parliament, like a Statute in <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>To proceed from Explication to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, and ſo to Application. How prove you, That there hath beene in all ages paſt, is now, and ever ſhall bee betweene the wicked and the godly a perpetuall Warre, enmity and ſtrife, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Lords Prediction, or Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For proofe I could produce teſtimonies and examples innumerable, there being ſcarce a page in the Bible, which doth not expreſſe, or imply ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what touching this enmity. Yea, as if the Scriptures contained nothing elſe, the Holy Ghoſt ſignificantly calls them the Booke of the Battles of the Lord, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.14. as <hi>Rupertus</hi> well obſerves. But I will confine my ſelfe, and onely mention three examples in every age.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To begin with the firſt age, <hi>Viz.</hi> the old World before the Flood. We reade of this war, enmity and ſtrife betweene <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.12. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mech</hi> and the holy Seed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.23, 24. and between thoſe wicked Gyants, which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeakes of, and the ſonnes of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.2. to 12. Yea, thoſe Gyants bade battle to Heaven, as our Mytho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſts add, to <hi>ver.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After the Flood, before the Law, betweene all the men of <hi>Sodome</hi> and righteous <hi>Let, Gen.</hi> 19.4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.11. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. Betweene <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> the Bondwoman and her ſonne, and <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153780:9"/>Free-woman, and her ſon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.9, 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4 29. And between <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob:</hi> firſt in the wombe, the more plainely to ſhadow out this enmity, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.22, 23. and after they were borne, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.41.</p>
            <p n="3">3. After the Law, before <hi>Chriſt,</hi> betweene <hi>Doeg</hi> and the eighty five Prieſts, which he ſlew with the edge of the ſword, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.18, 19. Betweene <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabell</hi> and all the Prophets of the Lord, which ſhe deſtroyed, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.13, 14. And betweene the Heads in <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Micahs</hi> time, and all that were good, <hi>Micah</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Since the Goſpell, in the time of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles this enmity ſo manifeſted it ſelfe, not onely in the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> but in the <hi>Jewes,</hi> Gods owne people, who firſt moved thoſe perſecutions againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Members, that having beheaded <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt his Harbinger, and crucified himſelfe the <hi>Lord of life,</hi> we read, that of all the Twelve, none dyed a naturall death ſave onely Saint <hi>John,</hi> and he alſo was baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Domitian</hi> to <hi>Pathmos;</hi> and at another time thruſt into a Tun of ſeething oyle at <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> and Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> doe report: See <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51. to 60. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.1. to 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 21.18, 19.</p>
            <p>Now all theſe, beſides many other of his Diſciples, ſuffered martyrdome meerely for profeſſing the faith of Chriſt; whereof ſome were ſtoned, ſome crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſome beheaded, ſome thruſt thorow with Speares, ſome burnt with fire, with a multitude of other Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, for Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory makes mention of two thouſand which ſuffered the ſame day with <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canor, Acts and Monuments,</hi> page 32. which makes Saint <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul</hi> cry out, <hi>I thinke that God hath ſet forth us the laſt Apoſtles,</hi> as <hi>men appointed to death,</hi> 1 <hi>Corin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</hi> 4.9.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:153780:9"/>5. After the Apoſtles, if we conſider the reſidue of the ten Perſecutions, rayſed by the <hi>Romans</hi> againſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which was for three hundred yeares, till the comming of godly <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> we find that there was ſuch an innumerable company of innocent Chriſtians put to death and tormented, that Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> (in his Epiſtle to <hi>Chromatius</hi> and <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>odorus</hi>) ſaith, There is no one day in the whole yeare unto which the number of five thouſand Martyrs might not be aſcribed, except onely the firſt day of <hi>Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> who were put to the moſt exquiſite deaths and torments that ever the wit or malice of men, or Devils could invent to inflict: we reade of no leſſe then twenty nine ſeverall deaths that they were put unto, if no other be omitted.</p>
            <p n="6">6. From the Primitive times and infancy of the Church hitherto the <hi>Turke</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> have acted their parts, in ſhedding the blood of the Saints, as well as the <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours: touching which, for brevities ſake, I referre you to the Booke of <hi>Acts and Monuments.</hi> Yet becauſe a taſte may pleaſe ſome, I will inſert what the Holy Ghoſt hath foretold in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> touching the <hi>Pope,</hi> who cals himſelfe <hi>Chriſts</hi> Vicar and ſupreame Head of the Church: the Angell, ſpeaking of the Whore of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> ſaith, <hi>She was drunke with the blood of the Saints and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus, Revel.</hi> 17.6. Which in part was fulfilled in <hi>England,</hi> under the raigne of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> when in one yeare, a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſeventy ſix perſons of good quality were burnt for Religion, with many of the common ſort: and in <hi>France,</hi> for before theſe late bloody Maſſacres, there were more then two hundred thouſand which ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Martyrdome about Tranſubſtantiation: For the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153780:10"/>chiefe perſecutors of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his followers, are not <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> or <hi>Turks,</hi> or <hi>Jewes,</hi> but ſuch as hold great place in the Church, <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> and <hi>Pſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dochriſtians;</hi> which makes our Saviour ſay <hi>they ſhall excommunicate you,</hi> that is, they ſhall blot out your names from among Gods people, or caſt you out from the viſible outward communion of the Saints.</p>
            <p>And indeed, vertue hath ever ſuffered moſt from thoſe, which ſhould, and ſeeme to uphold her: and intruders upon other mens right can indure any man, how bad ſoever, rather to live by them, then the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of him whom they intrude upon, as you may ſee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.33. to 39. where thoſe Farmers of the Vineyard killed the ſervants, who came to receive their M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſters rent: they did not kill the Theeves, and Robbers, and Spoylers of the Vineyard, but the ſervants; yea, and the ſonne too, and the end of all was, that they might take the Inheritance.</p>
            <p>Yea, the godly have ever ſuffered moſt from ſuch as profeſſe the ſame Faith and Religion with them. It hath been the complaint almoſt of all the Fathers and Saints of God, which have written, that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in their ſeverall times, were hated, traduced, calumniated, ſlandered, reproached, accuſed, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and condemned of ſuch as profeſſe the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion with them, though under other pretences, yet onely for their auſtere and holy lives, that they ſtuck cloſe to the truth, made conſcience of their wayes, and would not ruſh ſo boldly into ſin as others, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Hiſtory. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.5.16.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To come unto theſe preſent times wherein we live. Is the World mended with age? Yea, I would to God we did not find, that as it is in the little world, the older it grows the more diſeaſed; ſo in the great
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153780:10"/>World, the older the more vicious; that the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of times and ſinnes were not met together upon us. But as commonly in a diſeaſed body all the humours fall downe into the Legs or feet, and make an Iſſue there: ſo the corruption of all ages hath ſliden downe into this of ours, as into the feete. <hi>Many</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>walke, that are enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt, Philip.</hi> 3.18. If many in Saint <hi>Paules</hi> time, more now; for Satan, who was then bound, is now looſed again out of his priſon, and hath great wrath, becauſe he knowes he hath but a ſhort time, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.12. To ſpeake onely of the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which piety findes among ſuch as would bee counted (not onely Chriſtians, but) Proteſtants, which principally I intend. Is it poſſible for a man to live a conſcionable and unreproveable life, abſtaine from drunkenneſſe, ſwearing, prophaning the Lords day, ſeparate himſelfe from evill; yea, wicked com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, be zealous for the glory of God, &amp;c. without being traduced, calumniated, hated, ſlandered and perſecuted for the ſame? No, it is not poſſible: for if our righteouſneſſe doe but exceed the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a ſwearer, or a drunkard, we are ſure to be perſecuted for our righteouſneſſe, as <hi>Abel</hi> was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted of <hi>Caine,</hi> becauſe his Sacrifice was better then his. If a man walke with God, he is too preciſe: if he will be more then almoſt a Chriſtian, he is curious, phantaſticall, factious, and ſhall be mocked with the Spirit, as if the Spirit of God were a Spirit of diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſhame. How common a thing is it to wound all holineſſe under the name of <hi>Puritan,</hi> a name ſo ful of the ſerpents enmity, as the egge of a Cockatrice is full of poyſon? What ſhould I ſay? The World is growne ſo much knave, that 'tis now a vice to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153780:11"/>honeſt. O the deplorable condition of theſe times! Even the Devill himſelfe durſt not have been ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, as to have ſcoft at holineſſe in thoſe ancient and purer times: but now I could even ſinke downe with ſhame, to ſee Chriſtianity every where ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced: our very names come into few mouths, out of which they returne but with reproaches. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt of our ſinnes, O God, be mercifull to the contempt of thy Servants.</p>
            <p>True, bleſſed be God, and our gracious Soveraigne the very <hi>breath of our noſtrils,</hi> we ſuffer little but the laſh of evill tongues; but were wicked mens powers anſwerable to their wils and malice, they <hi>would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us up to be afflicted, put us out of the Synagogues, excommunicate and kill us,</hi> as our Saviour ſhewes, <hi>John</hi> 16.2.33. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.9.</p>
            <p>Yea, their enmity and hatred would be ſo viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and bitter, that the brother would betray the brother to death, the father the ſonne, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren would riſe up againſt their Parents, and cauſe them to dye, the kinſman againſt the kinſman, and the friend againſt the friend, onely for profeſſing <hi>Chriſts</hi> Name, and being religious, as himſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.34, 35, 36. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.16, 17. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it ſtrange, for this was one of the ends of <hi>Chriſts</hi> comming into the World, as appeares, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.34, 35. where himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Thinke not that I am come to ſend peace, but the ſword;</hi> meaning betweene the Seed of the Serpent and the Seed of the Woman; for <hi>I am come to ſet a man at variance againſt his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the daughter-in-Law againſt the mother-in-Law, and a mans enemies ſhall be they of his owne houſhold, Luke.</hi> 12.51, 52, 53.</p>
            <p>Neither want we precedents of this, For, by whom
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153780:11"/>was upright <hi>Abel</hi> perſecuted and ſlain, but by his own brother <hi>Caine?</hi> Who ſcoffed at righteous <hi>Noah,</hi> but his owne ſonne <hi>Cham?</hi> By whom was that vertuous and religious Lady <hi>Barbara</hi> put to death, for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing the Chriſtian Faith, but by her owne Father <hi>Dioſcorus?</hi> And laſtly, by whom was our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> betrayed, but by his owne Diſciple <hi>Judas?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. For the time to come, As this ſtrife and enmity in the wicked againſt the godly, was early in its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, taking its firſt being in the beginning of time, and hath conſtantly continued hitherto: ſo it will be long in continuance, and endure to the end of time, as the Scripture ſhewes: Yea, the laſt rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of time are likely to have the moſt of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as in them <hi>love ſhall wax cold, Math.</hi> 24.12. ſo as love groweth cold, contention groweth hot.</p>
            <p>More expreſly the Holy Ghoſt foretels, That <hi>in the laſt dayes ſhall come ſuch perilous times,</hi> that <hi>all who will live godly ſhall ſuffer perſecution,</hi> and that <hi>toward the end of the World there ſhall be ſcoffers, falſe accuſers, curſed ſpeakers, fierce deſpiſers of them that be good, ſuch as ſhall turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny God the onely Lord, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; And being fleſhly, not having the Spirit, they ſhall ſpeake evill of the things which they know not; And whatſoever things they know naturally as brute beaſts, which are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon,</hi> in thoſe things <hi>they ſhall corrupt themſelves; And that many ſhall follow their damnable wayes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the way of truth ſhall be evill ſpoken off:</hi> And that <hi>as Jannes and Jambres withſtood Moſes; ſo theſe alſo ſhall reſiſt the truth, being men of corrupt mandes, repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate concerning the Faith, being before of old, ordained to condemnation,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. to 13. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. &amp; 3.3. <hi>Iude</hi> 4.10, 16, 18, 19. And ſo much of the continuance.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:153780:12"/>
            <p>Now to wind up with a word of Application: If it be ſo, that all the godly that have gone before us ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> beene envyed, hated, traduced, nicknamed, and perſecuted by wicked men, and all that come aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r us ſhall be; let no particular member of the Church looke to fare better then the whole body: we ſee the Patriarchs went this way, the Prophets this way, the Apoſtles this way, the Martyrs this way, this way went all the Saints and ſervants of God, and doe we looke for an eaſier way? Yea, if the deareſt of Gods Children in former ages have ſuffered ſo much for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> beene put to ſuch cruell deaths and torments for keeping of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; let us praiſe the Lord, who hath dealt with us farre otherwiſe; and pray for his Majeſty, to whom, next under God, we owe the thanks: Yea, if our Fore-fathers ſo willingly underwent thoſe fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tryals, let none for ſhame ſhrinke under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of an aiery tryall onely.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the brother perſecute the brother, the ſon the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther, the Parent his Childe, the Diſciple his Lord, thinke it not ſtrange to be perſecuted of any; for lightly they which are not perſecuted, are perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors themſelves.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Having proved the</hi> Continuance <hi>of this Enmity in all ages, now tell us what be the</hi> Signes <hi>and</hi> Properties <hi>of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They are either
<list>
                  <item>Mentall,</item>
                  <item>Verball,</item>
                  <item>or Actual.</item>
               </list> The firſt whereof are inward and ſecret, the two later outward and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153780:12"/>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What are the</hi> mentall properties, <hi>which you call inward and ſecret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They are foure in number.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is the <hi>manner</hi> of wicked men, out of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> to envy the vertuous and good eſtate of the godly: For envy ſhall lead the troope, as <hi>Iudas</hi> lead the ſouldiers; and it may challenge the firſt place in the right-hand file (as pride doth in the Popes Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of the ſeven deadly ſinnes) becauſe it was the eldeſt and firſt borne ſinne that ever was in the Devill, after he was caſt out of Heaven, and the firſt that ever he begate upon our nature, after we were caſt out of Paradiſe; which makes Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore call it (as by a kind of excellency) <hi>the Devils ſin.</hi> Thus <hi>Caine</hi> envied his brother <hi>Abel, Gen.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Saul David;</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.28, 29. and thoſe unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Iewes Paul, Acts</hi> 17.13. The wicked take as much delight to ſee the vertuous life of an holy man, as fore eyes doe to looke upon the Sunne. How con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary are good Angels and evill men? The Angels rejoyce at that, whereat theſe powre and ſtomack; they are ready to cry and burſt for anger, at that which makes muſicke in Heaven. But why is it? Theſe Antipodes to vertue, having loſt all good them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are vexed to ſee it in another: a true note to know the Serpents ſeed by, for it is the Devils cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.14, 15. as Love is <hi>Chriſts, Iohn</hi> 13.35.</p>
            <p>And as it is the very Lees of vice; ſo it hath a puniſhment anſwerable: for by a juſt judgement of God, their owne malice turnes back into their owne bowels, as it is <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 7.14, 15, 16. and ſlayeth them, as the ſwords of <hi>Gideons</hi> enemies kild them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153780:13"/>
               <hi>Iudges</hi> 7.22. For that none might have cauſe to envy the envious man againe, but all to pity him; envy it ſelfe is a fire, which conſumes that fuell; a Worme which gnaweth that gourd; a Viper, which eats through thoſe bowels; a Moath, which fretteth tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> garment wherein it is bred, nouriſhed and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; <hi>it is the conſuming of the fleſh, and rotting of the bones: Prov.</hi> 14.30.</p>
            <p>And for hereafter, if wicked men thus envy the vertuous and good eſtate of the godly in this World, which is but their Hell, or at leaſt their Purgatory; How will it gall them, <hi>when they ſhall ſee Abraham, and Iſaac, and Iacob, and all the Prophets and Saints of God in the Kingdome of Heaven, and themſelves thruſt out of doores, and caſt into the Lake which burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with fire and brimſtone?</hi> This ſhall make them <hi>gnaſh their teeth for envy,</hi> as our Saviour ſhewes, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.28. <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.11.12. but how juſt is it with God, that this fire of envy ſhould be puniſhed with the fire of Hell!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, it is their <hi>manner</hi> and <hi>property</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the ſuppoſed meane eſtate of the godly, as <hi>Samballat, Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Gerſhom,</hi> with the reſt of that crue, contemned <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and the <hi>Iewes, Nehem.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. Thus <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> contemned <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and his people, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18 19. to 36. and the <hi>Epiourean</hi> Philoſophers <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 17.18</p>
            <p>Whereas miſery, with good natures, is made a loadſtone of mercy: with baſe mindes, it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily made a footſtoole for pride to trample on; and nothing ſo midnights the ſoule of him that is falne, as ſcorne and contempt.</p>
            <p>But you may obſerve, That arrogancy is a weed that ever growes on a dunghill, and from the rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153780:13"/>of that ſoyle, ſhe hath her heighth and ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; for they are but puft mindes, and frothy wits, that get ſo to the top, and bubble thus above infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. As what makes them contemne us, but, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with pride, their ignorance? For, alaſſe, they take notice of our miſery, not of our happineſſe. <hi>Noahs</hi> vertues are not <hi>Chams</hi> admiration; but his drunkenneſſe is his ſport. Wicked men are like thoſe ill taught Children, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.24. that could upbraid <hi>Eliſha</hi> with his bald head, but had not the wit to conſider how God had crowned that head with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and honour. O that they could but ſee all, that they would but ſay all: as <hi>Ephialtes,</hi> when one caſt him in the teeth with his poverty, anſwered, <hi>Why doſt thou not make rehearſall of other things alſo, as that I love law, and regard right?</hi> But indeed, this were to cleane our faces, and foule their owne.</p>
            <p>But let them inſult for a while, they cannot ſit upon ſo high a cogge, but may with turning prove the loweſt in the Wheele: as it fell out with <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> who being now made Lackey to a deſpiſed <hi>Iew,</hi> begins to envy, where halfe an houre ſince he had ſcorned; and miſery, like a Vulture, muſt have ſome body to prey upon. There is a continuall viciſſitude of things: <hi>The Righteous is delivered out of trouble, and the wicked cometh in his ſtead, Prov.</hi> 11.8. <hi>The wicked ſhall bee a ranſome for the righteous, and the tranſgreſſor for the upright, Prov.</hi> 21.18.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, it is their <hi>manner,</hi> to rejoyce at the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed evill eſtate of the godly, as the Princes of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> did at <hi>Sampſons</hi> blindneſſe and bondage, whom they inſulted over, and made their laughing ſtock, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.25. <hi>Peninna</hi> at <hi>Hannahs</hi> barrenneſſe, eſpecially when ſhee went up to the houſe of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:153780:14"/>Lord, 1 <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</hi> 1.6.7 And the <hi>Iewes</hi> at the Diſciples, and the reſt of the Church, when <hi>Herod</hi> vexed ſome, and ſlew others, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. Wicked men feede themſelves with others adverſity, as Beetles are fed with their fellowes dung: and like Fleſh-flies, make the wounds of Gods children their chiefe nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Yea, Crocodile-like, they would, if they might, fatten themſelves with the warmeſt blood of godly mens lives.</p>
            <p>And not ſo onely; for we have a generation, whoſe onely rejoycing is, <hi>Cham</hi>-like, to ſee another fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome groſſe ſinne, or infirmity: Yea, as <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>they hunger and thirſt after the ſcandals of the godly;</hi> and if at any time through humane frailty they doe fall into ſome evill, like hungry Hogs, they muzzle in their excrements, and feaſt upon them, as upon dainties; there being nothing that ſo glads their hearts, that ſo opens their mouths with ſo much inſolency and triumph; as what care will they take to ſpread the ſame abroad by a common fame: Yea, it were well, if they would not play the Curres, and open when they are able to ſpring no Game.</p>
            <p>But they muſt needs be filthy creatures, that feed upon nothing but corruption. To delight in mens ſinnes, is the ſport of Devils: recovery from thoſe ſinnes, is the joy of good men and Angels. <hi>Cham</hi> derides his Fathers nakedneſſe; it ſhould have been his ſorrow: he makes it his ſport. But it is ill for a man to make himſelfe merry, with that which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is their <hi>manner,</hi> to hate the religious, as all car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men hate the members of <hi>Chriſt, Matth.</hi> 10.22. Thus <hi>Ahab</hi> hated <hi>Eliah,</hi> as himſelfe confeſſed, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.8. Yea, ſo inveterately, that there was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:153780:14"/>not one Kingdome or Nation, where he had not ſent to take away his life, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.10. and <hi>Haman Mordecai,</hi> which was ſo deadly, that he thought it too little to lay hands on <hi>Mordecai</hi> on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſought to deſtroy all the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the people of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> that were throughout the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Ahaſuerus, Heſter</hi> 3.5, 6. For the effecting of which, he obtained that bloody Edict, <hi>ver.</hi> 6.9. And leſt it ſhould want ſucceſſe, he offered ten thouſand Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of ſilver into the Kings Treaſury, to have it effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Heſter</hi> 3.9, 13. And ſuch another was cruell <hi>Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del,</hi> ſometime Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> who vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſwore, he would not leave a ſlip of Profeſſors in this Land. For you muſt know, That their hatred extendeth not to this, or that perſon alone, but to the whole generation of Gods Children and people. As what ſaith the wicked in <hi>Davids</hi> time? <hi>Come, let us out them off from being a Nation, and let the name of Iſrael be no more in remembrance, Let us take for our poſſeſſions the habitations of God, Pſalme</hi> 83 4, 12.</p>
            <p>And the World is no changeling; for this age wants not many ſuch <hi>Hamans</hi> and <hi>Arundels,</hi> who ſo hate the Children of God, that they wiſh, as <hi>Caligula</hi> once did of the <hi>Romans, That they had all but one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that ſo they might cut it off at a blow,</hi> were it in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> power, <hi>Micah.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.4.</p>
            <p>But our comfort is, they have not ſo much a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as malice; reſembling the Serpent <hi>Porp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which abounds with poyſon, but can hurt non<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> want of teeth: Though their puniſhment ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> never the leſſe. For as the will to doe God acce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervice, is accepted, as if it were ſervice inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſo the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent and offer of wrong, ſhall be judge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wrong, in that Court of Juſtice. Good and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:153780:15"/>thoughts and deſires, in Gods account are good and evill workes: And ſo much touching the <hi>Mentall properties</hi> of this enmity.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What are their</hi> Verball properties?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> They are Eleven in number. Firſt, ungodly men <hi>verbally</hi> manifeſt their enmity by <hi>murmuring</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Children of God: as <hi>Labans</hi> ſonnes mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured againſt <hi>Iacob, Geneſis</hi> 31.1. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> Yea, againſt God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; for which, the utmoſt part of the Hoſt was conſumed with fire from Heaven, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.2, 3. And laſtly, the labourers in the Vineyard againſt the Maſter of the houſe, and their fellowes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.11, 12.</p>
            <p>And have not we the like murmurers? O that ſo many Loaves and Fiſhes, as did feede five thouſand in the Wilderneſſe, would but ſtop their mouthes, who amongſt us doe both vex at others plenty of grace, and their owne want: that doe murmure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dly, even for no other cauſe, but that they alone ſhould be the men in whom no crime, or fault ſcandalous can juſtly bee found: that make it their Grace, both before and after Dinner, to diſgrace ſome Innocent.</p>
            <p>But ſo it is, That the baggage World deſireth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, then to ſcarre the face that is fairer then her ſelfe: whence ſhe takes occaſion, in every com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to erect the faylings of holy men very high, like Saint <hi>Pauls,</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he gaze of all; whereas they hide their good parts under ground, like Saint <hi>Faiths,</hi> that none may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> another diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dvantage, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lped. The multitude will ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ner beleeve them, then our ſolves. Affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mations being apter to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:153780:15"/>win beleife, then Negatives are to uncredit them: whereby it fals out, that Piety is every where puſht at, and the religious murmured at, and clamoured againſt in all places.</p>
            <p>If ſuch men would know their wages: let them looke, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. and there they ſhall finde, that as their tongues have walked againſt Heaven, ſo they ſhall be confined to Hell: And in the meane time, <hi>Curſed is he</hi> (ſaith the Holy Ghoſt) <hi>that ſmiteth his neighbour ſecretly; and let all the people ſay, Amen. Deut.</hi> 27.24.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>Cenſuring</hi> their actions, and <hi>miſconſtruing</hi> their intentions, as <hi>Eliab:</hi> did <hi>Davids</hi> zeale for Gods glory to be pride and malice, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.28. And thoſe wicked ones, his faſting and mourning to be Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifie, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 35.13. to 17. Thus <hi>Jobs</hi> friends con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned him for an Hypocrite, <hi>Job</hi> 4.6. to 11. And the <hi>Jewes,</hi> Chriſtianity to be Hereſie, and <hi>Paul</hi> the Preacher of it, <hi>a peſtilent fellow, a mover of ſedition, and maintainer of ſchiſme;</hi> yea, all the Diſciples to be deceivers, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.8.</p>
            <p>And thus too many in our dayes will definitively <hi>cenſure</hi> men for Hypocrites, whom they ſcarce know ſuperficially: Yea, (which is worſe) onely becauſe their workes are good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prejudice</hi> caſteth a falſe colour upon the beſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and Baſeneſſe, what it cannot attaine to it will vellicate and deprave. But what ſaith Sincerity? While my conſcience is innocent, the Worlds ſuppoſitions cannot make me culpable: Let me rather, with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> and <hi>Micah,,</hi> doe well, and heare ill; then, with <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezahell,</hi> doe ill and be flattered.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Accuſer of the Brethren</hi> makes choyce of wicked men to traduce thoſe whom he cannot ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:153780:16"/>as he deſireth; as wee may plainely ſee in our Saviours example, who notwithſtanding he fulfilled all righteouſneſſe, and did all things well, for <hi>in his mouth was found no guile,</hi> nor fault in his manners, nor error in his doctrine, <hi>Which of you</hi> (ſaid hee) <hi>can rebuke me of ſinne?</hi> Yet the World traduced him for a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> a Blaſphemer, a Sorcerer, a wine bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, an enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and what not?</p>
            <p>Thus they deale with the godly, as ſometimes a luſtfull perſon will doe by a chaſte woman, when he cannot take away her honeſty, he will take away her credit; brag of effecting his will with her, when yet he could never have admittance into her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>Bad natures, whom they cannot reach by imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they will by detraction: like the Fox, what they cannot attaine to, they will depreſſe and ſeeme to deſpiſe: their cunning is to condemne others, that themſeves may be juſtified. As <hi>Caligula</hi> tooke off the heads from the Images of the gods, to ſet up his own. Or as Merchants, who to raiſe the price of their own commodities, beate down the prices of others.</p>
            <p>And have they not reaſon thus to doe? Yes, for how is a vicious perſon diſcredited and made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, by the vertuous life of an holy man? We know ſtraight lines helpe to ſhew the crooked. And it is eaſie to gueſſe, that <hi>Pharaohs</hi> fat Kine made the leane ones more ilfavoured. A ſwarthy and hard fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured viſage, loves not the company of cleare beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>Againe, another reaſon is, They judge others by themſelves: now they doe all their good in hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and ſo thereafter judge of others. Saint <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> hath given the rule, <hi>As it is an hard thing</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:153780:16"/>he) <hi>for one to ſuſpect another to be evill, who is good himſelfe: ſo it is as hard for him to ſuppoſe another to be good, who is himſelfe ill.</hi> And we ſee it fulfilled in <hi>Nero,</hi> who verily beleeved, that all men were moſt fowle libidiniſts, becauſe himſelfe was ſuch an one.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Wicked men manifeſt their enmity againſt the religious, by <hi>carrying tales</hi> of them unto others: as <hi>Cham carryed tales</hi> to his brethren of <hi>Noahs</hi> naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: his tongue was the trumpet, to ſound forth his Fathers ſhame, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.22. thus <hi>Doeg carryed tales</hi> to <hi>Saul</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Abimelech,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.9, 10. and the <hi>Ziphins</hi> two ſeverall times brought tydings to <hi>Saul,</hi> where <hi>David</hi> had hid himſelfe, to the end <hi>Saul</hi> might ſlay him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.19, 20. &amp; 26.1. And thoſe Libertines, with other ſuborned men againſt <hi>Steven,</hi> to the Councell of Prieſts, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.8. to 15.</p>
            <p>And of this burthen many amongſt us are in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall travell. For how frequently doe debauched drunkards, and incorrigible ſinners (reſembling their father the Devill, who both by name, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.10. and by nature, <hi>Job</hi> 1.7, 8, 9. is a continuall <hi>Accuſer of the brethren</hi>) <hi>carry tales</hi> to their fellowes, of ſuch as will not conſorte with them? Yea, of their faithfull Miniſters, eſpecially if hee <hi>thunders in his doctrine, and lightens in his converſation,</hi> as <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Baſil?</hi> Yea, and thinke they doe as good ſervice in it, as Secretaries, and eſpialls of Princes, doe to the State, when they bring in bills of Intelligence?</p>
            <p>But doe they, as they ought, with an upright minde tell both our vertues and vices impartially, as <hi>Sueto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> writeth of the twelve <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and ſo leave the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:153780:17"/>upſhot to collection? No, but rather, as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did by <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 24. <hi>charge us with many things,</hi> as that we are <hi>peſtilent fellowes, movers of ſedition,</hi> and <hi>maintaienrs of ſchiſme,</hi> but <hi>proving nothing, verſe</hi> 13. And indeed, how ſhould they, when every word they ſpeak is a ſlander? Or if otherwiſe, they look on our infirmities, they looke not on our graces, on our repentance? No theſe Flyes skip over all a mans ſound parts, I meane his excellencies; to faſten on a ſcab, or ulcer; reſembling our Prognoſticators, that are more diligent to make mention of foule weather, then of fayre; ſtormes and thunder they much harp up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but calme and ſerene dayes paſſe them unobſerved: whereas an ingenuous nature would paſſe over the evill, where he findes more good; conſidering, we are full of faults by nature; good, not without our care and induſtry; for a minde well qualified, is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten beholding to the induſtry of the owner: and <hi>Vlyſſes,</hi> as <hi>Homer</hi> relates, was ſo applauded for the acute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of an ingenious mind, that men ſpared to object unto him the deformity of his body.</p>
            <p>But theſe contrarily, for want of matter to except againſt, will coyne it of their owne heads. And that they may deliver themſelves with the greater Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis will affirme as that <hi>Gymnoſophiſt</hi> in <hi>Plutarch</hi> did, of thoſe Orators to <hi>Alexander, That every one of them doth exceed his fellowes,</hi> and ſware that the matter is ſo cleare and manifeſt, that all the Towne ings of him (meaning the good fellowes of the towne) and to ſpeake truth, the parties faults are ſo cleare and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that you may ſee them as well in the darke, as with a candle, as appeares by the ſequell. For, are there not ſome godly and faithful, both Chriſtians and Preachers, that have beene often (I ſay not ninety
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:153780:17"/>five times) accuſed by them, as <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> was by the <hi>Athenians,</hi> and every time found innocent? Though no thankes to their accuſers, for they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour all they can to corrupt ſuch as heare them, and foreſtall their judgements againſt the good and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>O that men were ſo wiſe, as to heare the <hi>tale-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> with indignation, examine before they truſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve his reports, if infallibly true, with unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, acknowledge it with griefe, hide our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours faults with honeſt excuſes, and bury them in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: for commonly it fares with the firſt relator, as it doth with a ſtone throwne into the water, which of it ſelfe makes but one circle, but that one begets an hundred, and ſo both offends and infects many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but alwayes proves himſelfe to be uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. It were good for other men, if <hi>tale-bearers</hi> would conſider this, but better for themſelves.</p>
            <p>True, the wiſe and honeſt are able, as ſo many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God, to diſcerne truth from ſlander; though to the griefe of many good hearts, no muſick can be ſo ſweet to the eares of others, as to heare well of themſelves, ill of the religious.</p>
            <p>And theſe, as they often ſet the former on worke, ſo they are reſolutely opinionated in beleeving o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lyes (as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeakes of the <hi>Priſcillianiſts</hi>) whereby they ſupererogate of Satan.</p>
            <p>But what is the end of theſe <hi>tale-bearers,</hi> and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers againſt good men? Follow them to their ends, and you ſhall ſee, that if ever the Lord open their eyes to ſee this their fact, they are even in this life rewarded with the ſtrappadoes of an humane ſoule, rackt in conſcience, and tortured with the very flaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Hell fire, and not ſeldome forced to lay violent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:153780:18"/>hands upon themſelves, being never well, nor in their owne place, till they bee in Hell, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.25.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is their <hi>manner</hi> to perſwade and <hi>give devilliſh counſell</hi> to others, like themſelves, to perſecute the godly, as <hi>Balaam</hi> gave wicked counſell to <hi>Balack</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he could not be ſuffered to curſe them, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.14. Thus the Princes and Rulers did to <hi>Zedekiah</hi> the King againſt <hi>Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>We beſeech you, let this man be put to death, for thus he we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kneth the hands of the men of Warre, &amp;c. Jer.</hi> 38.4. and the <hi>Jewes</hi> of <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> to the people of <hi>Berea</hi> againſt <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 17.13.</p>
            <p>That the enemies of the Croſſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are ſtill accuſtomed to deale after this manner with the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, I need not demonſtrate; plaine things, which our ſelves are dayly witneſſes of, need no proofe, Onely note their matchleſſe malice herein, who that they may be ſure to prevaile, firſt dazell their friends eyes with <hi>falſe accuſations</hi> againſt us, as true and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, as that <hi>Naboth</hi> did blaſpheme God and the King; and their aſſociates are as ſure of it, as <hi>Darius</hi> was, that the Idoll <hi>Bell</hi> did eate and drinke every day forty Sheepe, twelve Kakes, and ſix great pots of Wine, becauſe threeſcore and ten of the Prieſts gave it out ſo; And that their mortall enmity may be taken for a zeale of the Churches good, as <hi>Judas</hi> would have his covetouſneſſe taken for Charity, <hi>John</hi> 12.6. And the <hi>Phariſees</hi> their Cruelty thought Piety, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.14. All the reproaches that the Devill and theſe his ſcavengers can rake out of the Channels of Hell ſhall be flung in our faces, the worſt language that hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been dipt in the forge, or tipt at the fire of Hell, ſhall be beſtowed upon us; wherein they reſemble
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:153780:18"/>thoſe ancient enemies of the Goſpell, who clad the Martyrs in the skins of wild Beaſts, to animate the dogs to teare them.</p>
            <p>Though perhaps this is more then needs, for not ſeldome the counſelled are more ready to yeeld their ayde, then they are to aske it; being of <hi>Maximinus</hi> his humor, who ſeeing none offer themſelves, ſet on worke certaine vile perſons to <hi>accuſe the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of haynous crimes, that ſo he might perſecute them with more ſhew of reaſon; for that one may ſupply the others defects, the firſt finds an head, the ſecond a tongue, the third hands: As <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> may contrive, but <hi>Diomedes,</hi> muſt thorow with it: ſo altogether deale with the poore Miniſter, or Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, as the ſouldiers did with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> firſt blind him, then ſtrike him, and laſt aske him, <hi>Who is it that ſmote thee?</hi> And he may anſwer the beſt man of them, It was thou, O mine enemy, thou waſt an <hi>Achitophell,</hi> in the one; a <hi>Doeg</hi> in the other; a <hi>Beliall</hi> in both. And let ſuch men know, that this their inſtigation will end at laſt either in anguiſh, or confuſion, teares or torment will become their recompence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is the <hi>manner</hi> and cuſtome of wicked men to <hi>ſcoffe</hi> at the righteous, as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ſcoft at <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 21.9. <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> at <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and his people, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.27. And the Philoſophers at <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 17.18. to 21.</p>
            <p>And to this day the World is too full of ſcoffing Atheiſts, and mockers of Piety. <hi>Michal</hi> was barren, yet ſhe hath too many Children, that ſcorne holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerciſes: every houſhold almoſt hath ſome in it, if not many, of the brood of <hi>Cham</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael:</hi> ſo that if any one refraine from impiety, refuſe to doe as the reſt in all exceſſe of ryot, he is made both their prey
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:153780:19"/>and laughingſtock: Yea, if he be ſo bold as to Preach righteouſneſſe to them, by voyce or by example, there is inſtantly ſome <hi>Tobiah,</hi> or <hi>Sanballat</hi> ſteps up to flout him. They ſo hate righteouſneſſe, that they will hate a man for it, and ſay of good living, as <hi>Feſtus</hi> did of great learning, it <hi>makes a man mad.</hi> But they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know who are ſober, that are mad themſelves: <hi>Achiſh</hi> and his Courtiers thought <hi>David</hi> mad, yet he was the wiſeſt man amongſt them. Yea, as old men anſwer young men, You thinke us fooles, but wee know you are not wiſe: ſo anſwer wee theſe, You thinke us madde that are ſo hot againſt ſinnes, but wee know you madde, that are ſo cold for your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Dogs will barke at the Moone: and what all men commend, you have ſome <hi>Therſites</hi> take delight to blaſt. <hi>Lot</hi> vexed himſelfe, becauſe he ſaw men bad; theſe, becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en are good: not becauſe Gods Law is broken, but becauſe others keepe it better then themſelves. But theſe are briniſh and ill made can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, which ſo ſparkle and ſpit at others: it is a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed zeale in theſe men, to maligne the good zeale of all men.</p>
            <p>But let them alone, they need no helpe to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable; for as they ſcoffe at us, ſo God laughes at them, <hi>He that fitteth in the Heavens ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion, Pſal.</hi> 2.4. yea, Judgments are prepared for theſe ſcorners, and <hi>ſtripes for the backs of theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fooles, Prov.</hi> 19.29.</p>
            <p>If t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ey ſmart not here, as <hi>Cham</hi> did, whoſe ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly brought his Fathers Curſe, and Gods up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: And the two and forty little children, who were devoured of wild Beares, for ſcoffing at <hi>Eliſhas</hi> bald head, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.24. And <hi>Foelix,</hi> who for one mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:153780:19"/>ſcoffe, did nothing day and night but vomit blood, till his unhappy ſoule was fetcht from his wretched carkaſſe: And <hi>Pherecydes,</hi> who was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by wormes alive, for giving Religion but a nickname; a ſmall matter, if thou mayſt bee made Judge: And <hi>Lucian,</hi> who for barking againſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, like a Dog, was by a juſt judgement of God devoured of dogs.</p>
            <p>For this let me tell them, what ever the Devill blinding them they thinke, there cannot be a greater argument of a foule ſoule, then the deriding of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious ſervices: Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to be a ſcoffer is the depth of ſinne: ſuch an one is upon the very threſhold of Hell, as being ſet downe in a reſolute contempt of all goodneſſe.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is their <hi>manner</hi> and property to <hi>nickname</hi> the godly as <hi>Ahab</hi> nicknamed <hi>Eliah, the troubler of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.17. The wicked, <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>David</hi> Hypocrites, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 35.13, 14. <hi>Job</hi> 4.6. to 11. The Courtiers, <hi>Ieremiah</hi> an enemy to the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The <hi>Iewes, Paul</hi> a factious and ſeditious fellow, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.14. Yea, they tearmed all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, Sectaries, Schiſmaticks, ſubverters of the State, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9.10.</p>
            <p>And the ſame Devill, who ſpake in <hi>Ahab</hi> and thoſe wicked ones of old, now ſpeakes in our looſe Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, who nickname the conſcionable, Puritans, and ſeditious perſons, for doe but examine who they be which caſt theſe aſperſions upon the godly, and you ſhall find, that the hand of <hi>Ioab,</hi> I meane the Devill, is in this buſineſſe. Alaſſe, poore ſoules, they are but ſet on by that ſubtill Serpent, as <hi>Zebede</hi> was by her ſounes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.20. <hi>Mark</hi> 10.35. it is but his heart in their lips.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153780:20"/>
            <p>And Satan hath ever found it infinitely ſucceſſefull, to give every vice a title, and every vertue a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace; for ſtill he hath found, that the rude and unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble multitude onely looke upon the vizard and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of things, which he pleaſeth to put upon them, and ſo <hi>judge according to appearance, not righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither doth the Devill onely gaine by faſtning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull nicknames upon the religious, but his ſervants gaine too: much like the theef, who mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with a full purſe, not onel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> takes it away, but returnes a ſtab: for in making <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rtue contemptible, and in depraving the godly, they are at leaſt upon even pround with them, if they have not the better: for were all the World ugly, deformity would be no monſter. Among the <hi>Myconians</hi> baldneſſe is no unſeemly thing, becauſe all there are borne bald: and hereupon infamous perſons love to mitigate their owne ſhame, with others diſcredit. As <hi>Aeſops</hi> Fox, when ſhe had loſt her tayle, would have redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med her ſhame, by perſwading all her fellow foxes to cut off theirs; yea, by depreſſing the good, they may poſſibly get the ſtart of them. Even <hi>Heliogabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> that beaſtly monſter, thought to make himſelfe the ſole god, and be onely worſhipped, by baniſhing all other religions out of the World.</p>
            <p>But let theſe depravers take heed, leſt imitating the fact of Cenſor <hi>Fulvius,</hi> who untiled <hi>Iuno's</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to cover his owne houſe, they partake of the like judgement, run mad, and dye deſpayring.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It is their <hi>manner</hi> to <hi>revile</hi> and <hi>rayle</hi> on them, as <hi>Goliah</hi> reviled and rayled on the Hoſt of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and their God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.45. <hi>Shimei,</hi> upon <hi>David,</hi> call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him murtherer, and wicked man, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:153780:20"/>And likewiſe the mighty men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.13. And the <hi>Jewes</hi> upon <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas, Acts</hi> 13.45.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calumny</hi> is every good mans Lackey, which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes him whereſoever he goes; for the Devill hath his ſervants in every corner; and rotten Lungs can never ſend forth ſweet breath. If the Law bind their hands, yet they will be <hi>ſmiting with their tongues:</hi> and if the Law keep them in awe for ſmiting on the mouth yet they will doe what they dare, they will ſmite with the mouth.</p>
            <p>It is with theſe men, as it was with <hi>Zoilus</hi> that common ſlanderer, who being demanded why hee ſpake evill of ſuch and ſuch, anſwered, becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe them evill: or elfe, like another <hi>Pariſian</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gils, we ſhould feele their ſwords, before we heard their alarums. When the Devils hands are bound, he <hi>vomits a flood of reproaches with his tongue, Revel.</hi> 12.15. What ſay they? Since we cannot attaine to their vertues, let us revenge our ſelves with rayling againſt them.</p>
            <p>It is not for nothing, that wicked men are ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Scripture called Dogs, as <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 59.6. <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my ſoule,</hi> or my darling, <hi>from the power of the Dog:</hi> and <hi>They make a noyſe like a Dog, and goe round</hi> about the City. <hi>Beware of Dogges,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 3.2. which either grin with malice, or barke with reproaches, or bite with miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, although ſome of theſe Dogs have <hi>teeth like ſwords, and jawes like knives,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.14. And <hi>ſmite cruelly,</hi> as <hi>Jeremy</hi> complaines, Chap. 18.18. which deſerve, like Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards Curres, to have their teeth beaten out, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their biting; yea, and their chaps muzled, for feare of opening; yet moſt of them are tooth-leſſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:153780:21"/>Curres, which though they barke, yet they cannot bite; and cowardly Curres, for if you note ſuch an one, he ſeldome unbuttons his tumoured breſt, but when he finds none to oppoſe the bignes of his looks and tongue.</p>
            <p>And for ſuch our onely way is, either to ſlight them, as King <hi>Philip</hi> did <hi>Nicanor,</hi> in the like caſe, who being told by <hi>Smitichus</hi> of his evill reports and raylings, anſwered, <hi>Nicanor is not eſteemed by the worſt in Macedonia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or elſe ſtop their mouths with ſome good turne, as <hi>Aeneas,</hi> in the fiction, caſt <hi>Cerberus</hi> the hell-hound a ſweet morſell, that he might not barke againſt him. The doore, when it hath been oyled, leaves crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: and this is good policy: for barking Curres oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times great maſtiffs wake.</p>
            <p>But as if the tearme of <hi>Dogge,</hi> were of too narrow extent, the Scripture elſewhere cals them Devils. Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. (as Biſhop <hi>Andrewes</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves from the Originall) foretels, that in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes there ſhall be men Devils, foule mouthed men, evill ſpeakers, and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.11. he ſpeaketh of women-devils, whoſe ſpeeches are calumnious. And wherefore is the Devill called by that name, but by reaſon of his foule mouth in defaming? Yea, <hi>A Calumny,</hi> ſaith one of the Fathers, <hi>is the Devils minde in the mouth of a man, his arrow ſhot by mans bow;</hi> he lendeth him his lyes and malice, and borroweth his tongue to utter them, becauſe the Devill wants a tongue.</p>
            <p>I cloſe up this point with thoſe words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, either <hi>convert the perſons or confound the lying lips, O God, that ſpeake againſt the righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. It is their <hi>manner</hi> to <hi>raiſe ſlanders</hi> of the godly,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:153780:21"/>as thoſe wicked men ſlandered <hi>Naboth,</hi> ſaying, he hath <hi>blaſphemed God and the King,</hi> confirming the ſame with an oath, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. Thus the wicked ſlandered <hi>David, Pſam.</hi> 57.4. And the multitude <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> ſaying <hi>he had a Devill, Matth.</hi> 11.18.</p>
            <p>It is Satans policy (becauſe report both makes jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, where there are none, and increaſeth thoſe that are) to abuſe our eares in hearing, our tongues in ſpeaking, and our hearts in beleeving lyes, to diſable us from diſcerning the truth.</p>
            <p>Yea, this ſtratagem of raiſing ſlanders upon good men, like a huge and mighty <hi>Polypheme,</hi> hath done ſuch ſervice to the uncircumciſed, that examples thereof in Scripture are like moates in the Sunne: and it were eaſie to parallell former ages with this of ours, for well may we take up thoſe words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>The wicked bend their bow, and make ready their arrowes upon the ſtring, that they may ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhoote at them which are upright in heart, Pſalmes</hi> 11.2.</p>
            <p>Innocency is no ſhelter againſt evill tongues. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice never regards how true any accuſation is, but how ſpitefull.</p>
            <p>And great wits are not more ready, with the high Prieſts and Elders, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.12, 13. to raiſe theſe ſlanders, then the common ſort are apt to beleeve the ſame; as we ſee by our Saviours example, <hi>ver.</hi> 15. And how many particular perſons know, to their ſmart, that a ſlander once raiſed will ſcarce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dye: for comming once into the mouth of the vulgar, true or falfe, like wild-fire it can never be quenched; for even death it ſelfe, which delivereth a man from all other enemies, is not able to deliver him from this of the tongue. Whereas Truth hath
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:153780:22"/>much adoe to be beleeved, a lye runs farre before it can be ſtayed.</p>
            <p>However, a man once wounded in his good name, is not cured without ſcarres of ſuſpition. Yea, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, as a little ball rowled in the ſnow gathers it ſelfe to a great lumpe: ſo the report that is but a little ſparke at firſt, proves a great flame, by that it hath paſt through many mouthes.</p>
            <p>But did not mens owne wickedneſſe blinde them, were they not abſolutely turned fooles, they would thus argue: Not he that is accuſed, but he that is convicted is guilty, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> hath it. In the Chancery are many accuſations they never meane to prove: Neither doth any Law condemne a man, till he comes to his anſwer. Vpright <hi>Cato</hi> was fifty times undeſervedly indited and accuſed by his fellow Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, yet was every time acquitted and found in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent.</p>
            <p>The Orator <hi>Tertullus,</hi> when he would pleade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Paul,</hi> ſayes, <hi>We have found this man a peſtilent fellow, Acts</hi> 24.5. But, if you marke it, this fooliſh <hi>Tertullus</hi> miſtooke the antidote for the poyſon, the remedy for the diſeaſe: Indeed, he had ſome wit in his anger, and ſo have his followers in ſlandering ſuch as excell in vertue: for whereas formerly the ſplendor of the others vertues hath obſcured the meanneſſe of their credit, as the leſſer light of a candle is obſcured by the greater light of the Sun: ſo now by clouding and depraving him and all his fellowes, himſelfe ſhall bee judged vertuous very cheape, accounted a man of honeſty and honour, though a Paricide or a ſacrilegious perſon.</p>
            <p>And is it not good policy, for a ſwiniſh drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, or a beaſtly liver to fling durt in a holy mans
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:153780:22"/>face, when, firſt, any colour ſeemes the fairer, when as black is by? Secondly, when (being conſcious of their owne defects) by this meanes they draw away mens thoughts, and conſideration of the beholders, from climing up into their faults, while they are fixed and buſied upon a new object. One colour we know, being laid upon another, doth away the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and remaines it ſelfe. A Cut-purſe in a throng, when he hath committed the fact, will cry out, my Maſters, take heed of your purſes; and he that is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued will cry, ſtop theefe, that by this meanes he may eſcape unattached.</p>
            <p n="9">9. It is <hi>uſuall</hi> with them to <hi>Curſe</hi> the godly, as <hi>Goliah</hi> curſed <hi>Dauid,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.43. And alſo <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. to 15. Thus the Heathen curſed <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, Zach.</hi> 8.13. And thus the wicked in all ages ſhall be ſo drunke with malice, that they ſhall ſpew out curſing and ſlander againſt the godly, as our Saviour hath foretold, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.44.</p>
            <p>And experience proves, that not a few amongſt us doe ſteep their words in hate and curſes againſt the good, carrying this deadly poyſon, theſe arrowes, ſwords, knives, razors in their mouthes, wherewith to interlace their diſcourſe, whether in reviling the preſent, or backbiting the abſent.</p>
            <p>There is a generation (pity they ſhould be called Chriſtians) all whoſe <hi>Prayers</hi> are <hi>Curſes,</hi> and all their relations lyes: Or if ſometimes they lend the truth their voice, they are but falſe witneſſes in ſpeaking of it; for their hearts are of another judgement. As let them ſay with their mouthes, <hi>I beleeve in God,</hi> or <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> or <hi>God ſpake theſe words, &amp;c.</hi> even in this they lye, for <hi>in their hearts they thinke there is no God</hi> at all: or if with their hearts they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:153780:23"/>beleeve, and with their tongues confeſſe that there is a God, at leaſt <hi>by their workes they deny him,</hi> and the power of his word. So that all the difference betweene them, and very Infidels, is onely this, the one are infidels in their hearts, the other are infidels in their lives, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> pithily.</p>
            <p>And whats the reaſon they curſe us, but this? They are the Devils beſt ſchollers, and of his higheſt Forme; the language of Hell is ſo familiar unto them, that they ſpeake not a word of our countrey language: And indeed, how ſhould they ſpeake the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> to whom blaſphemy is become the mother tongue?</p>
            <p>Secondly, they curſe us becauſe they cannot be ſuffered to kill us; for in heart and Gods account they are no better then murtherers; nor will it be any rare thing at the day of Judgement, for Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers to be indited of murther: they would kill us, if they durſt: they doe kill, ſo farre as they can. I would be loath to truſt his hands, that bannes me with his tongue. It is eaſie to gueſſe how they would deale with us, if we were at their mercy. He that ſiniled on <hi>David</hi> in his throne, curſeth him in his flight: Now his unſound and treacherous heart diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers it ſelfe in a tongue full of venome, a hand full of ſtones; and had not <hi>David</hi> been yet too ſtrong for his impotent Subject, hee had then breathed his laſt.</p>
            <p>Proſperous ſucceſſe hides many a falſe heart, as a drift of Snow covers a heape of dung: but when that white mantle melts, the filthy rottenneſſe will ſoone appeare.</p>
            <p>Neither is it any ſinne we commit, or offence we give them, that they <hi>Curſe</hi> us. Who could have leſſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:153780:23"/>deſerved thoſe curſes, thoſe aſperſions, thoſe ſtones, then <hi>David?</hi> Had <hi>Shimei</hi> been other then a dog, he had never ſo rudely barked at ſo harmeles a paſſenger. That head deſerved to be tongueleſſe, that body to be head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that thus blaſphemed an Innocent, though he had been leſſe then the Lords Anoynted.</p>
            <p>Againe, Why would they kill our bodies, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they could not ſlay our ſoules? For it is ſoule-blood which the Serpent and his Seed thirſt after, as I ſhall ſhew afterward.</p>
            <p>But alaſſe, if all their Curſes and threats, all their aſperſions and Antichriſtian ſlanders, could flout us out of the integrity of our devotion, when our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers feared not the flames, wee were fearefull cowards.</p>
            <p>As for their <hi>banning</hi> of us, we have learnt from <hi>Solomon, That the cauſeleſſe curſe ſhall not come, Prov.</hi> 26.2. or at leaſt, it ſhall not come where the curſer meant it. Yea, the Pſalmiſt tels us plainely, That <hi>though they curſe, yet God will bleſſe, Pſalm,</hi> 109.28. And his bleſſing ſhall doe us good, while their cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes hurt none but themſelves: for what ſaith the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt in the ſame Pſalme, ſpeaking of the deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately wicked, whoſe brand is, that <hi>they love curſing.</hi> The words are theſe, <hi>As hee loved curſing, ſo ſhall it come unto him; and as he loved not bleſſing, ſo ſhall it be farre from him. As he cloathed himſelfe with curſing, as with a rayment: ſo ſhall it come into his bowels like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and like oyle into his bones. Let it be unto him, as a garment to cover him, and for a girdle, wherewith he ſhall be alwayes girded,</hi> ver. 17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>Heare this all yee whoſe tongues run ſo faſt on the Devils errand, Yee loved curſing, you ſhall have it, both upon you, about you, and in you, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:153780:24"/>that everlaſtingly, if you perſevere and goe on. For if Chriſtians be charged to bleſſe their enemies; What will be their caſe, that curſe their friends? Yea, if he which but curſeth Satan, curſeth his owne ſoule, as it is, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 21.27. What doth he, that curſeth the Saints and deare children of God? Surely, their curſes ſhall bound back into their owne breſts, as the ſtones which <hi>Shimei</hi> threw at <hi>David</hi> did rebound upon <hi>Shimei,</hi> and ſplit his heart; yea, and at laſt knockt out his braines.</p>
            <p>Curſing mouthes are like ill made Peeces, which while men diſcharge at others, recoile in ſplinters upon their owne faces. Their words and wiſhes be but whirle-windes, which being breathen forth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe to the ſame place; <hi>Curſed be hee that curſeth thee, Gen.</hi> 27.29. Yea, hee ſhall be curſed with a witneſſe, for even <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which <hi>came to ſave the World,</hi> ſhall ſay unto them at the laſt day, <hi>Depart yee curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devill and his Angels, Matth.</hi> 25.41. Where they ſhall doe nothing but <hi>curſe for evermore, Revel.</hi> 16.11.21. And indeed, Who ſhould goe to Hell, if curſers ſhould be left out? Wherefore let all thoſe learne to bleſſe, that looke to be heires of the Bleſſing.</p>
            <p n="10">10. It is their <hi>uſe</hi> to <hi>threaten</hi> the religious, as all the men of <hi>Sodome threatned</hi> juſt <hi>Lot,</hi> that they would <hi>deale worſe with him then with the Angels, Gen.</hi> 19.9. <hi>Jehoram, Eliſha,</hi> ſaying, <hi>God doe ſo to me, and more alſo if the head of Eliſha ſhall ſtand on him this day,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.31. And thus <hi>Paul,</hi> before his converſion, <hi>breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out threatnings and ſlaughter againſt the Diſciples, Acts</hi> 9.1, 2.</p>
            <p>It were no living for godly men, if their hands were allowed to be as bloody as their hearts. But
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:153780:24"/>men and Devils are under the reſtraint of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
            <p>Neither are their words more ſwelling, or their deſignes more laviſh, then their atchievements be vaine, and their execution ſhort. <hi>Benhadad</hi> ſends great words unto the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as if it were nothing to conquer him: but ſtay the proofe, <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hadad</hi> flyes, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> perſues. Commonly they that leaſt can doe, beſt cavill, can and make the greateſt flouriſh.</p>
            <p>However, it is well for the innocent, that wicked men cannot keep their owne counſels as God fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their thoughts out of their owne mouthes, many times, even againſt their wils, for the good of his Children; as we may ſee in <hi>Eſau,</hi> when he purpoſed the death of <hi>Jacob;</hi> and in <hi>Saul,</hi> touching <hi>David;</hi> and in <hi>Jezabell,</hi> touching <hi>Eliſha;</hi> whoſe threats did preſerve them, whom they meant to kill. The wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power of God could have found evaſions for his Prophets, with their enemies greateſt ſecrecy: but now they need no other meanes of reſcue, then their owne lips. And it is a mercy (deſerving thanks) from God, that the lightning of anger in a cruell mans eyes, gives us warning of the thunderbolt in his hand.</p>
            <p>But this concernes us onely, when we are threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the potent: in other caſes, our beſt way will be to ſtand it out: for many a foe hath ſpoken brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who in the puſh hath made more uſe of his heeles, then of his hands: their threats being but like a boyes ſquib, that onely flaſhes, and cracks, and ſtinks, but is nothing.</p>
            <p n="11">11. It is their <hi>manner</hi> by <hi>ſubtlety</hi> to <hi>undermine</hi> the godly in talke, that they may <hi>betray</hi> them, as <hi>Saul</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153780:25"/>cauſed his ſervants to undermine <hi>David</hi> by flattery, thereby to worke his confuſion, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.17. And againe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21.25. thus thoſe falſe Prophets, and other enemies of the truth undermined <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> ſeeking every way to deſtroy him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.18. to the end of the Chap. And thus certaine of the Synagogue ſought to undermine <hi>Steven,</hi> that ſo they might have matter whereby to informe the Councell againſt him, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.9, 10.</p>
            <p>Their chiefe Principle is that of <hi>Lyſanders, Where the Lyons skinne will not ſuffice, we muſt add a ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Foxes.</hi> Whereupon, as intelligencers for States-men, mingle themſelves with all companies, but uſe their beſt art to keep themſelves concealed: ſo doe theſe, you may travell with ſuch an one as farre as the <hi>Indies;</hi> and yet finde the way into his heart a farther journey. For as High-way-men, lighting into true meaning company by the way, can talke of ſincere dealing, and uprightneſſe, againſt rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery and oppreſſion, to take off ſuſpition, till they ſpy their opportunity: ſo will they have ſemblan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of religion, pretend great love; yea, perhaps doe you a reall curteſie; but with the ſame intent that <hi>Saul</hi> gave <hi>Michall</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> which was onely to enſnare him.</p>
            <p>Like Fowlers and Anglers, when they meane to catch and ſnare us, they hide their nets, and cover their hookes with the pleaſing baites of flattery, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ſunſhine countenance upon cloudy thoughts: Yea, when they intend to murther, then ſpeake they faireſt; when deadly malice dives deepeſt into their hearts, then the ſmootheſt words floate in their mouthes, as no faces looke lovelyer then the painted.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:153780:25"/>
            <p>Now this kind of <hi>undermining</hi> they have borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Satan, that old Serpent, and arch-politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, who in the beginning uſeth this complement to our firſt Parents, <hi>Yee ſhall be as gods:</hi> when his drift was, to have them devils, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.5. Yea, he ſets them on worke, who never ceaſeth, either by himſelfe or by his ſervants to tempt and undermine the people of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. eſpecially at ſuch times, as they are, or ſhould be addreſſing themſelves to ſome nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble workes in performing the will of God, as we may ſee, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 1.6. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.14, 15. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.5, 6, 7, 10. <hi>Acts</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.1.</p>
            <p>But beware we truſt them not, for theſe Hypocrites never wound ſo deadly, as when they ſtroake us with a ſilken hand; being like the miſtaken lanthorne in Eighty eight; for under pretence of guiding, they will draw us into hazzard and loſſe among our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and whoſoever puts confidence in their words, ſhall finde them to reſemble ſinking floores, which will then fayle us, when our weight is on them. And ſo much of the <hi>Verball properties</hi> of this enmity.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>In the laſt place what are the</hi> Actuall Properties?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theirdly, wicked men <hi>actually</hi> manifeſt their enmity againſt the Religious in ſeven particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by <hi>geſture,</hi> as <hi>Goliah</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> when he looked upon him with a diſdainefull countenance, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.42. Which is a kind of brow-beating; and other wicked ones, who <hi>made mowes, and nodded the head at him, Pſalm.</hi> 22.7. <hi>Gaped upon him with their mouthes, as ramping and roaring Lyons, verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Guaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:153780:26"/>ſhaked their heads</hi> at him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.25. Thus <hi>Job</hi> complaines, That his enemies <hi>opened their mouthes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, Job.</hi> 16.10. And <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> that the ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing Idolaters <hi>gaped and thruſt out their tongues againſt the godly,</hi> in his time, <hi>Iſay</hi> 57.3, 4. And the Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in the Parable are ſaid to have an <hi>evilleye</hi> againſt the Maſter of the Vineyard, becauſe he was good, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.15. Many will ſpeak, that dare not ſtrike; and ſome will make mouthes, that feare to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>Now this of <hi>geſture</hi> is a ſilent foe; yet upon inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition made, I find none more guilty of the Serpents enmity, then he, who ſpeakes with his brow, and ſtriketh with his eyes; who becauſe his tongue can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not juſtly condemne a man, he will leave him ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of ill by ſilence, or ſome diſdainefull <hi>geſture:</hi> For, as his Majeſty ſaid moſt aptly and elegantly, <hi>As the tongue ſpeaketh to the eare; ſo the geſture ſpeaketh to the eye.</hi> And though ſuch an one be ſilent for want of words, yet he is not ſo for want of malice, even ſcoffes and nicknames, ſlander and curſing ſticks in his teeth, and onely dares not freely come forth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is guilty of his owne faultineſſe: and were he not a monſtrous coward, not daring to ſpeake or act for feare of Juſtice, there would be no dealing with him: Yet bad as he is, being dumbe, I finde him uncapable of a verdict, and ſo diſmiſſe him to leade the Van, which is both a puniſhment to himſelfe and thoſe that follow.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is their <hi>manner</hi> to <hi>withſtand</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> the doctrine which they are commanded by God to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver. Thus <hi>Zidkiah</hi> the falſe Prophet withſtood and contraried <hi>Michaiaes</hi> doctrine, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.24. The Prieſts, Prophets, and all the people, <hi>Jeremiahs,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Why haſt thou propheſied in the name of the Lord,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:153780:26"/>that this houſe ſhall be like Shilo, and this City ſhall be deſolate, and without an inhabitant? Jer.</hi> 26.8, 9. And thus <hi>Elimas</hi> the Sorcerer withſtood and contraried <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> in their preaching, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.8.</p>
            <p>And this is ſtill the manner of wicked men (being better acquainted with wrangling then reaſoning, and deeper in love with ſtrife then truth) even to cavill againſt the good word of God, and oppoſe the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, and what they cannot maintaine by reaſon, a feminine teſtineſſe ſhall outwrangle.</p>
            <p>Theſe night-birds know right well, that where the Sunne ſhines, there is ſmall place for them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: whence the Miniſters preaching is as great a vexation to them, as their converſation is to him: and in caſe he hath a fire in his tongne kindled with a coale from the <hi>Altar,</hi> they have a ſea of water in their hearts to quench it.</p>
            <p>But if ſome one be more ſpecially gifted in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing of ſinne, he is ſure to have treble oppoſition, if he moleſt Satan, and diſpoſſeſſe him of his ſtrong holds, Satan will moleſt him with a powder; all the drunkards in that Pariſh ſhall fall about ſuch a Miniſters eares; Yea, perhaps ſome neighbour Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that pretend gravity and good will to God, ſhall more then ſet them on: for vertue fares hardeſt oftentimes from ſuch as ſhould uphold her.</p>
            <p>Thus Satan and his inſtruments deale like our Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, who will ſet upon rich laden ſhips, but paſſe by thoſe that are empty.</p>
            <p>Nor are they to be appeaſed after they have once begun, for that which raſhneſſe and folly have brought forth, pride afterwards and contumacy ſhall main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the laſt gaſpe. Vſually an ill cauſe once un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, ſhall be maintained, though with blood.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:153780:27"/>Nay, rather then want cauſe, they will now hate ſuch a Miniſter, becauſe they have formerly hurt him: as many husbands hate their wives, onely becauſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have wronged them, or at leaſt love them the leſſe for their owne faults: all which they will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend with their tongues, though they condemne it with their conſciences.</p>
            <p>Which men are like thoſe wicked <hi>Jewes, Acts</hi> 13.45. who would neither beleeve the doctrine which <hi>Paul</hi> preacht, nor abide that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhould bee brought to the Faith of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> For they not only forbeare to heare ſuch a Miniſter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but will dehort all their familiars: In imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the high Prieſts, Scribes, and Phariſees, who in their owne opinion were too good, too wiſe, too holy to receive <hi>Chriſt</hi> into their company; and, not content to ſequeſter themſelves from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they diſdained alſo that he ſhould be converſant with Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and ſinners.</p>
            <p>Pride was ever envious and contumelious, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe adds ſo much to her owne reputation, as ſhe detracts from others: and indeede the twinckling ſtarres at the approach of the Sunne loſe their light, and after regaine it not, untill darkeneſſe be upon the deepe: Yea, the whiter the Swan is, the more black is the Crow thats by her.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They will <hi>combine themſelves</hi> together, and ſay devillſh plots to deſtroy the godly, as the new King of <hi>Aegypt</hi> with his people did againſt the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they perceived them to multiply ſo faſt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.9.10. Thus the hundred and twenty Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors combined together to worke <hi>Daniels</hi> overthrow <hi>Dan. 6.</hi> And thus <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Silver-ſmith, and the reſt of the craftſmen, which made gaine by the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:153780:27"/>ſilver Temples of <hi>Diana,</hi> combined themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to conſpire the death of <hi>Pauls</hi> campanions, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. And when <hi>Paul</hi> was reſcued by <hi>Lyſias,</hi> the next day there were more then forty of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> which bound themſelves by a curſe, ſaying, <hi>They would neither eate nor drinke, till they had killed Paul;</hi> in which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, the chiefe Prieſts and Elders were likewiſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, <hi>Act.</hi> 23.10.14.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If God be on our ſide, who can be againſt us?</hi> But S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> in opening of thoſe words, ſaith, Nay rather, <hi>Who is not againſt us, if God be with us?</hi> For, <hi>they caſt their heads together,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, with one conſent, and are confederate againſt God and his ſecret ones, imagining crafty counſell againſt them, ſaying, come, let us rout them out, &amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 83.3.4, 5.</p>
            <p>How wicked men agree in perſecuting the truth, and profeſſors thereof, we may ſee, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.26, 27. and <hi>Mark</hi> 14. where even old <hi>Annas,</hi> and that wicked bench of gray-headed <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> are content to break their ſleep to do miſchief, and make noon of midnight.</p>
            <p>As for the manner of their conſultations, they are lively expreſt by the Author of the booke of <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> who bringeth them in, ſaying thus, one to another, <hi>Come, let us lie in wait for the righteous, becauſe he is not for our turne, but is cleane contrary to our doings: bee up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bradeth us with our offending the Law: hee was made to reprove our thoughts; it grieveth us alſo to looke upon him, for his life is not like other mens, his wayes are of another faſhion, he vaunteth to have the knowledge of God, and counteth us as baſtards: he withdraweth himſelfe from our wayes as from filthineſſe; he commendeth the latter end of the juſt, and boaſteth that God is his Father. Wherefore let us ſee if his workes be true; let us prove and examine him with rebukes and torments; let us condemne him to a ſhamefull
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:153780:28"/>death.</hi> And then gives the reaſon: <hi>Such things do they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, for their owne wickedneſſe hath blinded them, and they doe not underſtand the myſteries of God, neither hope for the reward of righteouſneſſe, nor can diſcerne the honour of the ſoules which are faultleſse,</hi> Wiſd. 2.12. to 23.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>I, But what have they whereupon to ground their accuſations? For the religious mans life is commonly like</hi> Pauls, Philip. 3.6. unrebukeable, <hi>and</hi> he walketh in all the commandements and ordinances of the Law, without reproofe, <hi>as</hi> Zachary <hi>and</hi> Elizabeth <hi>did,</hi> Luke 1.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> He that ſtudies quarrels will eaſily find occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. When the Governours were reſolved that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> ſhould die, they ſoone found pretences: As ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it be a private Chriſtian, they will lie in wait to finde faults in him, and turne good into evill, and are of ſo prying an obſervation, that they will looke far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into his actions, then the beſt man would willingly have them ſearch.</p>
            <p>But being diſappointed of their hopes, heare what they ſay, We ſhall not find an accuſation againſt him, he is ſo faithfull, <hi>except we finde it concerning the law of his God, Dan.</hi> 6.5. And his punctuall obedience to Gods Lawes, and ſticking cloſe to the Word of truth, ſhall ſerve for a need.</p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, If he be a Miniſter, they will aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble together to heare him pray and preach, that ſo they may catch ſomething out of his mouth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they may accuſe him, as the Scribes and Phariſees dealth with our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.54. And thoſe Gòvernours with <hi>Daniel,</hi> wherein he ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpeake ſo warily, but they will finde matter enough to inſnare him, as the words ſhall be wreſted,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:153780:28"/>though indeed, to have a great audience onely ſhall be made crime enough: you know when the Jewes ſaw that a great company were at <hi>Pauls</hi> Sermon, they were filled with envy, and fell to contradiction and blaſphemy: <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45. And the <hi>high Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> when our Saviour was ſo flockt after ſayd among themſelves: perceive yee not, behold the World goeth after him, and if we let him thus alone, all men will beleeve in him, <hi>John</hi> 11.48. &amp; 12.19. they were like the dog in the manger, that will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eate Hay himſelfe, nor ſuffer the Horſe; yet they had a reaſon for it as theſe have: <hi>Rome</hi> thinkes that the Goſpels riſing, muſt needs be her falling, as when the day comes, the night muſt end. Indeed, opinion makes them coyne that for a reaſon, which others will not aſſent unto: Yea, what is truth to theſe men, is error to others more wiſe.</p>
            <p>And when once he is queſtioned, every one, like <hi>Jael</hi> to <hi>Sizera,</hi> will drive a nayle, to keep him from riſing againe.</p>
            <p>O the wicked mindes that many goe to Church withall, and the great dangers that Miniſters are lyable unto, did not God mightily ſupport them! many of their hearers being like that Lawyer, which ſtood up to tempt <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for they come not to be taught by him but to catch him.</p>
            <p>But what ſaith <hi>David? Though they have conceived miſcheife, and doe travell with wickedneſſe, yet they ſhall bring forth a lye,</hi> Pſal. 7.14. For <hi>the Lord breaketh their counſels, and bringeth their devices to naught,</hi> Pſal. 33.10. Yea, while the ungodly are whetting a knife to cut our throats, God is whetting a ſword to cut their throats. Shall the powder thinke to blow up the houſe, and ſcape it ſelfe from burning? No, it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:153780:29"/>is a true rule, that of evill premiſes doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a good concluſion, but from evill ſeeds come evill plants.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They are very proane to <hi>impriſon</hi> the godly, cauſe or no cauſe, As <hi>Ahab</hi> commanded <hi>Michaiah to be put into the priſon houſe, and fed with the bread of affliction and with the water of affliction,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.27. Thus the malicious Prieſts procured <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to be ſhut up in priſon, <hi>Jer.</hi> 36.5. And thus our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſhewing what entertainement the faithfull ſhould find in the World, foretelleth that wicked men <hi>ſhall lay hands on them, and deliver them up to the aſſemblies, and into priſons, bring them before Kings and Rulers, for his names ſake, Luke</hi> 21.12. As <hi>John Baptiſt, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Paul,</hi> and many other of the Apoſtles, were put into the common priſon by <hi>Herod,</hi> and the Synod of Prieſts, when they preacht in <hi>Chriſts</hi> Name, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.4 <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28.17. And 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23: And Ile warrant you, the common people were more glad of the Churches loſſe herein, then they would have been of their owne gaine.</p>
            <p>But why into priſon? Why not unto death? No thankes to Satan, nor his ſeede, they would deſtroy all. Yea, Why are not our Sanctuaries turned into Shambles, and our beds made to ſwimme with our bloods, but that the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath croſſed the confederacy of <hi>Balaak,</hi> and there wickedneſſe doth not proſper, their ſtudies are the pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts of our ruine, and the beſt they intend, is the deſtructions and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>through of Religion, or the religious, or both.</p>
            <p>Againe, Why theſe, and a thouſand more in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhut up in priſon? What was their delinquency? Even this, They were too good, too holy to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured. What was it but <hi>Joſephs</hi> goodneſſe, that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:153780:29"/>brought him to the ſtocks and Irons? And ſo of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah, Jeremiah,</hi> the Apoſtles, and all the Saints in ſucceding ages.</p>
            <p>And to ſpeake truly, this is a deepe point of pollicy in our adverſaries: for when all their arguments faile, by this meanes they get the better, and withall prevent further diſpute. In the midſt of their anger they this diſcretion, Stand not to argue, leſt thou be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and let the accuſed plead what hee can for his own innocencie: the Wolfe would anſwer the Lamb, <hi>Indeed thy cauſe is better then mine, but my teeth are better then thine, I will devoure thee:</hi> So the Devill puts off the Fox, and puts on the Lyon.</p>
            <p>Againe, we know the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one hath ſo much the leſſe light, by how much it is neer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the Sunne; yea, ſo long as the Sunne ſhines above the Horizon, the Moone is ſcarcely ſeene. And we uſe to ſay of <hi>Homer,</hi> that the dazling beames of his Sunne makes all other Poets, like little ſtars, looſe their light.</p>
            <p>This made <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> when he could not equall <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxenus</hi> in poetry, nor match <hi>Plato</hi> in diſcourſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the one to the ſtone-quarries, and ſell the other as a ſlave into the Ile of <hi>Agina.</hi> And out of like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, have the wicked alwayes dealt with the godly, even as <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate did by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, who tooke downe his Image in contempt, that he might ſet up his owne in the ſame place, and have the people worſhip it, which hee knew they would never doe, ſo long as the other was reverenc'd.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They often manifeſt their enmity againſt the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious by ſtriking them, as <hi>Zidkiah,</hi> the falſe Prophet, ſtrooke <hi>Michayah</hi> on the cheeke, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.24. thus <hi>Paſher</hi> ſtrooke <hi>Jeremiah, Ier.</hi> 20.2. And the Princes alſo, Chap. 37.15. And thus <hi>Ananias</hi> the high Prieſt cauſed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:153780:30"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> to be ſmitten on the mouth, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.2. and the <hi>Iewes</hi> whipt him five times with forty ſtripes ſave one, and others beat him with rods, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.24.25.</p>
            <p>And thus our rough adverſaries of <hi>Rome</hi> ſtopt our Martyrs mouthes, and refuted them, not with reaſons, nor by Law (for the Law hath no power to ſtrike the vertuous) but with fiſts.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Politiſians</hi> Rhetorick failes, <hi>Carters</hi> Logick muſt doe the fear. Their arguments are all Steele and Iron, they ſpeake daggers points: As <hi>Ioab</hi> diſcourſed with <hi>Amaza</hi> in the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Rib.</hi> So <hi>Zedikiah</hi> diſputed with the Prophet a word and a blow; yea, a blow without a word; for hee ſmote him firſt, and ſpake to him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards.</p>
            <p>Every falſe Prophet is like <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond, who threw Saint <hi>Peters</hi> keyes into the river <hi>Tiber,</hi> proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thenceforth <hi>he would uſe and helpe himſelfe with Saint Pauls ſword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in caſe they cannot have their wills, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble <hi>Achilles,</hi> who is fained to eate his owne heart, becauſe he might not be ſuffered to fight.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is uſuall with them to <hi>hurt</hi> and <hi>maime</hi> the godly: as the whole Congregation of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> would have ſerved thoſe true hearted Spyes, for ſeeking to appeaſe the tumult, and ſpeaking well of the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> had not the glory of the Lord appeared in the Tabernacle of the Congregation, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.10. Thus the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> put out <hi>Sampſons</hi> eyes, when they had bound him, <hi>Indg.</hi> 16.21. and thus the <hi>Iewes</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochia</hi> and <hi>Iconium</hi> hurt <hi>Paul,</hi> when they ſtoned him, and <hi>drew him out of the City, ſuppoſing he had beene dead, Act.</hi> 14.19. Neither have ſucceeding ages wanted <hi>Alexanders,</hi> who have done much hurt to Gods people: for not ſeldome when reaſon and rayling failed, have
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:153780:30"/>they come to plow-mans Logick, Gunpowder argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, open violence, taking up ſwords to ſtrike, or ſtones to caſt at us, though they incurre by it the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Law. Whereas religion makes wild beaſts civill; Atheiſme, and Impiety makes of wiſe men beaſts and fooles. How many have been knowne, like him in <hi>Aeſop,</hi> who willingly loſt one eye, that his fellow might looſe both?</p>
            <p>Yea, whereas the drift of ſuch an ones preaching, in caſe he be a miniſter, is to make them like him, in whoſe name they preach: contrarily, the very word of God, by accident, makes them degenerate into ſtocks and ſtones: for hearing but their ſinnes layd open, and the judgement due thereunto, they become ſo ſtupid and inſenſible of reaſon, that now, maugre all admonition, the quarrell muſt end in blood: Yea, away with ſuch a fellow from the earth, for it is not meet that he ſhould live, <hi>Acts</hi> 22.22.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And laſtly, It is their manner out of Enmity to <hi>ſlay the godly,</hi> as <hi>Doeg</hi> ſlew <hi>Ahimeleck</hi> and the reſt of the Prieſts, even fourſcore and five perſons, and <hi>Nob</hi> the City of Prieſts, whom he ſmote with the edge of the ſword, both man and woman, child and ſuckling, at <hi>Sauls</hi> command, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.19. Thus <hi>Jezabell</hi> ſlew all the Prophets of the Lord ſhe could find, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.4. And <hi>Herod,</hi> all the male children that were in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and all the coaſts thereof, from two yeares old and under, that he might make ſure worke with <hi>Chriſt, Mat.</hi> 2.16. And thus the inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> Gods owne people choſen out of all the World, uſed to make ſuch havock of their owne Prophets, that our Saviour bemoaning her caſe, cryeth out, <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, which killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt them which are ſent unto thee, &amp;c. Matthew</hi> 23.37.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:153780:31"/>
            <p>And thus it fares with the Saints and ſervants of God at this day, in ſuch places where wicked men may have their wils. Whereas thoſe Romiſh Doctors are appointed for the ſaving of many, they are all for deſtruction: like raſh Empiricks, they can cure no way, but by letting of blood; and hereupon they turne their Maſſing into maſſacring; the Schoole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Camp; Arguments, into Armes; teaching all their Proſelites diſmall concluſions: as it hath been no rare thing, for ſome of their Prieſts in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> raigne, when in arguments they have found the weakneſſe of their pens to fall to their penknives: In ſtead of arguments, they take up armes; and in ſtead of zeale and the ſpirituall word, they uſe fire and the ſword; yea, treaſons, are their beſt reaſons; the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inquiſition, is their Grammer; fire and fagot their rhetoricke; Fleete and fetters, their Logicke; the Canons roare, their muſick; poyſoning, their phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; Yea, their very building of the Church, is by blowing up of common-wealths; and in ſtead of figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for God, they fight againſt God and his Leive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant.</p>
            <p>And if at this day they catch but a Proteſtant in their net, it is a miracle if ever he ſcapes death, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making ſhipwrack of faith and a good conſcience. For if we will not obey them rather then God, they have a Law by which men ought to dye, a law like <hi>Draco's,</hi> written with blood, and ſealed with death. Of which their ſavage proceeding, there are many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be rendred.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they muſt doe the workes of their Father the Devill: <hi>he is a murtherer,</hi> and ſo his children are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to blood, <hi>John</hi> 8.44.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that their deeds of darkneſſe may not
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:153780:31"/>come to light. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> muſt be put to death, leaſt <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> adultry bee diſcovered, and himſelfe diſgraced. A living Curre you know, will doe more harme then a dead Lyon: And it is a ſure rule, that of Egges fryed in the pan come no ill Chickens.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the wicked through malice ſeeke by all meanes to cut off the godly, becauſe their ſinfull and wicked lives are reproved by their godly converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: neither can they follow their ſinnes ſo freely as they would, nor ſo quietly, without detection or check. Now if <hi>Abels</hi> good works reprove <hi>Caines</hi> evill deeds, let <hi>Caine</hi> but take away the cauſe, kill <hi>Abell,</hi> and the effect ſhall not follow.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, whereas the godly are too hard for them in diſputing: take <hi>Steven</hi> for an inſtance: they will be even with him, by caſting of ſtones, ſtop his mouth with brickbats, fetch arguments from the Shambles; and this they are ſure will doe, when all other hopes and helps fayle. So they make their party good, if not with arguments of reaſon, yet with argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of ſteel, and Iron. But this is a very hard way of conſuting.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, their glory and credit with the World is eclipſed, by ſuffering theſe which excell in vertue. This made <hi>Adrian</hi> and <hi>Nero</hi> to kill all ſuch as eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their glory by any demerit: and <hi>Mercine,</hi> you know, was murthered of her fellowes, becauſe ſhee did excell the reſt in beauty. Thus <hi>Herod,</hi> thought he could not be King, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould raigne. Yea, as though he had beene of the race of the <hi>Ottomans,</hi> he thought he could not raigne, except the firſt thing he did, he killed all the males in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> from two yeares old and under: And the <hi>Phariſees</hi> that they ſhould be deſpiſed, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> were regarded.</p>
            <p>And ſo much of the <hi>Actuall properties</hi> of this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:153780:32"/>
            <p>Qu. <hi>In how many of theſe kindes did our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelfe ſuffer (whoſe example hitherto you have omitted) in his owne perſon of the</hi> Jews, <hi>his Countrey men and kinſfolke; yea, of the chiefe Prieſts, Scribes and Phariſees, who were teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and expounders of the Law, and which ſate in</hi> Moſes <hi>Chaire?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> In every one of the 22. for as touching the Mentall Properties.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 They Envyed him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.15.</item>
               <item>2 They Contemned him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.55.</item>
               <item>3 They Rejoyced at him in his miſery and deſtreſſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.29.</item>
               <item>4 They Hated him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.7.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. Touching the Verball.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 They Murmured againſt him, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.2.</item>
               <item>2 They Miſconſtrued his actions &amp; intentions, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</item>
               <item>3 They Carryed tales of him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.14.</item>
               <item>4 They Gave divelliſh counſell againſt him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.20.</item>
               <item>5 They Scoft at him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.42.</item>
               <item>6 They Nicknamed him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.55.</item>
               <item>7 They Rayled on him, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.39.</item>
               <item>8 They Slandered him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.13.</item>
               <item>9 They Curſed him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</item>
               <item>10 They Threatned him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.53.</item>
               <item>11 They Vndermined him in talke, that they might accuſe him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.15.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="3">3. Touching the Actuall.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 They Vſed diſdainful geſtures before him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.29.39</item>
               <item>2 They VVithſtood and contraryed his Doctrine, <hi>Luke</hi> 5.21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.34.</item>
               <item>3 They Combined together and layd Plots to deſtroy him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.14.</item>
               <item>4 They Tooke him priſoner, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.57.</item>
               <item>5 They Smote him, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.64.</item>
               <item>6 They Hurt and wounded him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.29. <hi>Iohn</hi> 19 34.</item>
               <item>7 They Put him to death, even that curſed death of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:153780:32"/>Croſſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.35. That the Scriptures might be fulfilled which ſaith, <hi>And thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele;</hi> for all that he ſuffered was but in his <hi>Humanity,</hi> and ſo no more then the bruiſing of his <hi>heele.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And why all this? Not for any evill they found in him; for their owne words are, <hi>He hath done all things well, Mark</hi> 7.37. He hath done, ſuch was his power; all things, ſuch was his wiſedome; well, ſuch was his goodneſſe: and yet crucified, and abuſed every way he muſt be. It was indeed for his zeale, purity and holineſſe, and becauſe his life and practice was cleane contrary to theirs, his Doctrine too powerfull and pure for ſuch carnall hearts to imbrace or endure. So that it is plaine, and all men may ſee, who are not dead in ſenſe, how it would fare with us, might our enemies, the ſame Seede of the Serpent have their wils.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What</hi> uſes <hi>may this ſerve for, which hath been ſpoken touching the properties of this enmity, and our Saviours ſuffering?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> Firſt, by this taſte of its fruits learne we to <hi>deteſt</hi> them all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it may ſerve to informe every man, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be of the <hi>Serpents ſeed,</hi> a child of the Devill, as he came into the world, or regenerate, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the womans Seed, a child of God and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt: for as our Saviour ſaith, ſpeaking of falſe Prophets, <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall know them:</hi> ſo I of the ſeed of the Serpent, and children of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, By theſe 22. fruits of enmity you ſhall know them, aſwell as you ſhall know the life by breathing, or the day by its light. Wherefore all ye that read, reflect and caſt your eyes on theſe examples, which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:153780:33"/>are ſuch lively emblemes and repreſentations of your ſelves, if you be the Sepents ſeed, and yet in your ſins. Yea, let it make you tremble; for know aſſuredly, that if this ſpawne of enmity, formerly ſpoken of, remaine in you; if any of theſe wayes you perſecure <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his members, or but hate the good, becauſe they will not be ſo evill as you are, you have not caſt off this ſerpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine quallity, which you drew from the loynes of old <hi>Adam;</hi> but it is an infallible ſigne, that you are of the Serpents ſeed, children of the Devill, enemies to God, and all goodneſſe, the brethren of <hi>Cayne,</hi> yea, <hi>Cayne</hi> himſelfe in another perſon, and without repentance, your portion ſhall be with <hi>Cayne,</hi> and the reſt of that curſed crue.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, doth any conſcionable Chriſtian find himſelfe hated and perſecuted by ungodly men for weldoing, for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake, for Religion and for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſake? Let him be comforted; for it is a manifeſt ſigne, and a notable ſtrong evidence, that he is of the Womans Seed, regenerate and borne a new, the child of God, a member of <hi>Chriſts</hi> myſticall body, and an heire of eternall life.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, theſe examples being written to admoniſh us, <hi>upon whom the ends of the world are come,</hi> may <hi>inform</hi> the godly what they are to <hi>expect</hi> from the world: Shall any hope to be free from ſuffering, or thinke it a ſtrange thing, when he doth ſuffer for well doing, when our Saviour-<hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe ſuffered ſo much as he did, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the onely begotten Sonne of God, full of grace and truth?</hi> No, <hi>the Diſciple is not above his Maſter, nor the ſervant above his Lord:</hi> If they have perſecuted <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they will perſecute you alſo, <hi>John</hi> 15.20. <hi>If they have called the Maſter of the houſe Beelzebub, how much more them of his houſhold? Mat.</hi> 10.25. Yea, ſenſleſſe were it once to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:153780:33"/>thinke, that the ſame enmity which ſpared not to ſtrike at the Head, will forbeare the weakeſt and remoteſt limbe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore arme thou us, O God, with an expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that evill which we cannot avoyd, yea, make thou us as ſtrong as Satan and his inſtruments are mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and then let them doe their worſt.</p>
            <p>And ſo much of the <hi>kinds</hi> and <hi>properties</hi> of his enmity.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Cauſes.</head>
               <p>Qu. <hi>What are the</hi> Cauſes <hi>why wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men thus hate and perſecute the religious?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They are ſo many, that the time would be too ſhort, or this Treatiſe too long, if I ſhould ſpeake of every one, yea, or relate halfe of what is requiſite to to be ſpoken of each; for they require whole Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes, beſides inſtructions, if they exceed, are wont, as nailes to drive out one another.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Then ſelect out the principall, I meane, ſuch as in regard of our edification, are moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoovefull for us to know. And leſt the pages ſhould ſtill grow, as fiſh, into a multitude, garble your no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and give us onely the marrow of the matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Cauſes</hi> beſt deſerving our diſcovery, and the worlds notice, I take to be Eleaven:</p>
               <p>Firſt, a maine <hi>Cauſe</hi> why wicked men hate and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the godly, is the <hi>contrariety</hi> of their <hi>natures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>How contrary are they?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As <hi>contrary</hi> and <hi>oppoſite</hi> one to the other, as are God and the Devill: for the one are <hi>Children of God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. And <hi>partake of the Divine Nature,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. Being <hi>begotten, Iames</hi> 1.18.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:153780:34"/>And <hi>borne a new of God, Joh.</hi> 1.13. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>by the immortall ſeed of the word, Iames</hi> 1.18. And the <hi>ſpirits powerfull working with it, Ioh.</hi> 3.5.8. whereby they are become <hi>like God in holineſſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. And <hi>not chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren onely, but heires alſo, even the heires of God, and heires annexed with Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8.17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being his <hi>brethren, Rom.</hi> 8.29. <hi>Members of his body,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. <hi>Bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh, Epheſ.</hi> 5.30. having <hi>his Spirit dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in them, Rom.</hi> 8.9. <hi>to witneſſe with their ſpirits, that they are the children of God, verſ.</hi> 16. And being <hi>Temples of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19.</p>
               <p>And the other are the <hi>Seed of the Serpent, and children of the Devill,</hi> and ſo partake of his nature, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.8.10.12.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.70. and 8.44. and 14.30. and 16.11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.38.39. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and 5.3. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. to the end, and 5.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.18. <hi>Titus</hi> 3.3. to 8. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.10.25. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3.5.6. which being ſo, they muſt needs be very <hi>contrary,</hi> and if contrary, no marvell they ſhould ſo ill agree, although God had not proclaimed an enmity between them.</p>
               <p>For there can be no amity, where there is no ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy; No reconciling of the Wolfe and the Lambe; the winds and the ſea; No neighbourhood, no aliance, no conjunction is able to make the curſed ſeed of the Serpent, and the bleſſed ſeed of the Women ever agree: For fire and water, light and darkneſſe, heaven and hell are not more <hi>contrary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One blood, one belly, one houſe, one education could never make <hi>Cayne</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> accord, <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau, Iſack</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> at one. Yea, though they be man and wife, parent and childe, yet if they be not like, they will not like, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14.15. And indeed, what is the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall ſympathy to the ſpirituall antipathy? Can there
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:153780:34"/>be ſuch a parity betweene the parent and the child, the husband and the wife, as there is a diſparity betweene God and Satan? No certainly.</p>
               <p>A wicked man can agree with all that are wicked, be they <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Turkes,</hi> or <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> prophane and looſe perſons, civill or morall men, for all theſe agree with him in blindneſſe and darkneſſe: as who feeles the ſmart of their tongues, or hands? not the Idolator or vile perſon, not the profeſſed Atheiſt, the Canker fretting Arminian, or ſtate betraying Jeſuite: For with all theſe they are haile fellow well met. But with ſincere Chriſtians and Practicers of piety, he can never agree: the religious ſhall be ſure of oppoſition, becauſe their light is <hi>contrary</hi> to his darkneſſe; grace in the one is a ſecret diſgrace to the other.</p>
               <p>Yea, let wicked men be at never ſo much odds one with another, yet they will concurre and joyne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the godly. As for example, <hi>Edom</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael, Moab</hi> and the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>garens, Gebal</hi> and <hi>Ammon, Amma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> the men of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Aſsur</hi> had each ſeverall gods; yet all conſpired againſt the true God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.5. to 9. <hi>Manaſſes againſt Ephraim, and Ephraim againſt Manaſses; but both againſt Juda. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> two enemies, will agree, ſo it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Chriſt:</hi> they will fall in one with another, to fall out with God. The <hi>Saduces, Phariſees,</hi> and <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> were Sectaries of divers and adverſe factions, all differing one from another; and yet all theſe joyne together againſt our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. The <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, Cyrenians, Alexandrions, Cilicians</hi> and <hi>Aſians,</hi> differ they never ſo much, will joyne in diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Steeven, Acts</hi> 6.9. <hi>Herod</hi> neither loved the <hi>Jews,</hi> nor the <hi>Jewes Herod;</hi> yet both are agreed to vex the Church.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:153780:35"/>
               <p>I cannot thinke of a fitter embleme of a naturall man, then Lime, which agreeth well with all things that are dry and of it's owne nature; but meeting with water, a thing directly oppoſite, it breaks, burnes, ſwels, ſmokes, crackles, skips and ſcatters: ſo nature will give a man leave to be any thing, ſave a ſound Chriſtian, and agree with all others, be their conditions never ſo contrary, provided they agree in the maine, are all ſeed of the ſame Serpent. But let the naturall man meet with one that is ſpirituall, they agree like heate and cold; if one ſtayes, the other flies; or if both ſtay, they agree like two poyſons in one ſtomacke, the one being ever ſicke of the other, be they never ſo neer alyed. As how many a wife is ſo much the more hated, becauſe a zelous wife? How many a child leſſe beloved, becauſe a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious child? How many a ſervant leſſe reſpected, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a godly ſervant? And no marvell; for though they dwell in the ſame houſe, yet they belong to two ſeverall kingdomes; and albeit they both remaine on earth, yet they are governed by two ſeverall lawes, the ones burguſhip being in Heaven, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. And the other, being a denizon, belonging to Hell: as <hi>Iriſh-men</hi> are dwellers in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but denizons of <hi>England;</hi> and governed by the Statutes of this kingdome.</p>
               <p>Neither is this of theirs an <hi>ordinary hatred,</hi> but the moſt bitter, exorbitant, unlimited, &amp; unplacable of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>No ſuch concord, no ſuch diſcord,</hi> ſaith one of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>as that which proceeds from Religion.</hi> My name, ſaith <hi>Luther, is more odious unto them, then any thief, or murtherer:</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was more deteſtable to the <hi>Iewes</hi> then <hi>Barra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas. Behold,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, mine enemies, for they are many, and they hate me with a cruell batred, Pſal.</hi> 25.19. yea, ſo cruell, that it makes their teeth gnaſh, and their hearts burſt againe, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.54. which made the Truths adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaties
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:153780:35"/>give Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſtripes above meaſure, 2 Cor, 11.2, 3. And the Heathen Emperours to deviſe ſuch cruell tortures, for all thoſe which but profeſt themſelves Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Yea, agreement in ſome points, when there are differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the maine, does but advance hatred the more: Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Reigne of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> and the Butchery over all <hi>France</hi> of above two hundred thouſand Proteſtants; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the many thouſands of late yeares: Yea, aske from Eaſt to Weſt, from one Pole to the other; ſearch all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords under Heaven, if ever there was the like of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Powder-Plot.</p>
               <p>You cannot anger a wicked man worſe, than to doe well: Ye, hee hates you more b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tterly for this, and the cred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t you gaine thereby, than if you had cheated him of his Patrimony, with your owne diſcredit. But that there is no hatred ſo virulent and bitter, as that which is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by vertuous living, and profeſſing of CHRISTS Name, our Saviour Himſelfe proves copiouſly, <hi>Matthew</hi> 10. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>Wherein conſists their</hi> unlikeneſſe <hi>and</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chiefly in foure particulars; thou hindeed there bee more differences betweene the Children of God and the children of the Devill, than there are betweene men and beaſts.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they exceedingly differ in their judgments touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wifedom, 1 Cor. 1.18.20, 23. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 14. and 4.10. Luke 6.27. to 36. Acts 26.24. Wiſd. 5.4. Gen. 41.8. Iob 5.13. Proverbs 28.11. Ierem. 4.22. 1 Cor. 3.19. Exodus 1.10. Ioſhua 9.4. Titus 3.9. Proverbs 10. verſe 18. Rom. 16. ver. 19.</p>
               <p>Happineſſe, Luke 6.26. and 8.13. Iames 4.4. Marke 16, 16. Iohn 3.16, 18. and 8.34, 36. Romans 6.16, 18.22. Pſal. 2.3, 4. and 10.3. and 12.4. 2 Tim. 2.26. Mal. 3.15. Revel. 3.17. 1 Theſ. 5.3.</p>
               <p>Fortitude, Prov. 28.1, 2. Rev. 13.6, 7. and 12, 13, 17. Mar. 13.9. Acts 7.52. Matth. 10.28. Galathians 4.29. Iohn 16.2.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:153780:36"/>
               <p>Sinne, Luke 16.15. Prov. 13.19. Marke 7.5, 11, 12.13. Luke 7.33, 34. Matth. 7.14. 1 Peter 4.18. Pſalm. 35.13.16</p>
               <p>Holines, Acts 26.9. Exo. 8 26. 1 Cor. 4.10. and 2.14 Pro. 13.19. Pſal. 14.1. Ier. 44.16. to 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Yea, they are of a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate judgment touching actions and perſons, ſay 5.20. and ſo ſpeake, thinks and doe all by contraries, like <hi>Helioga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> who wore ſhooes of Gold, and Rings of Leather, or the Blackmoores who judge of beautie by contraries. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reade their words as Schollers do Hebrew, backward, and you have the meaning: for inſtance doe they call thee Puritan as nothing more frequent in their mouthes, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by it Saint for a Chriſtian indeed (as thou art) is a Puritan in the devils language and a Chriſtian in name on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as ſuch an one is) is an Atheiſt in Gods language.</p>
               <p>Secondly, They no leſſe differ in their Paſſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Love, Pſal. 119.57, 72. and 17, 14.</p>
               <p>Feare, Prov. 28.1, 2. 1 Tim. 4.1. Rom. 2.14 15.</p>
               <p>Anger, Acts 7.52. to 60. and 5.30. to 34. Prov. 12.10. Rev. 18.19, 20.</p>
               <p>Ioy, 1 Pet. 2.7, 8. Ioh 3.15. Matth. 11.19. And the like, which for brevities ſake I forbeare.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they differ no leſſe in Practice, and this breeds many quarrels: as what more common, than for all ſorts and kinds of men to hate, ſcorne, perſecute, reproach, revile, accuſe ſlander and condemne the Religious, becauſe their owne workes are evill and wicked, and the others good, holy, and righteous. Wherefore ſlew <hi>Caine</hi> his brother, ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> but becauſe his owne Workes were ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, and his brothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s good? 1 Iohn 3.12. Why was <hi>Joſeph</hi> accuſed of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Miſtreffe for an Adulterer, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon committed to priſon, but becauſe hee would not be an Adulterer like her? <hi>Geneſis</hi> 39. Yea, it was his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coloured Coate, compoſed of all kindes of graces and bleſſings that formerly procured his Brethrens hate. And what is it that <hi>Jobs</hi> Wife expoſtulates with him about, but
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:153780:36"/>his integrity? As if ſhe tooke it ill, that he tooke it no worſe: his patience made her impatient. Wherefore was holy <hi>David,</hi> as himſelfe complaines, almoſt in every <hi>Pſalme,</hi> Had in deriſion, hated, ſlandered, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled, contemned and made a proverbe and ſong of the drunkards, and other wicked men which ſate in the gate, but becauſe <hi>he follewed the things which were good and pleaſing unto God, and in him put his truſt? Pſal.</hi> 11.2. and 22.6, 7, 8. and 37.14. and 69.10, 11, 12. And laſtly (for I might be endleſſe in the proſecution of this) Why were all the juſt, in <hi>Solomons</hi> time, had in abhominations and mockt of the wicked, but becauſe they were <hi>upright in their way, and holy in their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, Prov,</hi> 29.27. Or thoſe numberleſſe Martyrs, whoſe ſoules Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw under the Altar (<hi>Revel.</hi> 6.9.) killed, but <hi>for the Word of God, and for the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony which they maintained?</hi> And the Maſter himſelfe, not for any evill as themſelves are forced to confeſſe, <hi>Marke</hi> 7.37. which examples ſufficiently prove; that all wicked men are like the women of <hi>Lemnos,</hi> who when they had every one ſlaine their husbands and kinſmen, exiled <hi>Hypſipyle</hi> the Kings daughter, for that ſhe alone ſaved her Father alive. That great Dragon the Devill, and theſe his Subjects, make warre and are wroth with none but <hi>the Woman, and the remnant of her Seed, which keep the Commandements of God and have the teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt, Revel.</hi> 12.17.</p>
               <p>But to apply this to our ſelves. I would faine know, whether the power of godlineſſe, the ſincere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> according to the Vow which we made in Baptiſme, all kind of purity and holineſſe, doth not live in perſecution amongſt us, as Proteſtants doe in <hi>Spaine?</hi> Is it not a capitall crime to be vertuous? Is not the name of an honeſt man, who
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:153780:37"/>makes conſcience of his wayes, growne odious? Is not circumſpect walking, the zeale of Gods glory in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the beſt things, frequent hearing of Sermons, ſinging of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> holy conference, brotherly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, &amp;c. counted a vice, and that vice called <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſme?</hi> And muſt not he who is called a <hi>Puritan,</hi> be derided, hated, perſecuted, ſlandered and laught to ſcorne? how many may complaine with <hi>Ieremy,</hi> that becauſe they live a godly life themſelves, and call upon others to doe the ſame, they are curſed of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, and counted contentious? <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.10. Yea, let but a ſparke of fervent devotion breake cut in a Family, all the reſt are up in clamors; as when Bels ring diſorderly, every man is ready with his bucket to quench the fire; diſgraced he muſt be for a <hi>Puritan,</hi> but onely by <hi>Laodiceans.</hi> Indifferency ſtrives to daſh zeale out of countenance, The reaſon is, whereſoever <hi>Chriſt</hi> comes, there will be oppoſition. When <hi>Chriſt</hi> was borne, all <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was troubled, and <hi>Herod</hi> cut the throats of all the children in <hi>Bethlehem:</hi> ſo when <hi>Chriſt</hi> is borne in any man, the ſoule is in an uproare, and Satan with his iuſtruments are ready to kil in him every good motion, though it bee never ſo little a Babe.</p>
               <p>That which the Ancients did chiefly admire (<hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse</hi>) we doe moſt of all contemne: for is not the godly man more deſpiſed for his godlineſſe, then the wicked for his wickedneſſe? Are not the members of <hi>Chriſt</hi> more hated, and worſe intreated by us, then the limbes of the Devill? What ſuppreſſing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing is there of Hels, and <hi>Romes</hi> chiefeſt adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, under the aſperſion and pretence of <hi>Puritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas if the ſame men, would but bare them
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:153780:37"/>company in their ſinnes, be drunke, ſweare, temporiſe, contemne holineſſe, miſpend their time, haunt Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes and Tavernes, play the good fellowes, and doe as the reſt doe, they ſhould have the approbation and good word of the greateſt number; yea, if they would not be preciſe in their actions, nor reprove others for their evill courſes; if they would not ſpeake againſt pluralities, Non-reſidents, lazy and good-fellow Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, who either ſtarve or quite neglect, or elſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead their flockes; if they would but be prophane and wicked, and make no bones of ſinne, their malice would ceaſe, and we ſhould not have a Puritane in all the world.</p>
               <p>As let me appeale from th ir tongues to their hearts, and from their mouthes to their conſciences, whether this be not the greateſt cauſe of their quarrell, We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to pledg them in their wicked cuſtomes. For may not all ſee (ſaving ſuch as the Prince of darkneſſe hath blind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d) that thoſe, for the moſt part, whom the world ſpeakes ſo baſely of, are b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore men, in reſpect of any ſcandalous offences or open crimes, unblameable, and may ſay with the Lamb, whom they follow, <hi>Which of you can rebuke me of ſinne,</hi> though with <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 1.15. they thinke themſelves the worſt of ſinners? And doe not their adverſaries know, that the men whom they terme <hi>Puritanes,</hi> are honeſter men, and more righteous then themſelves, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was forc'd to confeſſe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Moſes? Exod.</hi> 10.16, 17. And <hi>Saul</hi> touching <hi>David?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.21. yea, I know they are perſwaded well of them, even when they ſpeake moſt to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, though I expect not they ſhould uſe them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. We know <hi>Pilate</hi> judged <hi>Chriſt</hi> guiltleſſe, but yet he put him to death. And <hi>Feſtus</hi> acknowledged that <hi>Paul</hi> was without crime, yet he left him in priſon. I
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:153780:38"/>dare ſay <hi>Tertullus</hi> knew that he lyed, when he called <hi>Paul a peſtilent fellow:</hi> his conſcience could not chooſe but anſwer him, Thou lyeſt in thy throat <hi>Tertullus, Paul</hi> is an honeſter man then thy ſelfe. And muſt not theſe mens conſcinces tell them, that the ſame they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe ſo, are in their lives the moſt unreproveable of the land? Yea, I will appeale to their greateſt adverſaries, whether the Proteſtant at large, or thoſe who are called <hi>Puritanes,</hi> be of the pureſt religion, and moſt reformed to the Primitive Church? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or not ſeldome are wicked mens judgements forced to yeeld unto that truth, againſt which their affections maintaine a rebeilion: And yet, as if they would ſtamp Gods Image on the Divels droſſe, and the Divels image on Gods ſilver, they juſtifie thoſe actions and perſons, which God condemnes, and condemne thoſe which he juſtifies.</p>
               <p>True, theſe enemies to holineſſe ſpare not to caſt aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on us; elſe how ſhould they worke their wills? How ſhould <hi>Naboth</hi> be cleanly put to death, if he be not firſt accuſed of blaſphemy? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.13. and the like of <hi>Joſeph, Eliah, Jeremiah, Suſanna, Paul, Steeven,</hi> and our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe. But if you marke it, they are as guilty of the crimes whereof they be accuſed, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was, in forcing of his Miſtris, or as <hi>Naboth</hi> and the reſt were, of thoſe things which were laid to their charge.</p>
               <p>I ſpeake not of thoſe monſters, thoſe white devills, who make Religion a ſtalking horſe to villany. I know too many diſhonour God, by wearing of his livery. But what was Satan to the children of God, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.6. though he thruſt himſelfe into their company? Or what wiſe man will tax all the Apoſtles, becauſe one was a <hi>Iudas.</hi> To argue, becauſe ſome are ſo and ſo, therefore the reſt are alike, is a ſapleſſe reaſon, only becomming a foole.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:153780:38"/>
               <p>Yet moſt men are ſuch fooles, or rather brute beaſts, <hi>led with ſenſualitty, and made to be taken and deſtroyed,</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes, who becauſe they <hi>love to ſpeake evill of the way of truth,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.12. If they ſee but an hypocrite diſcover himſelfe, they not onely harden themſelves in their ſinnes, and, as it were, breake their owne necks at this ſtumbling blocke, being Satans trap, ſet on purpoſe to catch their blind ſoules in, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all the reſt of his profeſſion to be ſuch as hee is, ſave that they diſſemble their hypocriſie more cloſly &amp; cunningly; which is as equal and juſt, as it was for <hi>Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> to murther all the <hi>Sechemites</hi> for the offence only of <hi>Hamors</hi> Son. But as all are not thievs that dogs bark at; ſo all are not hypocrites which they terme ſo.</p>
               <p>Indeed, as all our enemies are not alike witty, ſo they are not alike malicious; for ſome tranſcend this way, as <hi>Doeg</hi> did the reſt of <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervants ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, you ſhall know ſuch an one by theſe few markes; his hatred is ſo inveterate and univerſall, that he ſpends all his wit in frothy ſcoffes, and invectives againſt the whole people of God? and as if the doore were not wide enough except he ſet open all the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and brake downe the walls to let in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious ayre, his tongue ſcrues ſomething againſt the religious into all diſcourſes; and when his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention failes, it ſhall be ſupplyed with what he hath heard: for as the Papiſts never found any error ſpued out by the Ancients, but they have licked it up, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly to abuſe the ſame: ſo he never heares of any ſcoffe, ſlander, or divelliſh invective formerly deviſed, but he licks it up, that he may ſpit it out againe in the face of ſome profeſſor, or on the other fide poyſon thoſe with whom he doth converſe; being to his company like a mad dog, that ſo biteth every one he meets, that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:153780:39"/>they become mad too, and as apt to bite others as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; or in caſe he meets with another like himſelfe in wit and malice, it may be ſaid of them, as <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſpake of two ill conditioned women, when hee ſaw them talking, <hi>See how the Viper and the Aſpe are changing poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> And nothing ſo ticles the ſpleene, or glads the heart of ſuch, as that diſcourſe which may moſt ſhame profeſſion, diſgrace Religion, and diſhonour God. But, O that ever thoſe tongues, which dare call God Father, ſhould ſuffer themſelves thus to be moved and poſſeſſed by that uncleane ſpirit! Or that ever the Church ſhould owne ſuch for her children. In the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, the Church would have denied her bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to ſuch a Sonne, that ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d have thought himſelfe diſparaged by ſerving <hi>Chriſt</hi> and wearing of his livo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, although he had not ſcoft at others: yet this man flatters himſelfe that he is a Chriſtian; yea, you cannot beat him from it, but that he is as good a Chriſtian as the preciſeſt, and ſhall goe to heaven as ſoone. But let him that reads, conſider whether it be not a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing, to lend to Satan the heart for deviſing, the tongue for uttering, and the eare for hearing of calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and all this to diſgrace the grace of God in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and make it frutleſſe to themſelves and others. O impiety to be abhorred: Such ſport on earth is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſport for the fiends in hell, and let them looke to it, for ſuch joyes may chance to coſt them eternall mourning; yea, certainly, if the infernall <hi>Tophet</hi> be not for them (in caſe they repent not) it can challenge no gueſts; for I may well ſay unto ſuch an one, Many ſinners have done wickedly, but thou ſurpaſſeſt them all; thine is ſuch a ſuperlative, ſuch a ſoule-murthering ſinne, that no other ſinne can parallell it.</p>
               <p>But thou haſt plenty of excuſes to pacify thy blinded
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:153780:39"/>and benummed conſcience: Yea, thou wanteſt not ſome carnall reaſons to make it good, as an eaſie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention may put falſe matters into true Sylogiſmes: And amongſt the reſt, thou wouldeſt not have men <hi>ſingular:</hi> wherefore that they may have leſſe zeale and more temper, thou ſeek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt to alay their heate with frumps and ſcoffs, and taunts, and jeeres; as how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten doe we heare remiſſe profeſſors ſtrive to choake all forward holineſſe and zeale by commending the <hi>golden meane?</hi> For carnall men (who cleave as cloſe to cuſtome, and example of the greateſt number, as clay to a Cart wheele) thinke every one exorbitant, that walketh not after their rule, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.4. As the <hi>Sodomites</hi> thought of <hi>Lot, Gen.</hi> 19.9. the hundred and twenty <hi>Governours</hi> of <hi>Daniel, Dan.</hi> 6.11. and the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi> of <hi>Shadrach, Meſhech,</hi> and <hi>Abednego, Dan.</hi> 3 8. to 30. <hi>Daniel</hi> of all <hi>Darius</hi> his ſervants was ſo bold as to pray three times a day, not in contempt of the King of <hi>Babylons</hi> decree, but in zeale and obedience to the God of Heavens command: the Governours ſtranging at it, accuſe him, and ſay, this <hi>Daniel</hi> which is of the captivity, regardeth not thee O King, nor the decree which thou haſt ſigned; but doth ſo and ſo: wherefore command we pray thee, that he be caſt into the Lyons den, for no decree, nor ſtatute which the King eſtabliſheth may be altered, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. Againe what diſorder is this that I heare of you, ſaith <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> to <hi>Shadrach, Meſhech,</hi> and <hi>Ahednego:</hi> will not you ſerve my gods, nor worſhip the golden Image that I have ſet up, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.14. who anſwer no, be it knowne unto thee O King, we are not carefull to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thee in this matter: they were all as ſtiffe as if they had eaten a ſtake, and they could not bow to an Idoll: as the godly have beene in all ages, not being
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:153780:40"/>able to wheele with the times. Yea, they that truely feare <hi>God</hi> are uſually as immoveable as the Sun in its courſe, becauſe they thinke, and ſpeake, and live by rule, and not by example, and hold themſelves as faſt tyed, as if they had the oath given them, which the <hi>Aegyptian Kings</hi> ſolemnly preſented to their Judges, <hi>not to ſwerve from their conſciences,</hi> what command ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they ſhould receive from rhemſelves to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Which ſtrictneſſe is a great eye-ſore to carnall men: who hate ſingularity, almoſt as they doe ſanctity, which makes them to cry it downe.</p>
               <p>Now this imputation of ſingularity, and their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling the meane, is a cunning diſcouragement, but it is the Devils Sophiſtry; for the meane of vertue, is betweene two kindes, not betweene two degrees: it is a meane grace, that loves a meane degree of grace.</p>
               <p>Yet this is the onely ſtaffe, with which the World beates all that are better then themſelves. What will you be <hi>ſingular?</hi> Or are you wiſer then all? Or what is this but want of diſcretion? And to ſpeake truth, that which worldly men call diſcretion, eates up all true wiſedome: There diſcretion and moderate ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, devoures all true honeſty, and goodneſſe. But ſhall <hi>Lot</hi> leave his righteouſneſſe for ſuch an imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>ſingularity?</hi> Or ſhall he not depart <hi>Sodom,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the whole City thinkes it better to ſtay there ſtill? Shall <hi>Noah</hi> leave building the <hi>Arke,</hi> and ſo him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his houſhold periſh, becauſe all the World elſe, thinkes him haire-brayned? Or muſt the name of a <hi>Puritan,</hi> diſhearten us from the ſervice of <hi>God?</hi> No, but as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in his Apollogie, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.14. <hi>after the way which they call Herefie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers:</hi> ſo we in this caſe, After the way
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:153780:40"/>which prophane men call <hi>Puritaniſme,</hi> let my ſoule deſire to ſerve <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ob. <hi>I grant (will the more moderate world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſay) in ſuch caſes wherein the word of God is expreſſe, ſingularity is not lawfull onely, but laudable: But (which makes my ſpleene riſe) they will not conforme to things indifferent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> A ſeduced heart deceives thee in ſo ſaying, why elſe doſt thou caſt the ſame aſperſions, upon ſuch as are conformable.</p>
               <p>But admit they onely are thornes in thine Eyes, doſt thou well to hate all that are not of thy owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or that have tenderer conſciences then thy ſelfe? No, for honeſt and good men may differ in opinion, not onely in things trivyall, but in matters of great moment; provided, they agree in the <hi>fundamentall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Catholique faith,</hi> and yet may, and ought to continue brotherly love and communion, as members of the ſame myſticall body: as many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples witneſſe, both of eminent Chriſtians, and Fathers of the Church: as alſo our Saviours words, who ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the fundamentall poynts, penneth the league thus, <hi>He that is not with us, is againſt us,</hi> but of poynts not fundamentall thus, <hi>He that is not againſt us, is with us.</hi> Whereas theſe differ from thee (if thou beeſt a true Proteſtant as thou wouldeſt be thought to be) in nothing materiall, for there is a vaſt difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene another diſcipline, and another doctrine: and they little differ, that agree in matter. Onely their conſciences are not ſo large as thine: and thou think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thoſe things indifferent, which they cannot aſſent unto; though they take more paines to ſatisfie and informe themſelves then thou doſt. But admit they be
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:153780:41"/>things of an indifferent nature, even actions of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency, when once they are felt to trench upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, lay deep obligations upon the ſoul, even whiles they are moſt ſlighted by careleſſe hearts: there being no leſſe difference in <hi>conſciences,</hi> then <hi>ſtomacks,</hi> of which ſome will digeſt the hardeſt meates, and turne over ſubſtances not in their nature edible, whiles others ſurfeite of the lighteſt food, and complaine even of dainties.</p>
               <p>And indeed, every gracious heart is in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſcrupelous, and finds more ſafety in <hi>feare,</hi> then in <hi>preſumption:</hi> And certainely in caſes of a doubtfull and queſtionable nature, it is ever good to take the ſureſt ſide, and which drawes neereſt to probability. Many things are of ſo queſtionable a nature, that much may be ſaid on either ſide: Now if I chooſe that ſide on which I am ſure I ſhall not ſin, I deſerve to be <hi>excuſed,</hi> rather then <hi>cenſured;</hi> if I uſe them it is poſſible I may ſinne, it may be they are not ſinnefull; yet I am not ſo ſure of it that I ſhall not ſinne if I uſe them, as I am ſure I ſhall not ſinne, nor breake any of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements if I doe not uſe them. This I may be bold to build upon, He that <hi>ſayles</hi> amongſt <hi>Rocks,</hi> it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he may eſcape <hi>ſplitting,</hi> but he is not ſo ſure to keep his <hi>Veſsell</hi> ſafe, and whole, as he that ſayles in a cleare <hi>Sea,</hi> where no Rocks are at all.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>But to ſpeake really, and as the truth is, Why doe they uſe all theſe</hi> diſcouragements?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> Their onely <hi>aime</hi> is, to make us ſquare <hi>our lives</hi> according to <hi>their Rule;</hi> as that Gyant did proportion the bodies of all his gueſts, to the bed of his Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot; Yea, if they would give their tongues liberty to acquaint us with their hearts and conſciences, they muſt needs confeſſe, that they uſe that odious nickname
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:153780:41"/>(deviſed by Satan himſelfe) for no other end, but to flout men out of their faith and holy profeſſion, and to bring the very truth of Religion, and power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe into contempt and ſcorne.</p>
               <p>And indeed, whom not heroicall in fortitude (the caſe ſtanding as it doth) would it not diſcourage and beat backe to the world? But thankes be given to God, his Spirit herein ſo hardeneth and ſteeleth his ſervants, that their faces are like flint, and themſelves like bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen walls, and defenced Cities, though otherwiſe ſoft in affection, and true profeſſors of meekneſſe.</p>
               <p>Yea, undoubtedly he muſt be more then man (that is, more ſpirit then fleſh) that can contentedly make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe contemptible to follow <hi>Chriſt,</hi> be pointed at for <hi>ſingularity,</hi> endure ſo many baſe and vile nicknames, as are every where caſt upon the conſcionable (for there is ſcarce a houſe, but is haunted with theſe kind of ſpirits, familiars, viſible and carnall Devils, ſoule-murtherers) have his religion judged Hypocriſie; his Chriſtian prudence, craft and policy; his godly ſimplicity, ſillineſſe; his zeale, madneſſe; his punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all obedience to Gods Lawes, rebellion to Princes, his contempt of the world, ignorance; his godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, dumpiſhneſſe, &amp;c. For theſe and the like, asun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable froſts, nip all gracious offers and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings in the bud, and as much as in them lyeth, with <hi>Herod</hi> labour to kill <hi>Chriſt</hi> in young profeſſors. Yea, the cenſures and ſcoffes of theſe Atheiſts and World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, like the blaſts of Rams-hornes before the wals of <hi>lerico,</hi> lay all the ſtrength of a young begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vertues leavell at one utterance: yea, it is the onely <hi>Remora</hi> and greateſt cauſe of arreſt, if any looke heaven-ward, that makes them recoyle.</p>
               <p>True, a wiſe man will not be ſcoft out of his money,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:153780:42"/>nor a juſt man be flouted out of his faith; Yea, like <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> he will hold his profeſſion, though hee looſe his head for it. If <hi>Chriſt</hi> have but once poſſeſt the affections, there is no diſpoſſeſſing him againe. The league that Heaven hath made, Hell wants power to breake. If the ſweet doctrine of <hi>Chriſt</hi> be once gotten into the heart, it cannot be got out againe by all the torments which wit and cruelty can deviſe, as we ſee in the Martyrs.</p>
               <p>Neither would he ever endure a blow, who cannot concoct a foule word. Hee that is diſcouraged and made returne with an <hi>Iſhmaelitiſh perſecution</hi> of the tongue: how would he endure a <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſitian,</hi> or thoſe <hi>Marian times?</hi> He that is ſo frighted with a ſquib, how would he endure the mouth of a Cannon? But to proceed.</p>
               <p>For a man to be ſcoft out of his goodneſſe, by thoſe that are lewd, is all one, as if a man that ſeeth ſhould blind-fold himſelfe, or put out his eyes, becauſe ſome blind wretches revile and ſcoffe at him for ſeeing: or as if one that is ſound of limbes, ſhould limpe, or maime himſelfe, to pleaſe the Criple, and avoid his taunts. For my part, I had rather live hated of all men for goodneſſe, then be beloved of all for vice; and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſe one good man, then content a thouſand bad ones; his ſingle authority being ſufficient to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervayle the diſdaine of a whole Parriſh of ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts.</p>
               <p>Yet experience ſhewes, That divers are content to be <hi>miſled</hi> with the <hi>multitude,</hi> rather then be an object of their <hi>ſcorne</hi> and <hi>diriſion.</hi> Yea, thouſands hold it the beſt and ſafeſt way, in differences of religion, without further queſtion, to take the ſtronger part; that ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the moſt doe, they may have the feweſt to finde
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:153780:42"/>fault with them, and all through baſe cowardlineſſe, which baſhfull devil never leaves a great many, ſo long as they live; whereby with the rich man, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. they never thinke of heaven, till tormented in the flames of hell.</p>
               <p>Whereas Satan formerly aſſaulted the Church by <hi>violence,</hi> now he doth it by deceit: and certainly the devill gets more by ſuch diſcouragements, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches that are caſt upon religion, then hee did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly by fiere and Faggot; for then the <hi>blood of the Martyrs</hi> was found to be the <hi>ſeed of the Church,</hi> others (Phenix-like) ſpringing out of their aſhes, whereas now multitudes of ſoules are ſcoft out of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by wicked men. But I grieve to ſee how they wrong themſelves, in thus wronging others: for in that wicked men doe ſo mocke and deride ſuch as are in love with heavenly things, it is hard to ſay whether they doe moſt offend in hindering the honour of God thereby, or their neighbours welfare, or their owne ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Alas, ſome men will better abide a ſtake, then ſome others can a mocke. <hi>Zedikiah</hi> was willing to harken to the Prophets, counſell, but that this lay in his way, the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> would mocke him, <hi>Ier.</hi> 38.10. it was death to him to be mock'd. A generous nature is more wounded with the tongue, than with the hand: yea, above hell there is not a greater puniſhment, then to become a <hi>Sannio,</hi> a ſubject of ſcorne, as <hi>Sampſon,</hi> I doubt not, found. <hi>Alcibiades</hi> did profeſſe, That neither the proſcription of his goods, nor his baniſhment, nor the wounds received in his body, were ſo grievous to him as one ſcornfull word of his enemy <hi>Cteſiphon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou thinkeſt not <hi>tongue-taunts</hi> to be <hi>perſecution,</hi> but thou ſhalt once heare it ſo pronounced in thy bill of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:153780:43"/>inditement. <hi>Iſhmael</hi> did but flout <hi>Iſaak,</hi> yet S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he <hi>perſecuted him, Gal.</hi> 4.29. God calls the ſcorning of his ſervants by no better a name, then <hi>perſecution.</hi> And what ever thou conceiveſt of it, let this fault be as far from my ſoule, as my ſoule from hell.</p>
               <p>And thus you ſee, That nothing but goodneſſe is the whetſtone of their malice; which being ſo, are not wee heatheniſh Chriſtians? What honour of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is there amongſt us, where Religion makes one contemptible? Is this Chriſtian-like? Such men may be Chriſtians in ſhew, or name, but they are divels indeed (however they flatter themſelves) reſembling the high Prieſts, Scribes, and Phariſees, who called themſelves the Church, while they went about to kill the head of the Church: who the ſame night that <hi>Chriſt</hi> inſtituted the Sacrament, and conſulted how to ſave them, did conſult how they might deſtroy him; yea, let any indifferent ſtander by, judge whether thou beeſt not bottomleſſely ill, who doeſt malice goodneſſe in others, who art diſpleaſed with us, becauſe we pleaſe God, and murmureſt like the Scribes and Phariſees at the ſame things, whereat the Angels rejoyce: For none but a <hi>Cayne,</hi> or a Divell in conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will envie, <hi>becauſe his owne workes are evill, and his brothers good.</hi> They are deſperately wicked, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure ſo much as the ſight of godlineſſe: as hee was fearefully idle, that <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeakes of, whoſe ſides would ach to ſee another worke: Neither couldeſt thou doe ſo, if the divell were not in thine heart. And ſo much touching the third difference betweene the ſeed of the Serpent, and the Seed of the woman.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, as they hate and perſecute the godly, becauſe they doe wel: ſo likewiſe, becauſe they <hi>fare well,</hi> and are <hi>accepted</hi> before them. As why was <hi>Cayne</hi> wroth with his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> and after ſlew him, as
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:153780:43"/>affirmeth the holy Ghoſt, but becauſe, <hi>The Lord had reſpect unto Abel, and to his offering: but unto Cain and his offering, he had no reſpect? Gen.</hi> 4.4, 5. Why did <hi>Eſau</hi> hate <hi>Iacob,</hi> and purpoſe to kill him, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the bleſſing wherewith his father bleſſed him? <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.41. <hi>Iſaacs</hi> bleſſing bred <hi>Eſaus</hi> hate. Again, Wherefore did the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> and <hi>Abimelek</hi> envie <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſtop up his wels, and baniſh him from them, but becauſe the Lord ſo abundantly bleſſed <hi>Iſaac,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.12. to 18 Wherefore did <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren hate him, not being able to ſpeak peaceably unto him, and after ſell him into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> but becauſe his father more favoured him, and they feared he ſhould reigne over them? <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.4. If <hi>Ioſeph</hi> be his fathers darling, he is his brethrens eye-ſore. Wherefore did <hi>Saul</hi> perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute <hi>David,</hi> and purſue after him from place to place to take away his life, but becauſe he was ſo praiſed and preferred of the people before himſelf, and, <hi>The Lord was with David, and proſpered him in every thing he took in hand,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.12, 13, 28, 29. <hi>Davids</hi> ſucceſſe is <hi>Sauls</hi> vexation: yea, he findes not ſo much pleaſure in his king dome, as vexation in the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>David.</hi> And laſtly, (for I paſſe by the elder brothers envie in the Parable againſt his younger brother, when his father ſo royally entertained him at his return, <hi>Lu.</hi> 15.28. which is meant of the <hi>Iewes</hi> envying the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> converſion; and many the like inſtances) Why was <hi>Eliah</hi> wroth with his younger brother, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.28. but becauſe he ſhould be more exalted? And I doubt me, whether <hi>Davids</hi> brethren were more glad, that <hi>Goliah</hi> was ſlain, or angry that he was ſlain by their brother: for envie is ſick, if her neighbour be well; and the good mans honour, is the envious
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:153780:44"/>mans torment; as it fared between <hi>Haman</hi> and <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai:</hi> as hereafter the glory of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall adde to theſe reprobates confuſion, when they are driven to confeſſe, <hi>This is he, whom we once had in deriſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to apply what hath been collected out of the Word. See whether theſe examples ſure not with ſome, and not a few in our times. As,</p>
               <p>Firſt, why do a ſort of miniſters (none of the beſt) I meane ſuch as live ill and viciouſly, or preach ill and unprofitably, or both live ill, and preach ill, maligne, hate and traduce, yea, promote againſt ſuch as preach more faithfully and powerfully, and live more holily and unblameably, but becauſe God honours their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery with the converſion of ſoules, and their words are with ſuch power, that the people flock after them, as they were wont after <hi>Chriſt;</hi> while in the meane time them ſelves are neglected and diſ-eſteemed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as they ſuppoſe far greater ſcholers (for if a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter preach profitably, they will give it out he is no ſcholer, neither can they do Satan a greater pleaſure) and their Sermons more elaborate for they will be as long in the conſeption and breeding of them, as an Elephant is of her young; which being borne-onely amazeth the hearers, and makes them at there wits end with admiration, their own boſoms will tell them, that I ſpeak truth.</p>
               <p>Again, why do theſe men enveigh and preach againſt preaching? As, what needes ſo much preaching, ſay they (and all ſtupified ſenſualiſts) it was never a good world, ſince ſo many Lectures were ſet up: their was more love, and charity, and plain dealing among our fore-fathers (they mean in time of Popery) who were onely verſt in the Lords Prayer, Creed, and ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; one Sermon well remembred, and put in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:153780:44"/>practiſe, is better then ten; yea, quoth a Miniſter in the pulpit, that preacht <hi>(himſelf)</hi> once in ſix weekes, that he might ſilence his Pariſhoners, who complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for want of their daily food, you will finde this Sermon more then you will be able to practiſe this two months; and no queſtion, ſpake out of feeling; for he having lived already above five ages, could never yet put thoſe five wordes of his text into practiſe <hi>viz. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and beleeve the Goſpel.</hi> But the reaſon of this their murmuring is eaſie: Carnall worldlings cry up <hi>practiſe,</hi> to cry down <hi>knowledge,</hi> as you may ſee by their own practiſe: even as cunning Papiſts will extoll Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> onely to diſparage Saint <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This point would be further applyed, but let conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence do it; for it is a ſore that will not endure rubbing: onely this, if any man be vexed at his brother, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he fares better, and is better accepted, becauſe he is favoured and reſpected of God and goodmen, while himſelf is neglected and diſ-eſteemed of both; much more, if he belch out his ſpleene againſt the religious, becauſe they are praiſed and preferred before himſelf; let him know, that this could not be if he were not full of the venome of the ſerpent, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.10. <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.30.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this may be applied to people of the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſort. As, why do all drunkards and vicious livers <hi>hate</hi> the <hi>religious,</hi> and ſo belch out their enmitie and ſpleen againſt them, in raiſing and ſpreading of ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as they doe; but although, partly to reſcue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from contempt, and procure a contrary eſteem, by putting a foule and ugly vizard upon vertue, and decking up vice in a gorgeous and comely attire; yet chiefly, becauſe they are precious in Gods ſight, his peculiar, and <hi>choſen people out of all the world, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:153780:45"/>of God, and members of Chriſt, temples of the holy Ghoſt:</hi> yea, chiefly, becauſe they <hi>partake of the Divine Nature, and are one with the Father and the Sonne? Iohn</hi> 17.14, 21, 22. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18.</p>
               <p>This is the eye-ſore of our enemies, and let envie look her ſelfe blinde.</p>
               <p>And ſo much of the firſt Cauſe.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the ſecond Cauſe, why ungodly men</hi> hate <hi>and</hi> perſecute <hi>the religious?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Their <hi>ignorance</hi> of God, of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How is that proved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By Teſtimonies, Examples, Reaſon, and our own Experience.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, by <hi>Teſtimonies: They ſhall hate and perſecute you, yea, they ſhall excommunicate and kill you for my Names ſake,</hi> ſaith our Saviour to his Diſciples, <hi>becauſe they have not known the Father, nor me,</hi> Iohn. 16.2.3. &amp; 15.21. <hi>And again they are an offence unto us, becauſe they underſtand not the things which are of God, but the things which are of men,</hi> Matth. 16.23. <hi>And are deceived, becauſe they know not the ſcriptures, neither the power of God,</hi> Matth. 22.29. Luke 19.42.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, by <hi>Examples</hi> &amp; <hi>Reaſon.</hi> This the Apoſtle confeſſeth to have been the cauſe of his perſecuting the Church, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. Who ſo ſoon as he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned with the ſaving knowledge of the truth, changed his note, with his name, <hi>and preached that faith, which before he perſecuted,</hi> Its worth the noting, how he was no ſooner informed, but he was reformed. Now if we look upon him as <hi>Saul,</hi> we ſhall ſee what we are by generation; if we look upon him as <hi>Paul,</hi> we ſhall ſee what we are, or ſhould be, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:153780:45"/>Neither is it ſtrange, that the men of the world through ignorance, ſhould hate and perſecute the members of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> for upon the ſame ground, they even crucified <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, <hi>Father forgive them,</hi> ſaith he of his murtherers, <hi>for they know not what they do.</hi> And why have <hi>the kings of the earth, in all ages banded themſelves together againſt the Lord, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Chriſt,</hi> Pſal. 2.2. But becauſe they knew him not. John 15.21. For if the Princes of this world <hi>had known, they would not have cruciſied the Lord of glory,</hi> as the holy Ghoſt ſpeakes, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8.</p>
               <p>Yea, if we conſider it rightly, we ſhall finde, that ignorance is the cauſe of all ſin. Sin indeed at the firſt was the cauſe of ignorance, but now ignorance is the cauſe of ſin: <hi>Swearing, and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and whoring abound,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>becauſe there is no knowledge of God in the land,</hi> Hoſ. 4.1.2. <hi>It is a people that do erre in their hearts,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>why? becauſe they have not known my wayes,</hi> Pſal. 95.10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, <hi>Experience</hi> proves, that none are ſo far tranſported with a mad &amp; ſuperſtitious zeal againſt the religious, as the rude rabble who can yeeld no other reaſon, or confeſſion of their faith, if they be asked, than this, that they are no puritanes, or that they hate a Puritane from their ſoules; when as the devill him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who hates the Puritane they meane moſt of any, can make as good a confeſſion of his faith as this. For who are the greateſt cenſurers, and the violenteſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of goodneſſe, are not the ignorant fry, who have more rage then reaſon? and the more ſottiſh ſtill the more inſolent.</p>
               <p>As, reprove one of them for ſwearing, or drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or uniuſt dealing, or for prophaning the Lords day, for Atheiſme, and the like, you are ſure to be bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:153780:46"/>with the odious title of Puritane, yea you are factious and ſchiſmaticall, if ye will not be drunk, and every whit as lewd as they are.</p>
               <p>It is worth a large ſmile, to obſerve what a cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour the blundering rabble will make againſt the people of God, if one in their company but mention the word <hi>Puritane,</hi> or tell them how ſcrupulous &amp; preciſe ſuch an one is. O what a number of ſharp and deadly arrows will each of them ſhoot, both at the good and goodneſſe, maugre all admonition! For each being ſtung with the Gad-flie of miſ-governed zeal, as <hi>Paul</hi> was before he knew <hi>Christ,</hi> they preſume to affirm with incredible impudence, accompanied with invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible ignorance, that there are not worſe men in the world then the religious.</p>
               <p>Wherein it is hard to ſay, whether ignorance or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice do more abound: whether it be more out of the ſtrength of will, or weakneſſe of judgement.</p>
               <p>It is the nature of ignorant and carnall men (that walk after the fleſh in the luſts of uncleanneſſe, whom Saint <hi>Peter</hi> calls <hi>brute beaſts, led with ſenſuallity</hi>) <hi>to ſpeak evill of the things which they underſtand not,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. Eſpecially in judging acts of zeal and piety, their opinion ſtill lights upon the worſt ſenſe, like them in the ſecond of the <hi>Acts,</hi> who mocked the Apoſtles when they were filled with the holy Ghoſt, and hearing them ſpeak languages, which they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not, cried out, <hi>Theſe men are drunk with new wine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Untill we be born again, we are like <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> who <hi>knew not what it was to be born again, Iohn</hi> 3.4. Untill we become zealous our ſelves, we are like <hi>Feſtus,</hi> who thought <hi>zeale madneſſe, Acts</hi> 26.24. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we be humble our ſelves, we are like <hi>Michal,</hi> who
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:153780:46"/>mocked <hi>David</hi> for his humility, and thought him a <hi>foole,</hi> for <hi>dancing before the Arke,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.16. Yea, to ſuch as ſhall periſh, or are for the preſent in a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing condition, all religion ſeemes fooliſhneſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18.</p>
               <p>And thus you ſee in groſſe, that <hi>Ignorance</hi> is a main cauſe of hatred and perſecution. We ſhall more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerne how it comes to be ſo, if we note The
<list>
                     <item>Root, <hi>Ignorance,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Stem, <hi>Suſpition,</hi> or <hi>Iealouſie,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sap, <hi>Hatred,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Fruit, <hi>Perſecution,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> ſeverally, and apart; for <hi>ignorance</hi> cauſeth <hi>Suſpition;</hi> and <hi>Suſpition, Hatred;</hi> and <hi>Hatred, Perſecution.</hi> But I cannot ſtand upon theſe.</p>
               <p>Que. <hi>If</hi> Ignorance <hi>be ſuch a generall cauſe of hatred and perſecution, as you have ſhewne, What is the reaſon, that ſo many great Scholers and wiſemen do alſo hate and perſecute the godly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Great ſcholers they may be, and wiſe men alſo, in the worlds eſteem, but in the maine, and in Gods account they are nothing ſo: for admit they have inlightned heads, ſufficient to leave them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe, yet becauſe they <hi>withhold the truth in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe,</hi> and do not glorifie God with there <hi>knowledge,</hi> neither are thankfull, but <hi>become vain in their imaginations, their fooliſh hearts are darkned; and ſo while they profeſſe themſelves to be wiſe, in changing the truth of God into a lie, they become fooles,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it, by thus hating God and his children, <hi>Romans</hi> 1.18.21.22.25.30. So that <hi>Ignorance</hi> is the cauſe even in them alſo.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:153780:47"/>
               <p>And indeed if they were wiſe, they would foreſee the torments of hell, and prevent them, as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaks. Or if they knew God, they would keep his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>for herby,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn, is it known that we know god, if we keep his Commandments,</hi> 1. John 2.3. <hi>but he that ſaith I know him, and yet keepeth not his Commandments, is a lyar, and there is no truth in him,</hi> Ver. 4. Yea, theſe have ſworne to keep the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to deny the world, and yet are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with there own diſobedience, unleſſe they caſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſions upon them that obey.</p>
               <p>Again thirdly, if they knew <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they could not but love him; and loving him, they muſt needes love his members, not perſecute them; for it is the very firſt part of our converſion, <hi>to love them that love God,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.14. &amp; 4.7.8 and <hi>Ioh</hi> 13.35. But ſo many as are <hi>enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> ſhew that they never knew God in <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for their wiſdom and learning; you muſt know that men may be exquiſitely wiſe, and incomparably learned in the worlds opinion, and yet very fooles in Gods account, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.19. As ſharp-eyed as Eagles in the things of the earth, and yet as blinde as Beetles in the matters of heaven. And knowledge conſiſteth not ſo much in the quantity, as in the quality: not in the greatneſſe, but in the goodneſſe of it. For as a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle precious ſtone is of more worth then many other ſtones of greater bulk: ſo one drop of wiſdom guided by the fear of God, is more worth then all humane learning. One ſparke of ſpirituall, experimentiall and ſaving knowledge, is worth a whole flame of ſecular wiſdom and learning. One ſcruple of holineſſe, one dram of faith, one grain of grace, is more worth then many pounds of naturall parts.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:153780:47"/>
               <p>But learning and grace do not alwayes keep com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany together. Yea, O Lord, how many are there, that have a depth of knowledge, yet are not ſoul-wiſe! That have a Library of Divinity in there heads, and not ſo much as the leaſt Chatechiſme in their conſciences? no rare thing for men to abound in ſpeculation, and be barren in devotion: to have full braines, and empty hearts; clear judgements, and defiled affections; flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent tongues; and lame hands: Yea, you ſhall here a flood in the tongue, when ye cannot ſee one drop in the life.</p>
               <p>For example, I might inſtance in <hi>Balaam,</hi> whom the holy Ghoſt ſtiles <hi>a fool,</hi> 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.16. And <hi>Iudas Mat.</hi> 27.3.4.5. And <hi>Paul,</hi> before his converſion, who (even while he was a perſecuter like theſe men) was eminent among the <hi>Phariſees</hi> for wit and learning, but a very Iddiot among the Aſtoſtles. And laſtly the <hi>Prieſts, Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who were matchleſſe for their wiſdom and learning, as wanting nothing, that either nature or Art could inrich them withall: yea, and they were cheifly learned in the Scripture, Gods Oracles, which will make a man wiſe, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: and yet our Saviour (who could not be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) calles them four times in one Chapter <hi>blinde,</hi> and twice <hi>fools, Mat.</hi> 23.16.17.19.24.26. Becauſe they wanted faith and holineſſe, which are the ſinewes and nerves, yea the ſould of ſaving knowledge, inlivening, feeding and ſtrengthening the ſame; for in the dialect of the ſcipture a <hi>fool</hi> is a naturall man, and a <hi>wiſe man</hi> a man ſanctified.</p>
               <p>Alas! God regards not lip-learning, and tongue-wiſdom, and braine knowledge, except it ceaze upon the heart alſo, and lead captive the affections to the government of the Goſpel, whereby we are changed
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:153780:48"/>and <hi>transformed into new men, after the image of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.12. Ephe. 4.20 to 25. Col. 3.10. except we digeſt our knowledge into practiſe, and imploy our wiſdom to his glory that gave it, our neighbours good, and the furthering of our own ſalvation: For with him wickednes is folly and the greateſt ſinner is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt fool: and he moſt wiſe, that is moſt religious, and that offends leaſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 28.28. <hi>Pro.</hi> 9.10, 12. and 11.3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14.9. <hi>Iames</hi> 3.13.17. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. And he that is truly wiſe, thinks that to be wiſdom and folly which God thinks ſo.</p>
               <p>Neither is that worth the name of knowledge which may be heard onely, and not ſeen. Good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is but the froth of wiſdom; the pure and ſolid ſubſtance of it, is in well framed actions. What ſaith the Scripture? <hi>Keep the Commandements of God, and do them, for this is your wiſdom and underſtanding before God and men, Deut.</hi> 4.6. And again, He that is a wiſe man and indued with knowledge, will ſhew it by his converſation in good works, <hi>Iames</hi> 3.13. For,</p>
               <p>Rightly, a man knows no more then he practiſeth. It is ſaid of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. that <hi>he knew no ſin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did no ſin: in which ſenſe, he knows no good, that doth no good. And certainly, they who wander in the by-paths of ſin and errour, declare themſelves ignorant of the right way of ſalvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.17.</p>
               <p>Saving knowledge of the truth works a love of the truth known; it is an uniform conſent of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and action, <hi>Ioh</hi> 28.28. <hi>He onely is wiſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, that is wiſe for himſelfe, Pro.</hi> 9.12. He whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience pulleth all he hears and reads to his heart, and his heart to God; who turneth his knowledge to faith, his faith to feeling, and all to walk worthy of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; he that ſubdues his ſenſuall deſires and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:153780:48"/>to the more noble faculties of the ſoul, Reaſon, and Underſtanding, and makes that underſtanding of his ſerve him, by whom it is, and doth underſtand; he that ſubdues his luſt to his will; ſubmits his will to reaſon, his reaſon to faith; his faith, his reaſon, his will, himſelfe, to the will of God, this is practicall, experimentall, and ſaving knowledge, to which the other is but a bare name or title. For, what is the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall ſweetneſſe of honey, to the experimentall taſte of it? It is one thing to know what riches are, and where they be; and another thing to be maſter of them. It is not the knowing, but the poſſeſſing of them, that makes rich. What ſaith one? No more then the knowledge of goodneſſe, maketh one to be named a good man; no more doth the knowledge of wiſdom only, cauſe any perſon properly to be called a <hi>wiſe man.</hi> And certainly, that wiſdom and learning is little worth, which nothing profits the owner of it, either to vertue, or happineſſe. <hi>Theſe things if ye know, happie are ye if ye do them, Iohn</hi> 13.17. So that he is the beſt Scholer, that learnes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> obedience, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp;c. He the beſt Arithmetician, that can adde grace to grace. He the beſt learned, that knows how to be ſaved. Yea, all the Arts in the world are Artleſſe Arts to this.</p>
               <p>But alas! Naturall men are ſo far from being thus learned, that not one of them doth really, and by his own experience know the chiefe Points of Chriſtian Religion; ſuch as are, Faith, Repentance, Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Love of God, the Preſence of the Spirit, the Remiſſion of ſins, the Efuſion of Grace, the Poſſeſſion of heavenly Comforts; he knows not what the peace of Conſcience, and joy in the holy Ghoſt is, nor what the communion of Saints means; he knows not what
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:153780:49"/>it is to have a certain and experimentall feeling, with a continuall proofe of Gods favour, in the whole paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of a mans life, and practiſe, &amp;c. Pro. 24.7. when every of theſe are eaſie and familiar to the meaneſt and ſimpleſt beleever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But the Word of God in divers places calls worldly men <hi>wiſe men;</hi> yea, aſcribes the greateſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and knowledge to the wicked.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw</hi> Its true, but in what ſenſe? Do ye not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that God either ſpeaks it in a holy deriſion? as, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.22. is to be underſtood: Or elſe he ſpeaks it in the perſon of the wicked, calling it <hi>wiſdom,</hi> becauſe worldly men deem it ſo: as in another place, he calls preaching, the <hi>fooliſhneſſe of preaching,</hi> becauſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked eſteem preaching but fooliſhneſſe: and as <hi>Christ</hi> calls the Phariſees <hi>just,</hi> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auſe they juſtified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.7. Or thirdly, he means the wiſdom of the fleſh, or of the world; and that is as much, as if he had ſaid in other words, <hi>fooliſhneſſe, for the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the world is fooliſhnes with God,</hi> and no leſſe then twelve times infatuated by the wiſdom of God in one Chapter, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>But to make it more plain, that no naturall man is a wiſe man, we muſt know that there is a ſpeculative knowledge in the brain, common to hypocrites with Gods children, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. And there is a ſpirituall and heavenly wiſdom, a practicall, experimentall and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving knowledge in the heart, which <hi>keepes a man from every evill way,</hi> Pro. 2.12. peculiar to the godly alone, Epheſ. 4.8. and 5.8. <hi>The naturall man,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſſe unto him:</hi> but the ſpirituall, who have the minde of <hi>Christ, underſtand all things, even the deep things of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14, 15, 16. And again, <hi>We
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:153780:49"/>ſpeak the wiſdom of God in a myſtery; even the hed wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which none of the princes of this world have known,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.7, 8. See Theſſ. 5.4 5. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence it is, that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men are ſaid to be <hi>in darkneſſe,</hi> Ephe. 5.8. Matth. 4.16. whereas the regenerate are called, <hi>Children of the light, and of the day,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.4, 5. Luke 1.79.</p>
               <p>Which compariſon is very emphaticall. For as the Soule, is the lamp of the body; and Reaſon, of the Soule; and Religion, of Reaſon; and Faith of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo <hi>Christ</hi> is the light and life of faith. Whence i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> follows, that as meer ſenſe is uncapable of the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les of reaſon: ſo reaſon is no leſſe uncapable of the things which are ſupernaturall. And as to ſpeak, is only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to men: ſo to know the ſecrets of the kingdom of heaven, is onely proper to beleevers. Senſe is a meer beaſts, reaſon, a meer mans; Divine knowledge is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Now if it be askt, Why <hi>a naturall man perceiveth not the things of the Spirit of God?</hi> Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in the place before quoted, anſwers; <hi>He cannot know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14. For if they be ſpiritually diſcerned, how ſhould they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them, that have not the Spirit? For as no man can ſee the Sun, but by the light of the Sun: ſo no man can know the ſecrets of God, but by the revelation of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8. <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.17. To know the myſteries of the kingdom of heaven, we muſt have hearts, eyes and cars ſanctified from above, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.2, 3, 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.45. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14, 15.</p>
               <p>Neither is ſpirituall and heavenly wiſdom the fruit of time and ſtudy, as the naturall is. It is not elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, nor Logicall demonſtrations, that can make us capable of it. We cannot attain to ſupernaturall and celeſtiall knowledge, by any naturall and terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriall
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:153780:50"/>means. No learning, nor experience will ſerve to know that great <hi>myſterie of godlineſſe,</hi> and <hi>hid wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> ſpoken of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8, 10, &amp;c. to know <hi>the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the glory of Gods inheritance in the Saints,</hi> to know <hi>the love of Christ, which paſſeth knowledge, &amp;c. Epheſ.</hi> 1.17, 18. and 3.19. Becauſe <hi>this wiſdom deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from above, Iames</hi> 3.17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, As none can attain to this precious grace of ſaving knowledge, except it be <hi>given them from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove:</hi> ſo it is a jewell of ſuch worth, that God gives it to none but his children the godly, and ſuch as he knows will improve their knowledge to his glory. <hi>The ſervant</hi> (ſaith <hi>Christ,</hi> meaning the ungodly man) <hi>knoweth not his maſters will, but I have called you friends</hi> (ſpeaking to his Apoſtles, and in them to all that are converted) <hi>for all things that I have heard of my Father, have I made known unto you, Iohn</hi> 15.15. <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, to a man that is good in his fight, God giveth wiſdom and knowledge, Eccles.</hi> 2.26. intimating, that he doth not ſo to the evill man. <hi>The wiſe,</hi> that is, the godly, ſaith <hi>Daniel, ſhall underſtand, but none of the wicked ſhall have underſtanding,</hi> Dan. 12.10. <hi>A ſcorner ſeeketh wiſdom, &amp; findeth it not; but knowledge is eaſie to him that will underſtand,</hi> Pro. 14.6. that is, to him that will be bettered by his underſtanding. <hi>Wicked men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not judgement, but they that ſeek the Lord, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand all things,</hi> Prov. 28.5. and 3.32. <hi>They which obſerve the Commandements, have a good underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 111.10. the reſt have an ill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and a vain; an underſtanding, like that of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> which was enough to condemne them, but not to ſave them.</p>
               <p>Thus as <hi>no man can ſee God, and live:</hi> ſo no man can ſee <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is God, ſitting at the right hand of his
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:153780:50"/>Father in heaven, ſo long as he lives a meer naturall man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. God will not powre <hi>new wine, but into new veſſels,</hi> Matth. 9.17. <hi>Christ</hi> is ſaid to have <hi>expounded all things to his Diſciples apart,</hi> to ſhew, that if we will have <hi>Christ</hi> to teach us, we muſt go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the world. <hi>If any will do Gods will,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>he ſhall know the Doctrine, whether it be of God, or no, Iohn</hi> 7.17. So that no man can learn this doctrine, but he that doth it: as no man could learn the Virgins ſong, but they that ſang it, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.3. Yea, if <hi>the fear of the Lord,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>is the beginning of wiſdom,</hi> how ſhould they have wiſdom, that have not the fear of the Lord? All unrepentant ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are enemies to God, ſervants to Satan: now we men, do not tell our ſecrets to enemies; neither will an Artificer teach another mans ſervants his trade: but the righteous are Chriſts friends, and brethren, and fiſters, and father, and mother, between whom there is a kinde of familiarity, ſo that he makes them of his counſell; <hi>His ſecrets,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, are with the righteous,</hi> Pro. 3.32. And again, Pſal. 25.14. <hi>The ſecrets of the Lord are revealed to them that fear him, and his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is to give them underſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See this in <hi>Abrahams</hi> example, <hi>Shall I hide from Abraham that thing which I do?</hi> ſaith God, Gen. 18.17. As if this were an offence in God, if he ſhould tell the righteous no more then he tells the wicked.</p>
               <p>Beſides, What ſhould he do with a talent, that will not improve it? And let a wicked man know never ſo much, he is reſolved to be never the better man. And they that are unwilling to obey, God thinks unworthy to know: which is but equity.</p>
               <p>Indeed, if they will <hi>put off concerning their former converſation the old man, with his corruptions, and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:153780:51"/>deceiveable luſts, and be changed, by the renewing of there mindes, and by putting on the new man, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God, is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe,</hi> Ephe. 4.20. to 25. Col. 3.10. 2 Cor. 5.17. 1 Iohn. 4.7. Then they ſhall ſee <hi>what the good and acceptable, and perfect will of God is,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhewes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.8. For God in the perſon of wiſdom hath made a generall promiſe to all that will ſerve him, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1. <hi>If thou wilt turn,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>at my correction, I will power out my heart unto thee, and make thee underſtand my words,</hi> Verſe 23. But elſe, they ſhall blindly go on in perſecuting <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his members, perhaps to the killing of his prophets, and thinke alſo that they do God good ſervice, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.2, 3. For <hi>as they like not to retain God in their knowledge,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>ſo God ſhall give them over to vile af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and to a reprobate minde,</hi> Rom. 1.28. And <hi>becauſe they will not teceaue the truth in love, that they might be ſaved; therefore God ſhall ſend them ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, that they might beleeve lies: that all they might be damned, which beleeve not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.10.11.12.</p>
               <p>And is it not juſt with God, to ſay, they would none of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> let them welcome Sathan and Antichriſt?</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What</hi> inſtruction <hi>from the premiſſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> As it ought to ſtop all wicked mens mouthes: ſo it may both ſerve for <hi>direction</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> to the godly, and to informe all.</p>
               <p>Firſt, If it be ſo, that all naturall men are uncapable of divine and ſupernaturall knowledge, that they are blinde touching ſpirituall things: let not any carnall wretch hereafter dare to ſpeak evill of the things, acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and perſons, which are out of the reach of his capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, but ſilently ſuſpend his judgement, untill he is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:153780:51"/>informed. For as it pertaineth not to the ruſticke to judge of Letters: ſo it belongeth not to naturall men to judge of ſpirituall things. And in matters of cenſure, nothing but a certaine knowledge ſhould make us give a certaine judgement; and in the meane time, confeſſe, that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> may know his brethren, although they know not him. Hee which is <hi>ſpirituall, diſcerneth all things;</hi> yet he himſelfe <hi>is Iudged of no man,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. that is, of no naturall man.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let thoſe that have uſed to <hi>ſpeake evill</hi> of the way of truth, learne to kicke no more againſt the pricks, leſt they bring the ſame curſe upon themſelves, that thoſe did, which brought up an evill report of the holy Land, <hi>viz.</hi> that, As they never entred into the terreſtriall <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan:</hi> So theſe never enter into the Celeſtiall. Yea, put caſe they ſhall thinke to doe God good ſervice in it: for <hi>there is a way,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, that ſeemeth right to a man, but the iſſues thereof are the wayes of death, Pro.</hi> 14 12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If all who deride and perſecute the godly, are <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> perſons, as hath beene proved; then let not Gods Children be diſcouraged, maugre all ſlander and oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; nor thinke the worſe of themſelves, if ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach them never ſo. The <hi>Corinthians</hi> exceedingly ſlighted <hi>Paul,</hi> he was this, and he was that; But what ſaith <hi>Paul? With mee it is a very ſmall thing, that I ſhould be judged of you,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4. Alaſſe! the beſt of them ſaw no more than St. <hi>Paul</hi> soutſide; the grace of his heart, the raptures of his ſoule, the raviſhing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of the inward man, and the like ſpirituall priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, more glorious than the ſtates of Kingdomes, were to theſe ſenſualiſts as a covered meſſe. And indeed, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men are as fit to judge of ſpirituall matters, as blind men are fit to judge of colours. We know little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:153780:52"/>will often laugh at wiſe men, when they are about ſerious and neceſſary affaires and buſineſſe; which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is not an argument of the unworthineſſe of the things they laugh at, but of the folly of them which laugh. Will the Merchant be diſcouraged, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Wine pleaſeth not a ſicke mans palat; when thoſe that are in health commend it, and himſelfe knowes it to be good? Much leſſe cauſe have we to be diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, having more certainety to rely upon. Our enemies have Senſe, Reaſon, and Experience to confirme their judgements; but wee have them, with an advantage of three infallible witneſſes, Gods Word, and Spirit, and Faith. Wherefore henceforward let us take our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Counſell, and ſeeke to juſtifie our judgements to the children of Wiſdome, of whom ſhe is juſtified; and not to fooles, by whom ſhe is daily crucified. Neither let any thinke the better of ſuch whom they extoll, for the blinde eate many a flye.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This ſhewes that they <hi>ſuſpect</hi> much, becauſe they know little, as Children in the darke ſuppoſe they ſee, what they ſee not. They complaine, like the Owle, of the glory of the Sunne, when the fault is in their owne eyes. They are blinde, yet the miſery is, they ſee not that they are blinde; and therefore believing that they ſee, they accuſe others of ſchiſme, when indeed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are only guilty of <hi>prejudice;</hi> as a blind man running againſt one that ſeeth, calls him blinde that did not ſhunne him. They are like <hi>Harpaſt,</hi> a blinde woman in <hi>Seneca</hi>'s family, who would not be perſwaded that ſhee was blinde; but found fault with the houſe wherein ſhe was, as being over darke.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If none are truely wiſe, but ſuch as have paſt the ſecond birth, it gives us to underſtand that the regenerate (for the moſt part) ſleepe nigh halfe their time in <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:153780:52"/>that the wicked are never awake. And if this Wiſedome commeth downe from the <hi>Father of lights,</hi> and that wee cannot have it, except God vouchſafe to give it us; It may teach us to bee <hi>bumble, Iob</hi> 42.6. And not like the Ape, that is proud of his Maſters Iacket. Heavenly notions grow not in us, we ſpin them not out of our owne breſts: And <hi>thankfull;</hi> for if they be given, let us not forget the giver.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If all naturall men, are like <hi>blind Sampſon</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his guide, not able without the Holy Ghoſts dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to finde out the pillars of the houſe, the principles of faith, let us not wonder that they ſwarve ſo much from the godly, in their judgements and practice. Is it any ſtrange thing, to ſee a blinde man ſtumble and fall? Yea, let us condole all their diſaſters, and drop ſome teares, in pity and compaſſion for their great and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous miſery.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And laſtly, If with God one ſparke of ſpirituall experimentall and ſaving knowledge be of more worth than all ſecular Wiſdome, and Learning; then ſtrive we for that <hi>knowledge</hi> which will make the knower bleſſed. Let us ſo be learned; that we may be ſaved. Let us not in our hearing, and reading, and communication, doe as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children, that looke only upon the Babyes in a booke, without regard to the matter therein contained: but like men in yeares have more reſpect to the pith and ſolidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the matter, than to the phraſe; and to the profit of our ſoules, than the pleaſing of our ſenſes. And ſo much of the ſecond cauſe.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the third cauſe, why ungodly men hate and perſecute the Religious?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Their <hi>infidelity</hi> and <hi>unbeliefe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>How doth that appeare?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:153780:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I will demonſtrate it beyond denyall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why doe the Heathen rage,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple murmure, the Kings of the Earth band themſelves, and the Rulers take counſell together, against the Lord, and againſt his Annointed, ſaying, Let us breake their bands,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 2.1. to 4. but this they thinke all wayes, <hi>there is no God, God is not in all their thoughts, Pſalm.</hi> 10.4. And againe, <hi>They breake in peeces thy people, O Lord, and afflict thine heritage, &amp;c.</hi> the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon followes, <hi>they ſay the Lord ſhall not ſee, neither ſhall the God of</hi> Iacob <hi>regard it, Pſalm.</hi> 94.5, 6, 7. And what ſaith our Saviour to the <hi>Iewes, Yee ſeeke to kill me, becauſe my Word hath no place in you, Iohn</hi> 8.37. that is, they beleeved not what he ſpake, <hi>nor the Scriptures which teſtified of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If yee will ſee it in Examples, looke 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18.35. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3 15. <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2.</p>
               <p>Or if in the New Teſtament, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 17. where the Holy Ghoſt makes a deciſion betweene ſuch as did, and ſuch as did not beleeve, <hi>Paul,</hi> when in the Synagogue he diſputed with them, by the Scriptures, opening and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaging that <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt have ſuffered, riſen againe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for faith the Text, <hi>So many of the</hi> Iewes <hi>as beleeved and of the</hi> Grecians <hi>and chiefe women as feared God, joyned themſelves in company with</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Silas. <hi>But thoſe that beleeved not, mooved with envie, tooke unto them certaine Vagabonds, and wicked fellowes, with the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and made a tumult in the Citie, and aſſaulted the houſe of</hi> Iaſon, <hi>drawing out him, and as many of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren as they could find, and brought them before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the heads of the City, crying; Theſe are they which have ſubverted the State of the world, and they all doe againſt the decrees of</hi> Caeſar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And laſtly, look but 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. you ſhall heare Saint <hi>Paul</hi> moſt ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:153780:53"/>confeſſing, <hi>I was a blaſphemer, a perſecuter, and an oppoſer of Chriſt; and his members; but I did it ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, through unbeliefe,</hi> v. 13.</p>
               <p>Now they which thinke, all whatſoever is written in Scripture of God, of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of His Kingdome of Grace here, and glory hereafter, to bee but a fable: as that impious Pope did, who was not aſhamed blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly to boaſt what he had gained by <hi>Fabula de Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto:</hi> And all <hi>Matchivillian</hi> Atheiſts, who think Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to bee but a Politicke device, to keepe men in awe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe, whoſe number is greater than is ſuppoſed. Theſe, I ſay, muſt needes thinke them madde and fooliſh, who loſe thereby either profit, or pleaſure, and uſe them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
               <p>True, this might ſeeme an abſurd poſition, if I ſhould preſume upon an Appeale to their owne blinded conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; for they thinke, they beleeve in God, and the Scriptures, as well as the preciſeſt: and ſo did thoſe <hi>Jewes, Iohn</hi> 5. which perſecuted <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and ſought to ſlay him, think they beleeved <hi>Moſes</hi> writings: but it is plaine, they did not, by <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s anſwer to them, who knew their hearts better than themſelves: his words are, <hi>Had yee beleeved</hi> Moſes, <hi>yee would have beleeved me, for he wrote of mee: but if yee beleeve not his wrightings, how ſhould yee beleeve my words?</hi> verſe 46 47. And againe, <hi>Yee have not my Fathers word abiding in you,</hi> for whom he hath ſent, <hi>him yee beleeve not, Ver.</hi> 38.39. So bring theſe, that perſecute any of Gods Children for well doing, to the tryall, and their owne conſcienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſhall teſtifie before God, that they neither beleeve the Old Teſtament nor the New.</p>
               <p>For did they beleeve that the godly are unto God as the <hi>Signet upon his right hand, Jer.</hi> 22.24. <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.24. Yea, <hi>as the Apple of his owne eye, Zach.</hi> 2.8. and that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:153780:54"/>whatſoever wrongs and contumelies are done to his Children, <hi>he accounts as done to himſelfe, Pſalme</hi> 44.22. and 69.7, and 74 4, 10, 18, 22, 23. and 83, 2, 5, 6. and 89.50, 51. and 139, 20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. and 9.20. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.22. and 25.45. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.17. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.45. <hi>Eſay</hi> 37.4.22, 23, 28. and 45.9. and 54, 17. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.39. and 9.4, 5 <hi>Iob</hi> 9 4. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.18, 20, 21, 23, 24, 25. <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> 16.11. 1 <hi>Samuel</hi> 8.7. They durſt not hate, revile, ſlander, deride, nicke-name and perſecute them, as they doe.</p>
               <p>More particularly, did they really and indeed beleeve God, when he ſaith in his Word, that <hi>whoſoever ſhall offend one of thoſe little ones, that beleeve in him, it were better for him, rather that a Milſtone were hung about his necke, and that hee were caſt into the Sea, Mark.</hi> 9.42. That he will <hi>deſtroy them for ever,</hi> and <hi>roote them out of the Land of the living, whoſe tongues imagine miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, and are like a ſharpe Razor,</hi> that cutteth <hi>deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, loving to ſpeake evill, more than good, Pſalm.</hi> 52.2. to 5. That hee will <hi>confound ſuch as perſecute his Children, and deſtroy them with a double deſtruction, Ier.</hi> 17.18. Yea, that he will <hi>render unto there enemies ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven fold into their boſome, their reproach, wherewith they have reproached the Lord, Pſalm.</hi> 79.12. In fine, that he will <hi>rayne upon them ſnares of fire, and brimſtone, with ſtormes, and tempests, Pſalme</hi> 11.6. and after all, <hi>caſt them into a furnace of fire, where ſhall bee wayling and gnaſhing of teeth, for evermore:</hi> when <hi>the juſt,</hi> whom they now deſpiſe, <hi>ſhall ſhine as the Sunne in the Kingdome of their Father:</hi> They durſt not doe as they doe to the godly. Yea, if they did beleeve but that one place, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.24. Where God cauſed two and fortie little Children to be devoured of wild Beares, onely for
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:153780:54"/>nick-naming <hi>Eliſha,</hi> they durſt not nick-name the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as they doe.</p>
               <p>But, alaſſe! they are ſo farre from beleeving what God threatens in His Word, againſt theſe ſinnes; that they <hi>bleſſe themſelves in their hearts, ſaying, wee ſhall have peace,</hi> we ſhall ſpeed as well as the beſt, although wee <hi>walke according to the ſtubbornneſſe of our owne wills; ſo adding drunkenneſſe to thirſt, Deut.</hi> 29.19. Yea, they preferre their condition before other mens, who are ſo abſtemious, and make Conſcience of their wayes; even thinking, that their God deceiveth them with needleſſe feares and ſcruples, as onc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rabſhakeb</hi> would have perſwaded the <hi>Jewes,</hi> touching their truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18.22, 25, 30, 32, 33, 35.</p>
               <p>Yea, how i'ſt poſſible, that any wicked man ſhould beleeve what is written of God in the Scripture, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally touching his juſtice, and ſeverity in puniſhing ſinne, with eternall deſtruction of body and ſoule? For did they really and indeed beleeve God, when he ſaith, that <hi>his curſe ſhall never depart from the houſe of the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, Zac.</hi> 5. They durſt not ſweare, yea and forſweare as they doe; much leſſe durſt they take a pride in oathing of it, reſembling <hi>Ballio</hi> the baud in <hi>Plautus,</hi> who was not aſhamed, but even proud of Carting. Yea, which is worſe, reprove a ſwearer, and he will ſweare the more to ſpite you: Which were not poſſible, if believing God, they did not, what in them lyes, give themſelves over to the Devill.</p>
               <p>Againe, did they believe, that <hi>neither fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor adulterers, nor thieves, nor murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, nor drunkards, nor ſwearers, nor raylours, nor ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, nor covetous perſons, nor extortioners, nor unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers nor no unrighteous men ſhall inherit the Kingdome of Heaven; but ſhall have their part in that lake which
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:153780:55"/>burneth with fire and brimstone, which is the ſecond death,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21 8. they durſt not continue in the practice of theſe ſinnes, without feare, or remorſe, or care of amendment. Did they beleeve, that <hi>except their righteouſneſſe doe exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, they ſhall in no caſe enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, Matth.</hi> 5.20. And that <hi>without holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe no man ſhall ſee the Lord, Heb.</hi> 12 14. with many the like, it were impoſſible they ſhould live as they doe. Yea, if they did in good earneſt beleeve, that there is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God, or Devill, Heaven, or Hell, or that they have immortall ſoules, which ſhall everlaſtingly live in bliſſe, or woe, and <hi>receive according to that they have done in their bodies, whether it bee good, or evill,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10 they could not but live thereafter, and make it their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall care, how to be ſaved.</p>
               <p>But, alaſſe! they beleeve what they ſee, and feele, and know; they beleeve the Lawes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Land, that there are places and kindes of puniſhment here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and that they have bodyes to ſuffer temporall ſmart, if they tranſgreſſe; and this makes them ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from murther, felony, and the like: but they beleeve not things inviſible, and to come; for if they did, they would as well, yea, much more, <hi>feare him that hath power to caſt both body and ſoule into bell,</hi> as they doe the temporall Magiſtrate, that hath one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power to kill the body: They would thinke it a very hard bargaine to <hi>win the whole world, and loſe there owne ſoules, Luk</hi> 9.25.</p>
               <p>But, alaſſe! if viſible powers, were not more fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red than the inviſible GOD, and the halter more than Hell, (naturall men being like beaſts, that are more ſenſible of the flaſh of Powder, than of the Bullet) the World would bee over-runne with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage:
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:153780:55"/>Whereas now, even the worſt of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents Seede, by reaſon of Authority, are kept in a meane betweene Devills and Chriſtians; ſo living like beaſts, becauſe they thinke they ſhall dye like beaſts, without any anſwer for ought they have either acted, or left undone.</p>
               <p>True, they doe not alwayes, nor at any time alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, think there is no GOD, or judgment to come. Not alwayes, for though at preſent they thinke their villany is unſeene, becauſe it is unpuniſhed, according to that in the <hi>Pſalmes, The wicked thinketh there is no GOD,</hi> and the reaſon followes, <hi>his wayes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way proſper, Pſalme</hi> 10.4, 5. yet none, as <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeakes, are ſo confirm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in Atheiſme, but ſome great danger will make them flye to the ayde of a Divine power. Extremity of diſtreſſe will ſend the propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to God: as the drowning man ſtretcheth out his hand to that bough, which hee contemned whiles hee ſtood ſafe on ſhore: Even <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> who for all his bould denying of God, at every hearing of thunder was wont to hide his head in a hole.</p>
               <p>Yea, in their greateſt jollity, even the moſt ſecure heart in the world hath ſome flaſhes of feare, that ſeaze on them like an Arreſt of Treaſon; for conſcience cannot but ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times look out of it ſelfe, and ſee what it would not.</p>
               <p>At leaſt, on their death beds they would give all the world to bee ſure what the Scripture ſpeakes of Hell were not true; though all their life they ſuppoſed it but a fable. How oft doe thoſe ruffians, that deny God at the Tap-houſe, preach him, at the Gallowes, and confeſſe that in ſobriety of ſpirit, which they oppugned in wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe. And not ſeldome are the moſt lethargized con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſo awakened ere they go to hell, that, <hi>Spira</hi>-like, they depart <hi>deſolate</hi> &amp; <hi>deſperate</hi> in &amp; into <hi>helliſh horrors.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:153780:56"/>
               <p>Proſperity doth ſo tympanize mens ſoules, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranſe them from themſelves, that they forget they hada Maker. <hi>Who is God?</hi> ſaith <hi>Pharaoh. There is no God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nabuchadnezar.</hi> What God can deliver out of my hand? ſaith <hi>Rabſhakeh. I am God,</hi> ſayes <hi>Alexander.</hi> But <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> found there was a God. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> found what that God was. <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> found, to his coſt, that there was an Almighty God, <hi>able to deliver in the Valleys, as well as on the hills. Alexander</hi> found hee was not as he ſuppoſed, and confeſt that he <hi>knew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe mortall by two things,</hi> viz. <hi>Sleepe and Luſt.</hi> And ſo it ſhall fare with theſe in the end. They that would <hi>ſtultizare in culpa,</hi> ſhall be forced <hi>ſapere in poena.</hi> Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance ſhall make them wiſe, whom ſinne hath made, and left fooliſh.</p>
               <p>At leaſt, in hell they ſhall know there is a righteous Iudge, that will reward every man according to his deeds; and confeſſe, that what they once vainely imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, was but imagined. There may be Atheiſts on earth, were are none in hell.</p>
               <p>A Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> being on his death bed, ſaid, <hi>Now comes three things to tryall, which all my life I have made doubt of, Whether there bee a God, a Devill, and whether the ſoule be immortall:</hi> it was not long ere he was fully reſolved with a vengance. And ſo ſhall you, ô ye fooles, when that houre comes, though ye flatter your ſelves for the preſent, like that deſperate Pirate, who when (ranſacking and rifling a Bottom) he was told by the Maſter, that though no Law could touch him for the preſent, hee ſhould anſwer it at the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; replyed, Nay, <hi>If I may ſtay ſo long ere J come to it, J will take thee, and thy Veſſell too.</hi> Nothing more cartaine than death. Amongſt Lawes, ſome are antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as that of divorce: ſome changed, as that of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:153780:56"/>Circumciſion: ſome diſpenſed withall, as that of the Sabboth (in caſes of neceſſitie, <hi>Matth</hi> 12.1. to 14.) but this <hi>ſtatutum eſt,</hi> that all ſhall dye, and come to judgement, it is neither antiquated, nor changed, nor diſpenſed withall.</p>
               <p>And as nothing is more certaine than death: ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more uncertaine than the houre thereof: thy pulſe may leave beating, before thou canſt fetch thy breath.</p>
               <p>Wherefore thinke not, as <hi>Lot's</hi> Sons-in-Law, that we ſpeak in jeſt, leaſt you feele the fire and wrath of God in earneſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, nor at any time doe they altogether thinke there is no God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For as the beſt faith is but like the twilight, mixed with ſome degree of darkneſſe and infidelity: ſo the moſt grounded Atheiſme, is mixed with ſome degree, either of beliefe or doubting. What ſaith <hi>David, The foole hath ſaid in his heart there is no God:</hi> in his heart he hath ſaid it, but in his heart he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver beleeved it: No foole ever thought it peremptorily; hee would faine have it ſo, he cannot beleeve it ſo: it is an opinion which he ſuggeſts to his heart, not which his heart ſuggeſts to him: and this makes him fearefull to dye, and to dye fearefully.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tully</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> an Atheiſt in his time, ſaith, <hi>Nec quemquam vidi, qui magis ea timeret, qua ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menda eſſe negaret.</hi> They that make a flout of hell, <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmant mihi &amp; tibi, non ſibi; noctu, non interdiu;</hi> their mouthes tell us ſo, their hearts doe not tell their mouths ſo. No hell, I dare ſay, if there were a generall col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection made throughout the whole world, that there might bee no Iudgement day, theſe men would bee none of the backewardeſt. Yea, if they had as many Provinces, as <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> had, they would give an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſix and twenty of them to be ſure of it. The
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:153780:57"/>conſciences even of wicked men can never bee ſo char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or over ruled, either by arguments, or the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Sathan, that they can let goe the ſenſe of a God-head. We are all borne Idolaters, and chooſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to adore the Sunne, the Moone, yea the meaneſt of all creatures, rather than not acknowledge a Deity. You may ſooner get a Conſcience to believe all the fables in the <hi>Popiſh legend,</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh Alcarou,</hi> than that this univerſall frame is without a minde,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Prima eſt haec ultio, quòd, ſe</l>
                  <l>Judice nemo nocens abſolvitur.—</l>
               </q>
               <p>So that to ſay truely, they doe not, and yet they doe believe there is a God, and a Hell: for when they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Conſcience into their counſell, they doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: but becauſe they would rather not beleeve it, they ſtifle Conſcience, ſtop their owne eares, and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their hearts with the contrary opinion: Like as it fared with the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. who when they had ſtood out that fore judgement ſeven moneths, and brought upon their god <hi>DAGON,</hi> and the whole Countrey, a very great deſtruction, and perceived, that all which were guilty of keeping and prophaning the <hi>Arke,</hi> ſuffered in the judgement, and onely they; at laſt could bring forth this concluſion, <hi>Peradventure it is GOD'S hand that ſmote us; yet, it may bee, it is but a chance that hath hapned unto us, Verſe</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>Wherein it is evident, they did halfe beleeve, and no more; Their Conſciences told their hearts there was a powerfull GOD, to revenge the prophaning of his <hi>Arke;</hi> but their hearts were very loth to give aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereunto: and ſo fares it with theſe, when they wrong and perſecute his Children. Or they may bee
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:153780:57"/>likened to thoſe untoward <hi>Iſraelites, Exod.</hi> 16. Who did in part beleeve GOD, when hee told them, <hi>If they reſerved of the Manna untill morning, it ſhould ſtinke; and that if they went to gather it on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both, they ſhould finde none,</hi> who would have thought it foule ſcorne, if one ſhould have told them, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved no ſuch thing: for all they had ſeene ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miracles, yet tis apparent, they did but halfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve him: for what elſe made them try whether hee ſpake true or no, after they were flatly forbidden? <hi>ver.</hi> 20. or,</p>
               <p>Laſtly, they are like the unbelieving <hi>Iewes,</hi> who conſidering the Oracles that CHRIST ſpake, and the Miracles which hee wrought, were forced to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie both theſe of him (for all they hated him) <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver man ſpake as this man doth;</hi> and <hi>Wee never ſaw it on this faſhion: yet this have yee ſeene, and beleeve not,</hi> ſaith Our SAVIOVR, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.36 They ſaw, they heard, they wondered, they were convinced, yet they beleeved not: therefore their owne eyes, in ſeeing; their owne eares, in heare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; their owne hearts, in wondring; their owne convicted reaſons ſhall but witneſſe againſt their unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16 9.</p>
               <p>And indeed, if they did not in ſome part beleeve a Iudgement to come, they ſhould bee worſe than the very Devills themſelves: there is no Hell, <hi>Quis Daemonum hoc aſſeret?</hi> What Devill will ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme? They know it, and feele it, <hi>Why</hi> (ſay the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to <hi>Chriſt</hi>) <hi>art thou come to torment us. before the time, Matthew</hi> 8.29.. <hi>And ſhall not men trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deny, what the Devils confeſſe?</hi> ſayes <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:153780:58"/>
               <p>Wherefore beleeve it peremptorily, ô yee fooles and madde men; yea believe it, and avoyd it, and by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to purpoſe, ye ſhall avoyd it: otherwiſe, if ye will give more credit to your deceitfull hearts, than to what the Word ſpeakes, as <hi>Eve</hi> beleeved the word of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, <hi>Adam</hi> the word of <hi>Eve,</hi> both, before the Word of GOD; God will leave you to bee confuted by fire and brimſtone; if you will not beleeve what is written, you ſhall feele what is written.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But here it will be objected, That the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edeſt man that lives, <hi>preſumes</hi> upon GODS <hi>mercy</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and thinkes he ſhall be ſaved, as well as the thiefe upon the Croſſe; yea, hee will prove by Scripture, that <hi>at what time ſoever he repents, his ſinnes ſhall be pardoned, Ezek.</hi> 18.21, 22. Yea, there is ſcarce a man on earth, but he thinkes to goe to Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, the fleſh propheſies proſperity to ſinne; yea life, and ſalvation, as the Pope promiſed the Powder Traytors; and to this the Devill ſets his ſeale: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon while proſperity laſteth, they can <hi>turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe,</hi> and even apply <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Paſſion, as a warrant for their licenciouſneſſe; and take his death, as a licence to ſin; his Croſſe, as a Letters Pattent to do miſchiefe.</p>
               <p>Yea, the Devill and ſinne ſo infatuates and beſots them, that they thinke to have part in that merit, which in every part they have ſo abuſed; to bee purged by that bloud, which now they take all occaſions to diſgrace; to be ſaved by the ſame wounds, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they ſweare by, and ſo often ſweare away to have <hi>Chriſt</hi> an Advocate for them in the next life, when they are Advocates againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> in this; and that Heaven will meete them at their laſt houre, when all their life long they have galloped in the beaten road toward hell.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:153780:58"/>
               <p>The Devill makes large promiſes; and perſwades his, they ſhall have what they deſire; yet ever diſappoints them of their hopes, as he did our firſt Parents: <hi>Diabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus menti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur, ut fallet; vitam pollicetur, ut peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But all one, their carnall hearts ſhall bee flint unto God, wax to the Devill, who blowes this preſumption into them; whereby they believe the promiſes, let goe the threatnings: <hi>you ſhall dye,</hi> ſaith God, is heard, but <hi>you ſhall not dye,</hi> ſaith the Devill, is believed, as it fared with <hi>Eve,</hi> when ſhe eate the forbidden fruit. Yea, they believe the promiſes, that they ſhall have them; but they beleeve not the precepts, to doe them; nor the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, that they ſhall ſuffer them, for their not beleeving and diſobedience; which ſhewes, that they truely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve neither. Yea, this makes it plaine, that either they beleeve there is no God at all, or elſe that God is not juſt, and true, nor ſpeakes as he meanes in his words; which is worſe: or if they doe beleeve that he is a juſt and true God, they beleeve alſo that they ſhall be puniſhed (as he threatens) for their provoking of him; and they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him, that they may be puniſhed; which is worſt of all. So that take them in the beſt ſenſe, they are but like <hi>David</hi>'s foole, which <hi>ſaith in his heart there is no God,</hi> and lives thereafter: which is never a whit ſtrange, for it is uſuall with them to think there is no God, for whom it would make that there were none: What we would have to be, we are apt to beleeve.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe, it is hard for men to beleeve their owne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe in this caſe: they that bee moſt dangerouſly ſicke, are leaſt ſenſible of their owne ſickneſſe: much more hard to make them confeſſe it; for he whoſe heart ſpeakes Atheiſme, will confeſſe with his tongue, that he beleeves there is a God, and that he is juſt, and true, and that every
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:153780:59"/>tittle of his Word is equally true: which being grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, this muſt neceſſarily follow, that God will as well puniſh the diſobedient, as reward the obedient; which in another fit they are apt enough; yea too forward to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve.</p>
               <p>For it is Satans method, firſt to make men ſo ſenſeleſſe, as not to feele their ſinnes at all; and then ſo deſperate, that they feele them too much: in the firſt fit men live as if there were no hell: in the laſt they dye as if there were no Heaven; for wicked men are altogether in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes: at firſt they make queſtion whether this, or that be a ſinne; at laſt they apprehend it ſuch a ſinne, that they make queſtion whether it can be forgiven: either God is ſo mercifull, that they may live how they liſt; or ſo juſt, that hee will not pardon them upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
               <p>But to prevent after claps, let this point be argued in the Court of thy Conſcience: ſay, whether thou art guilty, or not guilty. He that beleeves the promiſes of God, to be true, beleeves alſo the commands and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and thereupon feares God, and makes conſcience of ſinne: otherwiſe, if thou beeſt as it were a dead man, continuing under the burthen of notorious crimes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſorrow, or feare or remorſe, or care of amendment, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 2.1. If thou art of a reprobate judgement touching actions, and perſons, eſteeming good evill, and evill good, if the Devill hath ſo bewit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d thee, that thou preferreſt Hell to Heaven, and blameſt thoſe that doe otherwiſe: it, <hi>Iſhmael</hi>-like, thou mockeſt; or, <hi>Cham</hi>-like, thou ſcoffeſt at the religious, or uſeſt bitter jeſts againſt them, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 1.1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.4. If thou rayſeſt ſlanders of them, or furthereſt them being raiſed, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 4.2. and 31.18. and 35, 20. As <hi>the Red Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, Revel.</hi> 12. <hi>caſt a floud of water out of his mouth,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:153780:59"/>after the Woman,</hi> when he could not reach her with his clawes, <hi>verſe</hi> 15. Or any way oppoſeſt them; for the oppoſition of goodneſſe, gives thee the title of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which alone is the enemy thereof, and ſhewes that thou art a Souldier of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great Dragon, who goes out to make Warre with that bleſſed Seede, <hi>which keepe the Commandements of God, Revelations</hi> 12.17. theſe or any one of theſe, ſhew that thou haſt neither part, nor fellowſhip in the Chriſtian beliefe; that thou art an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, yea, an Atheiſt, which is a higher degree of infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and that thou doeſt no way differ from an Heathen, but only in the ſaying of a <hi>Paternoſter,</hi> a Creed, and, it may be the ten Commandements: Neither haſt thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more of a conſcience, than feare, which feare alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes more from the power of the Magiſtrate, than from the omnipotency of a God.</p>
               <p>But to make thy ſelfe confeſſe this, examine thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife by thy life; for infidelity is the bitter root of all wickednes, and a lively ſaith the true Mother of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Indeed if pride, ſwearing, prophaneing of the Lords Day, drunkenneſſe, adultery, contempt of Religion and all goodneſſe were fruites of Faith, then the world were full of Believers; but Faith purifieth the Heart, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. and <hi>worketh by Love, Gall.</hi> 5.6. Conſumes our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall unnaturall corruptions, and <hi>ſanctifieth the whole man throughout</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Acts.</hi> 26.18. So that our faith to G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is ſeene in our faithfullneſſe to men: <hi>Shew me thy faith by thy works,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Iames,</hi> that is, thy inviſible beleife, by thy viſible life: for the hand is the beſt commentary of the heart. What a man does, I am ſure he thinkes, not alwayes what he ſpeakes: men may ſay they beleeve the word, but certainely they would never ſpeake as they ſpeake, think as they think, do as they do, if they thought that their thoughts, words, and deeds, ſhould come to Iudgement.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:153780:60"/>
               <p>If men beleeved that heaven were ſo ſweet, and hell ſo intolerable, as the word makes them, they would be more obedient upon earth; the voluptuous would not ſay, with <hi>Eſau,</hi> give me the pottage of pleaſure, take who will the birth-right of grace here, and glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; the Covetous would not ſay, Take you heaven, let us have mony. Ile cleare it by a ſimilitude.</p>
               <p>If a Phyſitian ſhould ſay unto his Patient, here ſtands a Cordiall, which if you take will cure you; but touch not this other Viall, for that is deadly poyſon, and he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Cordiall, to take the poyſon; in this caſe, who can choſe but conclude, that either he beleeved not his Phyſitian, or preferred death before life? But go on.</p>
               <p>If men but beleeved, that God alwayes beholds them, they durſt not ſin. No theife was ever ſo impudent, as to ſteale in the very face of the Iudge. O God, let me ſee my ſelfe ſeene by thee, and I ſhall not dare to offend thee. Againe, if men beleeved, that there is a place of darkneſſe, they would feare the works of darkneſſe. If <hi>Lots</hi> Sonnes-in-law had beleeved their father, when he tould them the City ſhould ſuddenly be deſtroyed with fire and brimſtone, and that by flying they might eſcape it, they would have obeyed his counſell. If the old world had beleeved, that God would indeed, and in good earneſt bring ſuch a flood upon them, as he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they would not have neglected the opportunity of entring the <hi>Arke,</hi> before it was ſhut, and the windowes of heaven opened; much leſſe would they have ſcoft and flouted at <hi>Noah,</hi> while he was building it: ſo if you did firmely beleeve what the Scripture ſpeakes of hell, you would need noe intreaties to avoid it: yea, caſt but your eyes upon that fiery gulfe with a full perſwaſion of it, and ſin if you dare. You love your ſelves well enough to avoid a knowne paine, we know that there are ſtocks
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:153780:60"/>and Bridewells, and Ioales, and dungeons, and Racks, and Gibbets for malefactors, and our very feare keeps us innocent: were your hearts equally aſſured of thoſe hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh torments, yee could not, yee durſt not continue in thoſe ſinnes, for which they are prepared: yea, if you did truly beleeve a hell, there would be more danger of your deſpaire, than of your ſecurity.</p>
               <p>Yea, had you but ſo much of an hiſtoricall faith, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the Scriptures, touching what God hath already inflicted upon ſinners; as, upon the Angells, the old world, <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah, Pharoah</hi> and the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians, Nadab and Abihu, Chora, Dathan, and Abyram,</hi> with their 250 Captaines, and many thouſands of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> together with the whole Nation of the <hi>Iewes, Hammon</hi> and <hi>Balaam, Saul</hi> and <hi>Doeg, Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> and <hi>Achitophell, Ahab</hi> and <hi>Ieſabell, Senacherib</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> the 2 Captaines and their fifties, <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Judas, Annanias</hi> &amp; <hi>Saphirah,</hi> with a world of others.</p>
               <p>Much more, if you did beleeve how ſeverely he hath dealt with his owne Children, when they ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. <hi>vizt.</hi> with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Ely,</hi> which were in ſingular favour with him; yea, with <hi>David, a man after his owne heart,</hi> and that after his ſin was remitted; it were impoſſible but thou wouldeſt feare to offend ſo Iealous a God: for thus thou wouldeſt argue, If God be ſo juſt and ſevere to his owne children, who were ſo good and gracious; how ſhall I, a wicked &amp; ungracious ſervant, that never did him a peece of good ſervice all my dayes, look to be diſpenſed withall? If the godly ſuffer ſo many, and grievous afflictions here; what ſhall his adverſaries ſuffer in hell? If <hi>Sampſon</hi> be thus puniſhed, ſhall the Philiſtims eſcape? <hi>If the righteous ſhall ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and ſinner appeare?</hi> as the Scripture ſpeakes: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.18: For thou
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:153780:61"/>canſt not Imagine, that he will deale after a new and extraordinary way with thee, and ſo breake the Courſe of his ſo Iuſt, and ſo long continued proceedings.</p>
               <p>Wherefore dally no longer with your owne ſoules. Are yee Chriſtians in earneſt? Do yee beleeve the word? or doe you not? If you doe not, yee are worſe than the Devill; for <hi>the Devills beleeve and tremble;</hi> they have both faith and feare, where as thou haſt neither feare nor faith. If you be Chriſtians, there is an hell in your Creed: if there bee an hell, How dare you tare Heaven with your blaſphemies, and bandie the dreadfull Name of God in your impure mouthes, by your bloudy oathes and execrations? How dare you exerciſe your ſaucy wits in prophane ſcoffs at religion, and diſgrace that bloud, whereof hereafter you would give a thouſand worlds for one drop? It is no light or ſlight offence, to contemne the brethren of the Son of God: but thou fighteſt againſt the very graces of Gods Spirit, wherever they appeare: and notwithſtanding thou didſt vow in thy baptiſme, <hi>to fight under Chriſts banner, againſt the world, the fleſh and the Devill, and to continue his faithfull ſouldier and ſervant unto thy lives end,</hi> as good reaſon, ſince he laid downe his life to redeeme thee, and hath ever ſince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and provided for thee; for a very Dog will fight for his maſter that feeds him: thou contrarily takeſt part with the world, the fleſh and the Devill, his mortall eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and takeſt up armes to fight againſt <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, if there be an hell, and but a tithe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem Chriſtians, who call themſelves ſo; what meanes our grinding of faces, like edged tooles, and our ſpilling of blood, like water? What meanes our racking of rents, our detention of wages, our incredible cruelty to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, our incloſing of Commons, ingroſſing of commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, our griping exactions, with ſtreining the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:153780:61"/>of greatnes, our inequall levies of legall payments, our ſpightfull ſuites, griping uſury, our bouzing and quaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing, our bribery, perjury, partiallity, our ſacriledge, ſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacall contracts, and ſoule murther, our ſcurrill prophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, coſoning in bargaines, breaking of promiſes, perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous underminings, pride, luxury, wantonneſſe, contempt of Gods Meſſengers, neglect of his Ordinances, violation of his dayes, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> when if the Word of God be true, we need no other ground of our laſt and heavieſt doom, than <hi>ye have not given, ye have not viſited,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat</hi> 25, 41. to 46. Certainely, if the tythe of us be Chriſtians, which call our ſelves ſo, there are abundance of Chriſtians in hell: For what eyes can but runne over, to ſee for the moſt part, what lives men leade? There was a woman much ſpoken of in ſome parts of this Land, that lived in a profeſſed doubt of the Deity, yea, even after Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Repentance, ſhe could hardly be comforted; ſhe often proteſted, that the vicious and offencive life of a great learned man, in the Towne where ſhe dwelt, did occaſion thoſe damned doubts in her minde. And wee reade that <hi>Linacre</hi> reading upon the New Teſtament the 5.6. and 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Chapters of Saint <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpell, and comparing thoſe rules with Chriſtians lives, hee threw downe the book, and burſt forth into this proteſtation, <hi>Either this is not God's Goſpell, or we are not Chriſtians.</hi> Let any man looke upon the lives of moſt men, and then ſay, whether the argument be not without all exceptions.</p>
               <p>It is the abſtract of Religion, to imitate him whom we worſhip: neither are wee worthy to be called Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, except wee be like him in workes: Wee are not like <hi>Chriſt,</hi> except wee doe whatſoever God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and ſuffer whatſoever hee inflicts: Now we are naught at doing, but when it comes to ſuffering, we are gone: it is the happineſſe of theſe cold times, that wee
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:153780:62"/>are not put to the hot fire, for tryall of our faith and love: if the Wheele ſhould turne, which the mercy of God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, how many would turne from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> rather than burne for him? Alaſſe! the greateſt number are like <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilius</hi> the Grammarian, who not only forgot the Letters of his Booke, but even his own name: for they not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forget what is written in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Goſpell, but they forget alſo that they are Chriſtians, and can be of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, for a neede; which ſhewes their hearts are true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of none. True, Gods ſeed is ſowne, but the Devils fruit comes up: and, like the <hi>Iewes,</hi> we bring <hi>Chriſt</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, when hee thirſts for Wine. But what a ſhame? What a prodigie is this? We are bound to praiſe GOD above any Nation whatſoever, (for what Nation under Heaven injoyes ſo much light, or ſo many bleſſings as we?) above any Creature, for all the creatures were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for our ſakes: and yet Heaven, Earth, and Sea, all the Elements, all the Creatures obey the Word of God; only men, for whom they were all made, ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rebell againſt it.</p>
               <p>The which, as it mightily aggravates our unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; ſo when time comes, it will gall our Conſciences to death. Yea, when we ſhall conſider, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath removed ſo many evills from us, and conferred ſo many good things upon us, that they are beyond thought, or ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gination; and that our recompence of his love, hath been only to doe that which he hates, and hate thoſe whom he loves, it will make us ſpeechleſſe (like him in the Goſpell, who wanted his wedding Garment) as neither expecting mercy, or daring to aske it: for know this, that thy own conſcience will once ſting thee, like an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to think what <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath given, and what he would have forgiven thee, if thou wouldſt but have repented: to thinke how often thou haſt beene invited to Heaven,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:153780:62"/>how eaſily thou mighteſt have eſcaped hell, how often <hi>Chriſt</hi> by his Embaſſadors offered thee remiſſion of ſins, and the Kingdome of Heaven freely, if thou wouldeſt but <hi>beleeve and repent,</hi> and how eaſily thou mighteſt have obtained mercy in thoſe dayes, how neere thou waſt many times to have repented, and yet diddeſt ſuffer the Devill and the World to keepe thee ſtill impenitent, and how the day of mercy is then paſt, and will never dawn againe.</p>
               <p>For the ſame Devill that now ſhuts your eyes, and labours to keepe you blinde, during the preſumption of your life, will open them in the deſperation, that ſhall wait on you at death, or in hell: As it fared with the rich man, who when he was in hell, lift up his eyes to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but never before, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.23. Thoſe ſcorching flames opened them to propoſe: Sin ſhuts up mens eyes, but puniſhment opens them.</p>
               <p>But I hope I have ſaid enough, and that thou art con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd in thine own Conſcience, that hitherto thou haſt beene a meere Atheiſt, and that through Atheiſme, thou haſt hated, reviled and perſecuted the godly: If not, truth is as much truth, when it is not acknowledged, as when it is.</p>
               <p>Now if thou doſt confidently, and without perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture beleeve what the Scripture ſpeakes of God, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, hell, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If thou beleeveſt the threatnings and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, as well as the promiſes, and if thou beareſt any love to thine own ſoule, <hi>Breake off thy ſinnes by repentance,</hi> and oppoſe the good no longer, give no credit to the fleſh, or the Devill, which propheſy proſperity to ſinne; but beleeve God and the Scripture, which manifeſtly proves, that <hi>every man ſhall bee judged according to his workes, Revel.</hi> 12.13. and 22, 12. Make not <hi>Chriſt</hi> a boulſter for ſinne, nor Gods mercy a warrant for thy continuing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:153780:63"/>in an evill courſe. Be not therefore evill, becauſe hee is good, leaſt like the fooliſh builder, thou commeſt ſhort of thy reconning; for <hi>Chriſt</hi> came <hi>to deſtroy the works of the Devill, John</hi> 3.3.8, 9, 10. And not to be a Patron of ſinne; and <hi>there is mercy with God that he might be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> not that he might be deſpiſed, blaſphemed, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.4. Yea, know this and write it in the Table booke of thy memory, and on the <hi>table of thine heart,</hi> that if God's <hi>bountifulneſſe and long ſuffering towards thee does</hi> not <hi>leade thee to repentance,</hi> it will double thy doome, and increaſe the pile of thy torments: for every day, which does not abate of thy reckoning, will increaſe it, <hi>Qui numer at dotes, numer at</hi> dren; and thou by thy hardneſſe and impenitencie, ſhalt but <hi>treaſure up unto thy ſelfe wrath againſt the day of wrath, and the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the juſt judgment of God, Rom.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6.</p>
               <p>And ſo much of the third <hi>cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt. <hi>What other</hi> Cauſes <hi>are there, why they thus hate and perſecute us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Other maine <hi>Cauſes</hi> (as they make them) are theſe Eight,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Speaking of Truth.</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.8, 17, 23, 24, 26, 27. <hi>Ier.</hi> 11.19. and 26.8, 9, 11. and 36, 23, 26. and 38.4, 5, 6. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.10. <hi>Mark.</hi> 6.16. to 29. <hi>Acts</hi> 16, 19. to 25. and 17.5, 6, 7, 13. and 18, 11, 12, 13, and 19, 26. to 34. and 21: 27, 28, 30, 31. and 22, 22, 23. and 23 1, 2, 12, 13, 14. <hi>Gal</hi> 4.16.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Miſpriſion, Acts</hi> 24.14. and 26, 9, 10, 11, 24. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.17, 18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.17, 18, 19. <hi>Wiſ.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7 14. and 13.55, 56, 57. and 28, 15. <hi>Mar.</hi> 5.39, 40. and 7.5, 8, 9. <hi>John</hi> 2.19, 20, 21. and 3, 3, 4. and 7.15, 23, 24. and 8.15, 57, 58, 59. and 9.16. and 16, 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.13. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10.11, 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5, 6, 7, 8
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:153780:63"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. to 29. and 2.7, 8, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. and 3.18, 19, 20. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17,</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Example of the multitude, Gen.</hi> 19 4. to 12. <hi>Num.</hi> 14.2.3, 10. and 16.1. to 4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.20, 25, 27, 39, 49. <hi>Acts</hi> 19.24, to 30.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Separation, Gen.</hi> 39.12. to 21. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.4, 5. and 101.7. and 119, 63, 115. <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.8. and 23, 20. <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.19. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.7. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6, 14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4.</item>
                  <item>5. <hi>The preaching of ſome Miniſters, Ier.</hi> 5.31. and 8.11. and 23, 13.14, 15, 16, 17, 21, 22, 26, 27, 31, 32. <hi>Eze.</hi> 22.25, 26, 28. <hi>Mat</hi> 9.34. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.22. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.43. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.8 and 20, 29, 30. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16, 17, 18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17. and 11.13, 14, 15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. ch. and 3.3.</item>
                  <item>6. <hi>The ſcandalous lives of ſome profeſſors, Gen.</hi> 9.21, 22. and 12, 18, 19. and 19.33, 35, 36. and 20.2, 12, 16. and 34, 13, 14, 15, 16, 25, 26. to 31. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.12. to 18. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12, 14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15. and 18, 7. and 23, 3, 14, 23, 24.25.27. and 26, 14, 15, 16, 70, 72, 74. and 27.5.</item>
                  <item>7. <hi>Flocking after Sermons, Ioh.</hi> 11.48. and 12, 19, 6, 2. and <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.24, 25. and 15, 30. <hi>Mar.</hi> 3.10. and 8.1. and 10, 1, 2. <hi>Luke</hi> 5.15. and 6, 17, 18, 19.</item>
                  <item>8. <hi>The finall cauſe is, that they may have more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany here in ſin, and hereafter in torment, Pſal.</hi> 35.4 7, 12 and 40.14. and 5.6, 6. and 59, 2, 3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.13, 15. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.52. <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.48. and 12, 10.11. and 15.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.17. and 13, 15.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But they are all ſo prolix, and yet ſo unmeete to bee abbreviated, that if I ſhould handle them, and make of all but one Volume, they would ſo ſwell the heapè, that not a few would be deprived of the whole. He will buy a Manuall, or <hi>Enchiridion,</hi> that will not buy a Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary: and he will reade a <hi>Curranto,</hi> that will not reade
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:153780:64"/>a Chronicle Hiſtory. Yea, it may happen to meet with Patients ſo deſperate, that although they acknowledge it is of abſolute neceſſity for them to be informed touching theſe things, yet having Queſie ſtomacks, if they ſee their Potion bigge, aſwell as bitter, will reſolve to ſuffer, yea to dye rather than take it. That will bee ſwallowed by morſells, and eaſily digeſted, which being taken all at once, will not onely cloy, but ſurfet. Wherefore I will reſerve the reſt, untill I ſee what returne this will make: And the rather, for that there are three Treatiſes already publiſht of this very ſubject,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sinne ſtigmatized.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Victory of Patience,</hi> laſt Edition.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The miſchiefe and miſery of Scandalls.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Part.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Wykes.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153780:64"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
